<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="50"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Solution  Section 1.1 – Propositional Logic



             Exercise

             Which of these sentences are propositions? What are truth values of those that are propositions?

              a)  Boston is the capital of Massachusetts.
              b)  Miami is the capital of Florida
                       
                    
              c)  2 3 5
                    
                       
              d)  5 7 10
              e)  x   2 11
                       
              f)  Answer this question
              g)  Do not pass go
              h)  What time is it?
              i)  The moon is made of green cheese
                    n
              j)  2   100
             Solution

                a)  This is a true proposition
                b)  This is a false proposition, Tallahassee is the capital
                c)  This is a true proposition
                                                        
                                                    
                d)  This is a false proposition since 5 7 12  10
                e)  This is not a proposition. (The truth value depends on the value assigned to x.)
                f)  This is not a proposition, it is a command
                g)  This is not a proposition; it is a command
                h)  This is not a proposition; it’s a question
                i)  This is a proposition that is false
                j)  This is not a proposition; its truth value depends on the value of n.


             Exercise

             What is the negation if each of these propositions?
              a)  Mei has an MP3 player
              b)  There is no pollution in Texas
              c)  2 1 3  
              d)  There are 13 items in a baker’s dozen,
              e)  121 is a perfect square

             Solution

                a)  Mei does not have an MP3 player
                b)  There is pollution in Texas
                c)  2 1 3  

                d)  There are not 13 items in a baker’s dozen.
                e)  121 is not a perfect square

                                                              1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Suppose the Smartphone A has 256 MB RAM and 32 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 8
             MP; Smartphone B has 288 MB RAM and 64 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 4 MP;
             Smartphone C has 128 MB RAM and 32 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 5 MP.
             Determine the truth value of each of these propositions.
              a)  Smartphone B has the most RAM of these three smartphones
              b)  Smartphone C has more ROM or higher resolution camera than Smartphone B.
              c)  Smartphone B has more RAM, more ROM, and a higher resolution camera than Smartphone A.
              d)  If Smartphone B has more RAM and more ROM than Smartphone C, then it also has a higher
                  resolution camera.
              e)  Smartphone A has more RAM than Smartphone B if and only if Smartphone B has more RAM
                  than Smartphone A.

             Solution

                a)  This is a true proposition because 288 > 256 and 288 > 128
                b)  This is a true proposition, because the resolution is higher, C has 5 MP resolution compared to
                    B’s 4 MP.
                c)  This is not a true proposition. The resolution is not higher that A.
                d)  This is not a true proposition. Not necessary, the resolution in B is not higher that C.
                e)  This is not a true proposition



             Exercise

             Let p and q be the proposition
                           p: I bought a lottery ticket this week
                           q: I won the million dollar jackpot

                                                                                    
                                         
                                                                 q
                ) a    p           ) b  p q             ) c  p               ) d  p q
                                                                                             
                                                                                          
                        q
                ) e  p             ) f    p           ) g    p          ) h   p   p q
                                                                     q
                                                 q
             Solution
                a)  I did not buy a lottery ticket this week.
                b)  I bought a lottery ticket this week or I won the million dollar jackpot.
                c)  I bought a lottery ticket this week then I won the million dollar jackpot.
                d)  I bought a lottery ticket this week and I won the million dollar jackpot.
                e)  I bought a lottery ticket this week if and only if I won the million dollar jackpot.
                f)  I did not buy a lottery ticket this week then I did not win the million dollar jackpot.
                g)  I did not buy a lottery ticket this week and I did not win the million dollar jackpot.
                h)  I did not buy a lottery ticket this week or either I bought a lottery ticket this week and I won the
                    million dollar jackpot.







                                                              2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Let p and q be the proposition
                           p: Swimming at the New Jersey shore is allowed
                           q: Sharks have been spotted new the shore
                                         
                                                                
                ) a   q            ) b  p q             ) c    p q           ) d  p     q
                                                 q
                ) e    q   p      ) f    p           ) g   p      q     ) h   p   p     q
             Solution

                a)  Sharks have not been spotted new the shore.
                b)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is allowed and Sharks have been spotted new the shore.
                c)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is not allowed or Sharks have been spotted new the shore.
                d)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is allowed then Sharks have not been spotted new the
                    shore.
                e)  Sharks have not been spotted new the shore then Swimming at the New Jersey shore is
                    allowed.
                f)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is not allowed then Sharks have not been spotted new the
                    shore.
                g)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is allowed if and only if Sharks have not been spotted new
                    the shore.
                h)  Swimming at the New Jersey shore is not allowed and either Swimming at the New Jersey
                    shore is allowed  or Sharks have not been spotted new the shore


             Exercise


             Let p, q  and r be the proposition
                           p: You have the flu
                           q: You miss the final examination
                           r: You pass the course

              Express each of these propositions as an English sentence
                                                                                           
                                                                                               
                        q
                ) a  p                    ) b    q   r       ) c  q     r        ) d  p q r
                             q  
                ) e   p             r                ) f   p q    q r    
                          r
             Solution
                a)  You have the flu then you miss the final examination.

                b)  You don’t miss the final examination if and only if you pass the course.
                c)  You miss the final examination then you don’t pass the course.

                d)  You have the flu or you miss the final examination or you pass the course.

                e)  You have the flu then you don’t pass the course or you miss the final examination then you
                    don’t pass the course.
                f)  You have the flu and you miss the final examination or both you don’t miss the final
                    examination and you pass the course.
                                                              3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Determine whether each of these conditional statements is true or false.
                         
                      
              a)  If 1 1 2, then 2 + 2 = 5
              b)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then 2 + 2 = 4
              c)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then 2 + 2 = 5
              d)  If monkeys can fly, then 1 + 1 = 3
              e)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then unicorns exist
              f)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then dogs can fly
              g)  If 1 + 1 = 2, the dogs can fly
              h)  If 2 + 2 = 4, then 1 + 2 = 3

             Solution
                a)  Since the hypothesis is true and the conclusion is false, this implication is false.

                b)  Since the hypothesis is false and the conclusion is true, this implication is true.
                c)  Since the hypothesis is false and the conclusion is false, this implication is true.

                d)  Since the hypothesis is false and the conclusion is false, this implication is true.

                e)  Since the hypothesis is false and the conclusion is false, this implication is true.
                f)  Since the hypothesis is false and the conclusion is false, this implication is true.

                g)  Since the hypothesis is true and the conclusion is false, this implication is false.
                h)  Since the hypothesis is true and the conclusion is true, this implication is true.



             Exercise

             Write each of these propositions in the form “p if and only if q” in English

              a)  If it is hot outside you buy an ice cream cone, and if you buy an ice cream cone it is hot outside.
              b)  For you to win the contest it is necessary and sufficient that you have only winning ticket.
              c)  You get promoted only if you have connections, and you have connections only if you get
                  promoted.
              d)  If you watch television your mind will decay, and conversely.
              e)  The trains run late on exactly those days when I take it.
              f)  For you to get an A in this course, it is necessary and sufficient that you learn how to solve
                  discrete mathematics problems.
              g)  If you read the newspaper every day, you will be informed, and conversely.
              h)  It rains if it is a weekend day, and it is a weekend day if it rains.
              i)  You can see the wizard only if the wizard is not in, and the wizard is not in only if you can see
                  him

             Solution

                a)  You buy an ice cream cone if and only if it is hot outside.
                b)  You win the contest if and only if you hold the only winning ticket.

                c)  You get promoted if and only if you have connection.
                                                              4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[d)  Your mind will decay if and only if you watch television.

                e)  The trains run late if and only if you watch television.

                f)  For you to get an A in this course if and only if you learn how to solve discrete mathematics
                    problems.


             Exercise

             Construct a truth table for each of these compound propositions.

              a)  p    p                    i)   p    q         p    o)   p   q          q
                                                                                            p 
                                                               q
              b)  p   p                     j)   p    q   q    p      p)   p q    r
                                                                                      
              c)  p     p                   k)  p    p q                   q)   p q    r
                                                            
                                                                                      
                                                         
              d)  p     p
                                                                  
                                                        
                                                                                      
                                                     
                                                               
              e)  p     q                   l)   p q     p q              r)   p q    r
                                                                                      
              f)    p   q                   m)  q      p   p    q    s)   p q    r
                                                                                         
                                                                                      
                                                           p 
              g)   p     q               n)   p  q           q       t)   p q 
                                                                                              r
                              q
                        
                                   
              h)   p q      p q
                     
                               
             Solution
                  a)                              b)                              c)

                       p    p      p   p            p    p      p   p            p     p        p   p
                      T      F         F              T      F         T               T      F        F
                      F      T         F               F     T         T               F     T         T
                  d)                              e)                              f)

                       p    p        p   p       p     q    q        p   q    p     q    q        p  q
                      T      F         F            T     T     F        F          T     T     F        F
                      F      T         F            T     F     T        T          T     F     T        T

                                                    F     T     F        T          F     T     F        T
                                                    F     F     T        T          F     F     T        F

                  g)                                             h)

                                                                                                             
                                                                                      
                                                                             
                                                                                                        
                     p   q   q   p     q    p  q  q        p   q   p q   p q    q          p q
                                                                                              p
                     T  T     F       T             T              T  T      T        T              T
                     T   F    T       T             F              T   F     T        F              F
                     F  T     F        F            T              F  T      T        F              F
                     F   F    T       T             F              F   F     F        F              T






                                                              5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[i)

                                                                                      
                                                     q
                     p   q   p  q   q   p    p             q       p
                                                                               q
                                                                 p
                     T  T       T       F     F        T                  T
                     T   F      F       T     F        F                  T
                     F   T      T       F     T        F                  T

                     F   F      T       T     T        F                  T

                j)
                     p   q   p  q      q   p    p      q   q    p


                     T  T       T          T                T
                     T   F      F          T                T
                     F   T      T          F                F
                     F   F      T          T                T

                k)

                     p   q    p q     p    p q  

                     T  T       T           F

                     T   F      T           F
                     F   T      T           T
                     F   F      F           F

                l)

                                                          
                                                                    
                                                                 
                     p   q    p q       p q        p q     p q
                                                       
                     T  T       T         T                 T
                     T   F      F         T                 T
                     F   T      F         T                 T
                     F   F      F         F                 T

                m)

                     p   q   p         q   p    p   q   q      p   p    q

                     T  T     F          F           T                F
                     T   F    F          T           F                F

                     F  T     T          T           F                F
                     F   F    T          T           T                T







                                                              6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[n)


                                                                      p 
                     p   q   p       p q          p  q     p  q          q
                     T  T     F         T           T                 T

                     T   F    F         F           T                 T
                     F   T    T         T           T                 T

                     F   F    T         T            F                T

                o)
                                                                      p 
                     p   q   p       p q          p  q    p  q           q

                     T  T     F         T           T                 T
                     T   F    F         F           T                 F
                     F   T    T         T           T                 T
                     F   F    T         T            F                F

                p)

                     p   q    r      p q       p q    r

                     T  T     T       T            T

                     T  T     F       T            T
                     T   F    T       T            T
                     T   F    F       T            T
                     F   T    T       T            T
                     F   T    F       T            T
                     F   F    T       F            T

                     F   F    F       F            F

                q)
                     p   q    r      p q      p q   r


                     T  T     T       T            T
                     T  T     F       T            F
                     T   F    T       T            T
                     T   F    F       T            F
                     F   T    T       T            T
                     F   T    F       T            F
                     F   F    T       F            F

                     F   F    F       F            F






                                                              7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[r)


                                                 
                     p   q    r      p q      p q    r
                     T  T     T       T            T

                     T  T     F       T            T
                     T   F    T       F            T
                     T   F    F       F            F
                     F   T    T       F            T
                     F   T    F       F            F
                     F   F    T       F            T

                     F   F    F       F            F

                s)

                     p   q    r      p q      p q    r
                                                 
                     T  T     T       T            T
                     T  T     F       T            F
                     T   F    T       F            F
                     T   F    F       F            F
                     F   T    T       F            F
                     F   T    F       F            F
                     F   F    T       F            F

                     F   F    F       F            F

                t)
                                                          
                     p   q    r     r     p q    p q 
                                                       
                                                               r
                     T  T     T      F       T           F
                     T  T     F      T       T           T
                     T   F    T      F       T           F
                     T   F    F      T       T           T
                     F   T    T      F       T           F

                     F   T    F      T       T           T
                     F   F    T      F       F           F
                     F   F    F      T       F           F












                                                              8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Solution  Section 1.2 – Propositional Equivalences




             Exercise

             Use the truth table to verify these equivalences

                a)  p    T  p            b)  p     F  p           c)  p     F  F
                d)  p    T  T            e)  p  p   p             f)  p   p   p

             Solution

                 p      p T       p  F       p  F      p T       p   p     p   p
                T         T          T          F          T          T          T

                 F        F          F          F          T          F          F

                        hold       hold        hold       hold       hold       hold


             Exercise

                             
                          
                       
             Show that   p  and p are logically equivalent
             Solution
                 p  p     p 
                T    F      T

                 F   T      F
                                 
                              
                           
                Therefore,   p  and p are logically equivalent


             Exercise

             Use the truth table to verify the commutative laws
                              p
              a)  p q q  
                     
                              p
              b)  p q q 
             Solution

                          p   q    p q      q  p                   p   q    p q     q  p
                         T  T       T          T                    T  T        T        T

                         T    F     T          T                    T    F     F         F
                         F    T     T          T                     F   T     F         F
                         F    F     F          F                     F   F     F         F

                                    Identical                                  Identical




                                                              9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Use the truth table to verify the associative laws
              a)   p q   r   p  q r  
                                         
                     
              b)   p q      p  q r
                                     
                         r
             Solution
                a)
                                                                                
                     p   q    r     p q        p q    r    q  r     p    q r

                     T  T     T       T            T           T           T
                     T  T     F       T            T           T           T
                     T   F    T       T            T           T           T
                     T   F    F       T            T           F           T
                     F   T    T       T            T           T           T
                     F  T     F       T            T           T           T
                     F   F    T       F            T           T           T

                     F   F    F       F           F            F           F
                                          
                                       
                       
                           r
                     p q      p  q r   is true

                b)
                                                                            
                                                            
                     p   q    r     p q     p q    r   q r       p    q r
                     T  T     T      T          T           T          T
                     T  T     F      T          F           F          F

                     T   F    T      F          F           F          F
                     T   F    F      F          F           F          F
                     F   T    T      F          F           T          F
                     F   T    F      F          F           F          F
                     F   F    T      F          F           F          F
                     F   F    F      F          F           F          F

                     p q   r   p  q r    is true



             Exercise
             Show that each of these conditional statements is a tautology by using truth result tables.

              a)   p q     p
              b)  p    p q  

              c)        p    q
                    p
              d)   p q     p    q



                                                             10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[e)    p    q 
                                p
              f)       p   p q      
                                    q
                                
              g)   p   q  q     r       p    r
                  
                  
              h)      p   p    q      q

             Solution

                  a)                                           b)

                                                                                            p
                                                     
                        p   q     p q    p    p q                    p   q    p q    q      p
                                                                        T  T        T           T
                        T  T       T           T
                                                                             F
                        T    F     T           T                        T    T     F            T
                                                                        F
                        F    T     T           T                                   F            T
                        F    F     F           T                        F    F     F            T
                  c)                                           d)

                                                                           
                                                                                                       q
                    p   q   p   p   q         p        q    p   q   p q   p    q      p     p        q
                                                   p
                    T  T     F       T             T            T  T       T        T               T
                    T   F    F       F             T            T    F     F        F               T
                    F  T     T       T             T             F   T     F        T               T
                    F   F    T       T             T             F   F     F        T               T

                e)

                                           q   
                     p   q   p  q    p               p  q   p
                    T  T        T          F               T

                    T    F      F          T               T
                    F    T      T          F               T
                    F    F      T          F               T

                f)

                                                                    p
                                           q   
                     p   q   p  q    p             p    q   q
                                                                  

                    T  T        T          F                 T
                    T    F      F          T                 T
                    F    T      T          F                 T
                    F    F      T          F                 T









                                                             11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[g)

                                                                                                               
                                                                                         
                p   q    r    p q   q    r      p     q   q   r   p  r       q   r   q   p     r
                                                                                                        p
                T  T  T         T        T               T              T                      T
                T  T  F         T        F               F              F                      T

                T    F  T       F        T               F              T                      T
                T    F  F       F        T               F              F                      T
                F    T  T       T        T               T              T                      T
                F    T  F       T        F               F              T                      T
                F    F  T       T        T               T              T                      T
                F    F  F       T        T               T              T                      T

                h)

                                            q   
                     p   q   p  q   p    p              q     p   p    q

                    T  T        T           T                  T
                    T    F      F           F                  T
                    F    T      T           F                  T
                    F    F      T           F                  T



             Exercise

             Show that  p   and  p q    p     q  are logically equivalent
                            q
             Solution
                                      q
                The proposition  p   is true when  p  and  q  have the same true or false value.  Since  p  and  q
                                
                                                                                         
                                                                                                  
                are truth, then  p q only true. When  p  and  q  are false, then the negation  p  and  q  are true,
                     
                                                   
                then  p   is true. Therefore  p q            q  is true only when both are true. Therefore
                            q
                                                        p
                these two expressions are logically equivalent.

                          p   q     p q   p   q    q   p q           p     q    p  q
                                                          p
                                                                            

                          T  T       T       F     F        F                T                T
                          T   F      F       F     T        F                F                F
                          F   T      F       T     F        F                F                F
                          F   F      F       T     T        T                T                T









                                                             12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Exercise

                       
             Show that   p      q  and  p     q are logically equivalent
             Solution
                The proposition   p     q  is true when  p   is false. Since  p   is true when  p  and  q
                                                                                   q
                                                              q
                have the same truth value, it is false when  p  and  q  have different truth values (either  p  is true
                and  q  is false, or vice versa). These are precisely the cases in which  p     q is true. Therefore
                these two expressions are logically equivalent.

                                      p   q     p   q      p          q   p     q
                                                              q
                                      T  T        T            F         F       F
                                      T    F      F            T         T       T
                                      F   T       F            T         F       T
                                      F    F      T            F         T       F


             Exercise

                                   
                                           p
                            q
             Show that  p   and  q   are logically equivalent
             Solution
                It is easy to see from the definitions of conditional statement and negation of these propositions is
                false in the case which p is true and q is false the proposition is false, and true in the other three
                cases. Therefore these two expressions are logically equivalent.

                                        p   q     p q      q   p        p
                                                                            q
                                        T  T        T        F     F          T
                                        T   F       F        T     F          F

                                        F   T       T        F     T          T
                                        F   F       T        T     T          T


             Exercise

             Show that  p    q  and  p     q are logically equivalent

             Solution

                                                      
                The proposition  p    q  is true when  p  and  q  have the same truth values, which means that  p
                and  q  have different truth values (either  p  is true and  q  is false, or vice versa). By the same
                reasoning, these are exactly the cases in which  p     q is true. Therefore these two expressions

                are logically equivalent.




                                                             13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Exercise
                                                         
             Show that  p  q          r  and  p   q r  are logically equivalent
                                                      
                                p 
             Solution
                 p  q   p     r  will be true when either of the conditional statements is true. The conditional

                statement will be true if p is false, or if q in one case or r in the other case is true, when  q r  is
                                                  
                                               
                true, which is precisely  p   q r  is true. Since the two propositions are true in exactly the same
                situation, they are logically equivalent.


             Exercise

                               q 
                                                 
             Show that  p  r          r  and  p q     r  are logically equivalent
             Solution

                                    q 
                In order for  p  r         r to be false, we must have both of the two implications false, which

                                                                                                            
                happens exactly when r is false and both p and q are true. But this precisely the case in which p q
                                                
                is true and r is false, which is  p q     r  is false. Therefore these two expressions are logically
                equivalent.


             Exercise

                               q 
             Show that  p  q          r   p    r  is a tautology

             Solution
                                      q
                                                                                                  r
                Given that p and  p   are both true, we conclude that q is true; from that and  q   we conclude
                that r is true.



             Exercise

             Show that  p q    p r      q r   is a tautology


             Solution
                                 
                The conclusion  q r  will be true in every case except when q and r are both false. But if q and r
                are both false, then one of  p q or  p r     is false, because one of p or  p  is false. Thus in this
                                            
                        
                case  p q         
                             p r  is false. An conditional statement in which the conclusion is true or the
                hypothesis is false.






                                                             14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Show that | (NAND) is functionally complete
             Solution

                Equivalence of NOT:
                        p p    p

                          p    p           Equivalence of NAND
                                     p
                           p                Idempotent law
                                 p

                Equivalence of AND:
                                      
                          
                        p q     p q           Definition of NAND
                        p p
                                                                 
                                   
                         p q   p p q          Negation of  p q
                Equivalence of OR:
                          
                                  p 
                        p q             q    DeMorgan’s equivalence of OR
                       We can do AND and OR with NANDs, also do ORs with NANDs
                Thus, NAND is functionally complete.















































                                                             15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Solution          Section 1.3 – Predicates and Quantifiers




             Exercise

             Let    x  denote the statement "x  4". What are these truth values?
                 P
                                                   P
                    a)    0     b)    4      c)    6
                       P
                                     P
             Solution
                                 
                a)  True, since  0 4
                                 
                b)  True, since  4 4
                c)  False, since 7  4


             Exercise


                                                 x
                 P
             Let    x  be the statement "the word   contains the letter a ". What are these truth values?
                                
                                                                                            
                                                     
                                                                         
                    a)  orange          b)  lemon            c)  true         d)   false
                                            P
                                                                                    P
                       P
                                                                  P
             Solution
                a)  True, since there is an a in orange.
                b)  False, since there is no a in lemon.
                c)  False, since there is no a in true.
                d)  True, since there is an a in false.


             Exercise


                                                                x 
             State the value of x after the statement if    x  then  : 1 is executed, where    x  is the statement
                                                                                         P
                                                    P
             "x  1", if the value of x when the statement is reached is
                    a)  x        b)  x  1      c)  x 
                          0
                                                       2
             Solution
                a)  x is still equal to 0, since the condition is false.

                b)  x is still equal to 0, since the condition is false.

                c)  x is still equal to 1 at the end, since the condition is true, so the statement  : 1x   is executed.










                                                             16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Exercise

                 P
             Let    x  be the statement "  spends more than five hours every weekday in class,x  " where the domain
             for x consists of all students. Express each of these quantifications in English.
                                                                         
                            
                                                                                            
                                                  
                                            
                       
                                                                                    
                                                                                       
                                                                  
                                                                     
                    a)  x P x            b)  x P x             c)  x  P x        d)  x  P x
             Solution
                a)  There is a student who spends more than five hours every weekday in class.
                b)  Every student spends more than five hours every weekday in class.
                c)  There is a student who does not spend more than five hours every weekday in class.
                d)  No student spends more than five hours every weekday in class.



             Exercise

                                         x
             Let    x  be the statement "  has visited North Dakota, " where the domain consists of the students
                 N
             in your class. Express each of these quantifications in English.
                                                                                            
                             
                                                                                    
                       
                                                                                       
                    a)  x N x            b)  x N x          c)  x N   x    d)  x  N x
                    e)  x N   x      f)  x  N x     
             Solution
                a)  Some student in the school has visited North Dakota.
                    Or, there exists a student in the school who has visited North Dakota

                b)  Every student in the school has visited North Dakota
                    Or, all students in the school have visited North Dakota
                c)  No student in the school has visited North Dakota.
                    Or, there does not exist a student in the school who has visited North Dakota

                d)  Some student in the school has not visited North Dakota.
                    Or, there exists a student in the school who has not visited North Dakota
                e)  It is not true that every student in the school has visited North Dakota
                    Or, not all students in the school have visited North Dakota

                f)  All students in the school has not visited North Dakota.
                    Or, no student has visited North Dakota
















                                                             17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Exercise

                 C
                                                         D
                                        x
             Let    x  be the statement "  has a cat, " let    x  be the statement "  has a dog,x  ", and let    x  be
                                                                                                       F
                           x
                                         "
             the statement "  has a ferret.  Express each of these statements in terms of    x ,    x ,    x ,
                                                                                                     F
                                                                                      C
                                                                                             D
             quantifiers, and logical connectives. Let the domain consist of all students in your class.
              a)  A student in your class has a cat, a dog, and a ferret.
              b)  All students in your class have a cat, a dog, or a ferret.
              c)  Some student in your class has a cat and a ferret, but not a dog.
              d)  No student in your class has a cat, a dog, and a ferret.
              e)  For each of the three animals, cats, dogs, and ferrets, there is a student in your class who has this
                  animal as a pet.

             Solution
                a)     x C   x  D   x  F x
                                          
                b)     x C   x   D   x  F x
                                          
                c)     x C   x  F   x  D x
                                           
                d)     x C   x  D   x   F x
                                           
                                                 
                     
                            xD x  
                e)   xC x            xF x


             Exercise

                                             
             Let    x  be the statement "x   1 2 " x . If the domain consists of all integers, what are these truth
                 Q
             values?
                                                                                      
                                     Q 
                                                                                
                                                          Q
              a)    0Q          b)    1             c)    1            d)  x Q x
                                            
                                                                   
                        
                                                              
                                                           
                 
                                     
                                        
              e)  x Q x           f)  x  Q x            g)  x  Q x

             Solution
                             
                a)  Since 0 1 2 0  , that implies to    0  is true.
                                                    Q
                                                          Q 
                b)  Since   1   2     1 , that implies to    1  is true.
                           
                                1
                c)  Since 1 1  2 1 , that implies to    1Q   is false.
                                                                                           Q
                d)  We showed that    0Q   is true, therefore there is at least one x that makes    x  true, so
                     x Q   x  is true.
                                                                                           Q
                e)  We showed that    1Q   is false, therefore there is at least one x that makes    x  false, so
                     x Q   x  is false.
                f)  We showed that    1Q   is false, therefore there is at least one x that makes    x  false, so
                                                                                           Q
                      x  Q    x  is true.
                g)  We showed that    0Q   is true, therefore there is at least one x that makes    x  true, so
                                                                                           Q
                      x  Q    x  is false.

                                                             18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Exercise


             Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain consists of all integers
                      
                                                                     
                                            
                                                                                       
                a)  n n       n       b)  n 2n   3n      c)  n n     n      d)  n 3n   4n 
                                                                  
                   
                          1
             Solution
                a)  True, since adding 1 to a number makes it larger.
                b)  True, since  2 0 3 0  
                c)  True, since  0     0
                d)  True for all integers, 3n   4n     
                                                    3 4


             Exercise

             Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain consists of all real numbers
                                                                     
                    
                            
                      3
                                                                  
                 
                                            
                           1
                                                                                       
              a)  x x                  b)  x x     4  x 2     c)  x   2    x 2    d)  x 2x    x
                                                                        x
             Solution
                                                              
                                                      
                                                        3
                                                   
                a)  Since   1  3    1, the statement  x x   1 is true.

                                 2                    4   2 
                             4
                           1
                                  1
                                                     
                b)  Since   2    2   , the statement  x x   x    is true.
                                                                  
                                              2
                                                               
                                        x 
                           
                                                                     x
                c)  Since   x  2     2 2  x , the statement  x    2    x 2   is true.
                                    1

                                   
                          2 
                                                    
                d)  Since    1  1, the statement  x 2x    x  is false.


             Exercise
             Suppose that the domain of the propositional function    x  consists of the integers 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5.
                                                                 P
             Express these statements without using quantifiers, instead using only negations, disjunctions, and
             conjunctions.
                                                  
                a)  x P x             b)  x P x             c)  x P   x    d)  x P   x
                                            
                         
                   
                e)  x  x     3   P x      x  P   x
                                          
             Solution
                a)  The statement to be true, so either    1P   is true or    2P   is true or    3P   is true or    4P   is true
                    or    5P   is true. Thus,    1P    P   2   P   3  P   4  P   5
                b)  P   1   P   2   P   3  P   4  P   5
                c)  P    1  P   2  P   3  P   4  P  
                                                      5
                                                             19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[
                d)  P     1  P   2  P   3  P   4  P  
                                                      5
                                                               
                          
                                                                                 
                                            
                                 1 
                e)    1 3   P     2 3   P     3 3    P     4 3    P     5    3  P  
                       
                                         
                                                                              
                                                                                        4 
                                                                      3 
                                                   2 
                                                            
                                                                                                           5
                           P   1   P   2   P   3   P   4   P  
                                                               5
                    Since the hypothesis  x  3 is false when  x   3 and true when x is anything other than 3, we
                    have
                                                    5  
                    P   1  P   2  P   3  P   4  P    P   1  P   2  P   3  P   4  P  
                                                                                                  5
                    This statement is always true, since the first part is not true, then the second part must be true.


             Exercise
             For each of these statements find a domain for which the statement is true and a domain for which the
             statement is false.
              a)  Everyone is studying discrete mathematics.
              b)  Everyone is older than 21 years.
              c)  Every two people have the same mother.
              d)  No Two different people have the same grandmother.

             Solution
                        A
                    Let    x  be  "x everyone at the school"
                                                                                          
                                                                                    
                a)  Let    x  be "x is studying discrete mathematics" . Then we have  x B x , or
                        B
                      x   A   x   B x
                                    
                                                                                
                                                                                       
                b)  Let    x  be "x is older than 21 years" . Then we have  x C x , or  x  A x        C x
                                                                          
                                                                                                       
                        C
                                                                                 
                        D
                                                                                                 
                c)  Let    x  be "x has the same mother,"    E   x  two people . x  E x        D x
                d)  Let    x  be "x has the same grandmother,"     E   x  two people . x  E   x   D x
                                                                                                        
                        D


             Exercise
             Translate each of these statements into logical expressions using predicates, quantifiers, and logical
             connectives.
              a)  No one is perfect.
              b)  Not everyone is perfect.
              c)  All your friends are perfect.
              d)  At least one of your friends is perfect.
              e)  Everyone is your friend and is perfect.
              f)  Not everybody is your friend or someone is not perfect.

             Solution
                        X
                                                   Y
                    Let    x  be "x is perfect" ; let    x  be "x is your friend"
                a)    x  X    x . Alternatively, we can rewrite  x X    x

                                                             20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[
                b)    x  X   x
                c)    x  Y    x   X x
                                    
                d)    x  Y   x   X x
                                   
                e)    x  Y    x   X x
                                   
                                                            
                f)  This is a disjunction. The expression is  x  Y x         
                                                                     x  X x



             Exercise

             Translate each of these statements into logical expressions using predicates, quantifiers, and logical
             connectives.
              a)  Something is not in the correct place.
              b)  All tools are in the correct place and are in excellent condition.
              c)  Everything is in the correct place and in excellent condition.
              d)  Nothing is in the correct place and is in excellent condition.
              e)  One of your tools is not in the correct place, but it is in excellent condition.
             Solution

                    Let    x  be "x in the correct place" ; let    x  be "x is in excellent condition" ; let
                                                            B
                        A
                    C   x  be "x is a tool"
                a)    x  A    x                     There exists something is not in the correct place.

                b)     x C x      B x
                             A x 
                                           
                c)     x A   x   B x
                                  
                d)   x  A   x  B x
                                    
                e)     x C   x   A   x  B x
                                           




























                                                             21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Solution           Section 1.4 – Nested Quantifiers




             Exercise

             Translate these statements into English, where the domain for each variable consists of all real
             numbers
              a)   x   y x    y

              b)   x   y xy    y

                                                
                                  y 
              c)   x       y  x  0   0   x y  0 
              d)   x       y  x  0   0   xy  0 
                                  y 
              e)         z xy    z
                    x y
              f)         z x     z
                    x y
                               y
             Solution
                a)  For every real number x there exists a real number y such that x is less than y. Basically, there is
                    a larger number.
                                                                                      y
                b)  There exists real number x such that for every a real number y,  xy  . This is asserting the
                    existence of a multiplication identity for the real numbers, and the statement is true, since we
                    can take  x  1.

                c)  For every real number x and real number y, if x is nonnegative and y is negative, then the
                                
                    difference  x y is positive. More simply, a nonnegative number minus a negative number is
                    positive which is true.
                d)  For every real number x and real number y, if x is positive and y is positive, then the product
                    xy  is positive. More simply, a product of 2 positive numbers is positive.
                e)  For every real number x and real number y, there exists a real number z such that the product
                         z
                    xy  . More simply, the real numbers are closed under multiplication.
                f)  For every real number x and real number y, there exists a real number z such that the product
                                                                            
                         
                    x   y z . This is a true statement, since we can take  z   x y  in each case.


             Exercise
                        
             Let   ,Q x  y be the statement “x has sent an e-mail message to y,” where the domain for both x and y
             consists of all students in your class. Express each of these quantifications in English
                              
              a)    x yQ   ,x  y
                              
              b)    x yQ   ,x  y
                              
              c)    x yQ   ,x  y
                              
              d)    y xQ   ,x  y
                              
              e)    y xQ   ,x  y
                                                             22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[
              f)    x yQ  , x  y
                     
             Solution
                a)  There exist students x and y such that x has sent a message to y.
                    In other words, there is some student in your class who has sent a message to some student in
                    your class.
                b)  There exists a student x for every student y such that x has sent a message to every y.
                    In other words, there is a student in your class who has sent a message to every student in your
                    class.
                c)  For every student x in your class there exists a student y such that x has sent a message to y.
                    In other words, every student in your class has sent a message to at least one student in your
                    class.
                d)  There exists a student y for every student x such that y has sent a message to every x.
                    In other words, there is a student in your class who has sent a message to every student in your
                    class.
                e)  For every student y in your class there exists a student x such that y has sent a message to x.
                    In other words, every student in your class has sent a message to at least one student in your
                    class.
                f)  Every student in your class has sent a message to every student in your class.



             Exercise

             Express each of these statements using predicates, quantifiers, logical connectives, and mathematical
             operators where the domain consists of all integers.
              a)  The product of two negative integers is positive.
              b)  The average of two positive integers is positive.
              c)  The difference of two negative integers is not necessarily negative.
              d)  The absolute value of the sum of two integers does not exceed the sum of the absolute values of
                  these integers.
             Solution

                a)   x     y x  0    0  xy  0 
                                   y 
                                                  
                                                         
                                   y 
                b)          x   0    0       x y    0
                      x y
                                                         
                                                 2      
                                          x y 
                c)   x    y x  0   0        0 
                                  y 
                d)   x   y x y    x   y  












                                                             23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Rewrite these statements so that the negations only appear within the predicates
                                
              a)   y xP   ,x y
                                
              b)         , x y
                      x yP
                                          
              c)      y Q   y     , x y
                                 x R
             Solution

                                 
                                                  
                a)         , x y   y xP  , x y
                       y xP
                                                 
                                          , x y
                                      y x P
                                 
                                                 
                b)         , x y   x yP  , x y
                       x yP
                                                 
                                          , x y
                                      x y P
                                                                        
                c)     y Q   y     , x y    y Q   y     , x y
                                                              x R
                                   x R
                                                               x R
                                                 y  Q   y       , x y 
                                                                     
                                                 y  Q   y   xR  , x y



             Exercise

             Express the negations of each of these statements so that all negation symbols immediately precede
             predicates.
                                   
              a)          , , y z
                    x y zT x
                              
                                            
              b)   x yP   ,x y  x yQ   ,x y
             Solution
                       
                                           
                                               x y zT x
                                 , ,
                a)   x y zT x y z               , , y z 
                                             
                                           x       , , y z 
                                                y zT x

                                           x y        zT  , ,x y z 

                                                            
                                                  , , y z
                                            x y z T x

                                  
                b)   x yP     ,x y  x yQ   ,x y     x yP   ,x y     x yQ    ,x y 
                                                                  
                                                                           
                                                          
                                                     x  yP  , x y  x  yQ  , x y 

                                                                  
                                                     x y P    ,x y   x y Q   ,x y 







                                                             24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Exercise
                       
                 T
             Let   , x  y  mean that student x likes cuisine y, where the domain for x consists of all students at your
             school and the domain for y consists of all cuisines. Express each of these statements by a simple
             English sentence.
                           
              a)   T  , A  J
                                  
                                                      
              b)   xT   , x  Korean  xTx  , x  Mexican
                                                
                                         
              c)     y T Monique  y   ,   T Jay  y
                                             ,
                    x z
              d)           y x    z     T x y    ,  
                                               T z y
                                            ,
                                            
                                 
              e)         y T  , x y  T   , z y
                    x z
                                            
                                  
              f)         y T  , x y  T   , z y
                    x z
             Solution
                a)  A does not like J cuisine
                b)  Some student at your school likes Korean cuisine, and everyone at your school likes Mexican
                    cuisine.
                c)  There is some cuisine that Monique and Jay likes.
                d)  For every pair of distinct students at your school, there is some cuisine that at least one them
                    does not like.
                e)  There are two students at your school who have exactly the same cuisines (tastes).
                f)  For every pair of students at your school, there is some cuisine about which they have the same
                    opinion (either they both like it or they both do not like it).



             Exercise
                       
             Let   , x  y  be the statement “ x loves y”, where the domain for both x and y consists of all people in
                 L
             the world. Use quantifiers to express each of these statements.
              a)  Everybody loves Jerry.
              b)  Everybody loves somebody.
              c)  There is somebody whom everybody loves.
              d)  Nobody loves everybody.
              e)  There is somebody whom Lois does not love.
              f)  There is somebody whom no one loves.
              g)  There is exactly one person whom everybody loves.
              h)  There are exactly two people whom L loves.
              i)  Everyone loves himself or herself.
              j)  There is someone who loves no one besides himself or herself.

             Solution
                                  
                a)   x L  ,x  Jerry
                                 
                b)    x y L   ,x  y

                                                             25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[
                c)    y x L  , x  y
                      
                                  
                d)         , x  y
                       x y L
                                   
                e)    x  L Lois  x
                       
                                ,
                                  
                f)         , x  y
                     x y  L
                                                              
                       
                                  
                g)     y L  , y  x     z  w L  , w  z     x
                     x
                                                          z
                h)   x   y x   y  L   , xL    L   , y L      z L L , z   z   x z   y 
                              
                i)   x L  , x  x
                                  
                j)      L  , x  y     y
                     x y
                                      x


             Exercise

                                                                                                         
                 S
                                                                                                  A
             Let    x  be the predicate “x is a student,”    x  the predicate “x is a faculty member,”   , x y  the
                                                       F
             predicate “x has asked y a question,” where the domain consists of all people associated with your
             school. Use quantifiers to express each of these statements.
              a)  Lois asked Professor Fred a question.
              b)  Every student has asked Professor Fred a question.
              c)  Every faculty member has either asked Professor Fred a question or been asked a question by
                  Professor Miller.
              d)  Some student has not asked any faculty member a question.
              e)  There is a faculty member who has never been asked a question by a student.
              f)  Some student has asked every faculty member a question.
              g)  There is a faculty member who has asked every other faculty member a question.
              h)  Some student has never been asked a question by a faculty member.
             Solution
                      
                a)  A Lois        . Fred 
                           , Prof
                b)     x S   x   A x    . Fred 
                                   , Prof
                             A
                c)     x F x      , Prx    of  . Fred  A  Prof . Miller  x 
                                                                    ,
                          
                                                                 
                    
                                                           
                d)   x S x      y F   y   A  , x  y  or  x S x    y F   y   A  , x  y 

                e)     x F    x    y S   y   A  ,y  x 
                f)     x S   x    y F   y   A  , x  y 

                       
                g)   x F    x     y F   y     x   A  ,x  y 
                                            y
                h)   x S x       y F   y   A  ,y  x 






                                                             26]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Express each of these system specifications using predicates, quantifiers, and logical connectives, if
             necessary.
              a)  Every user has access to exactly one mailbox.
              b)  There is a process that continues to run during all error conditions only if the kernel is working
                  correctly.
              c)  All users on the campus network can access all websites whose url has a .edu extension.
             Solution

                                   
                                                                             
                a)           A u  m    n n   m   A  , u  n  , where   , u  m  means that user u has access to
                      y m
                               ,
                                                                      A
                    mailbox m.
                                                                                  
                b)   p   e H   e  S  , p  running    S kernel  working correctly , where    e  means that
                                                                                           H
                                                               ,
                                                          
                                                    S
                    error condition e is in effect and   , x  y  means that the status of x is y.
                                               
                                                               
                                    
                c)   u   s E  , s  edu   A  , u  s , where   , s x  means that website s has extension x, and
                                                         E
                           
                    A  , u  s  means that user u can access website s.

             Exercise
             Translate each of these nested quantifications into an English statement that expresses a mathematical
             fact. The domain in each case consists of all real numbers
              a)   x   y x     y
                            y
              b)   x       y  x  0   0   x y  0 
                                  y 
                                                
              c)   x      y  x   0   0     0 
                                         x y 
                                 y 
              d)   x       y  x  0   0   xy   0 
                                  y 

             Solution
                a)  There exists an additive identity for all real numbers
                b)  A non-negative number minus a negative number is greater than zero.
                c)  The difference between two non-positive numbers is not necessarily non-positive (i.e. can be
                    positive)
                d)  The product of two non-zero numbers is non-zero if and only if both factors are non-zero



             Exercise

             Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain for all variables consists of all
             integers
                                 
              a)   n m  n    2    m

              b)   n m  n m      2 



                                                             27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[c)       n m      0
                            
                    n m
              d)       nm  m 
                    n m
                           2   2    
              e)             m   5
                    n m  n 
                           2   2    
                    n m  n 
              f)             m   6

                                        
                           
              g)       n m   4    n m     1
                    n m
                                        
              h)       n m   4    n m     2
                           
                    n m
                                m n  
              i)   n m p  p     2
             Solution
                                                                                                 2
                a)  No matter how large n might be, we can always find an integer m bigger than  n . This is
                                        
                    certainly true, i.e.  m n   2  1.
                b)  There is an n that is smaller than the square of every integer. This statement is true since we
                    could take  n     1, and then n would be less than every square, since squares are always greater
                    than or equal to 0.
                c)   The order of quantifiers: m is allowed to depend on n. since we can take  m     n , this
                    statement is true.
                d)  Clearly  n  1, so the statement is true.
                e)  n   2  m   2  5  has a solution over the integers. This is true statement, since  n   1, m    and
                                                                                                        2
                    vice versa (8 solutions).
                f)  n   2  m   2  6 there is no integer solution. Therefore this statement is false.

                g)  There is a unique solution for the statement n m  4, n m    1 , namely  n   5  and m   3 .
                                                                 
                                                                           
                                                                                                2          2
                    Since there do not exist integers that make the equations true, the statement is false.
                h)  There is a unique solution for the statement n m   4, n m     2 , namely  n   3 and m   1.

                    Therefore the statement is true.
                i)  If we take  n   1 and m   2  then  p   3  which is not an integer. Therefore the statement is false.
                                                        2




















                                                             28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Solution           Section 1.5  Introduction to Proofs




             Exercise

             Show that the square of an even number is an even number

             Solution
                                                                  2
                We can rewrite the statement as: if n is even, then  n  is even
                Assume n is even, thus  n  2k  for some k.
                          2
                  2
                                2
                n         4k   2 2k 2
                      2k
                                      
                     2
                                              2
                As  n  is 2 times an integer,  n is thus even



             Exercise
                                             3
                                                5
             Prove that if n is an integer and  n   is odd, then n is even
             Solution
                By indirect proof:
                                                          3
                Using the contrapositive: If n is odd, then  n   is even
                                                             5
                                                3
                                                   5
                Assume n is odd, let show that  n   is even
                n   2k   1 for some integer k (definition of odd numbers)
                                                                               
                                3
                                                                      2
                  3
                                                2
                                   5 8k 
                n   5  2k    1    3  12k   6k        3   6k   3k  3
                                                        6 2 4k 
                     3
                As n   is 2 times an integer, it is even
                        5
                              3
                Assume that n   5 is odd, let show that n is odd, and Assume p is true and q is false

                n   2k   1 for some integer k (definition of odd numbers)
                                                                               
                                                2
                                                                      2
                  3
                                3
                                   5 8k 
                n   5  2k    1    3  12k   6k        3   6k   3k  3
                                                        6 2 4k 
                     3
                As n   is 2 times an integer, it must be even. Contradiction!
                        5
                The indirect proof proved that the contrapositive: ¬q → ¬p
                                 3
                If n is odd, then  n  5 is even

                The proof by contradiction assumed that the implication was false, and showed a contradiction
                    If we assume p and ¬q, we can show that implies q
                    The contradiction is q and ¬q
                    Note that both used similar steps, but are different means of proving the implication






                                                             29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Exercise

                         2
                              2
             Show that  m   n  if and only if  m n or    m  
                                                
                                                               n
             Solution
                              2
                                            
                                                m   
                Rephrased:  m   n    2    m n        n    . Proof by cases!
                                      2
                               
                Case 1: m n       m   n 2 
                            
                                                    2
                             m  2  m 2  and    n  2    n , this case is proven.
                                      2    2 
                Case 1: m     n   m   n

                            2
                                                     2
                                            
                          m
                             m 2  and     n  2   n , this case is proven.
                  2
                                
                m    n    2    m n        n  
                                     m   
                       2
                                 2
                m   2  n   n   2  n
                  2
                       2
                                                
                m    n   0      m n m n 
                                      
                                          
                                                   0
                                                    
                                  m n    0 or    m n   0
                                     
                                     
                                                    n
                                  m n or       m  


             Exercise
             Use a direct proof to show that the sum of two odd integers is even.
             Solution
                Let m and n be two odd integers. Then there exists a and b such that  n   2a   1 and  m   2b   1.
                n m   2a  1 2b   1
                                  2
                        2a  2b
                          2 a b    1

                Since this represents  n m   as 2 times  a b   1, we conclude that  n m   is even, as desired.
                                                       



             Exercise
             Use a direct proof to show that the sum of two even integers is even.


             Solution
                Let m and n be two even integers. Then there exists a and b such that  n   2a and  m  2b .

                n m   2a  2b

                         2 a b  
                Since this represents  n m   as 2 times  a b , we conclude that  n m   is even, as desired.


                                                             30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Use a proof by contradiction to prove that the sum of an irrational number and a rational number is
             irrational.
             Solution

                Let r is a rational number an s is irrational number then t   r s  is an irrational.
                                                                           
                Suppose that t is rational, then if t   a   and  r   c   where a, b, c, and d are integers with b   and
                                                                                                         0
                                                    b         d
                                                   
                                   r 
                d  0.  Then, t       a    c    ad bc   which is rational.
                                        b   d     bd
                t       r s r     s
                     r     , forcing that s is rational. This contradicts the hypothesis that s is irrational.
                Therefore the assumption that t was rational was incorrect, and we conclude that t is irrational.



             Exercise

             Prove or disprove that the product of two irrational numbers is irrational.
             Solution

                Let  2 be the irrational number,. If we take the product of the irrational number  2  and the

                irrational number  2 , then we obtain the rational number 2. This counterexample refutes the

                proposition.


             Exercise


             Prove that if x is irrational, then   1   is irrational.
                                            x
             Solution


                The contrapositive is: if   1   is rational, then x is rational.
                                        x
                                                                                            0
                Since   1   exists, then  x  . If   1   is rational then by definition  1    q   and  p  . Since   1   can’t be
                                         0
                       x                      x                              x   p                    x
                zero, then we would have the contradiction 1 x  0   .

             Exercise


             Prove that if x is rational and  x  , then   1   is rational.
                                             0
                                                     x
             Solution

                if x is rational and  x  , then by definition we can write  x   p  , where p and q are nonzero
                                      0
                                                                            q
                integers.  Since   1    q   and  p  , we can conclude that   1   is rational.
                                               0
                                x   p                                   x




                                                             31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Exercise

                                  P
                                                P
             Prove the proposition    0 , where    n  is the proposition “If n is a positive integer greater than 1,
                   2
             then  n   . n ” What kind of proof did you use?
             Solution
                                                                                                        2
                The proposition that we are trying to prove is If 0 is a positive integer gr2ater than 1, then  0  .
                                                                                                            0
                Our proof is a vacuous one.
                Since the hypothesis is false, the implication is automatically true.


             Exercise

                                                                                        n
                                                                                              n
                                                                                     
                 P
             Let    n  be the proposition “If a and b are positive real numbers, then a b    a  b n . ” Prove
             that    1  is true. What kind of proof did you use?
                 P
             Solution
                Our proof is a direct one. By the definition of exponential, any real number to the power 1 is itself.
                                             1
                             1
                Hence a b     a b a   1  b . Finally, by the addition rule, we can conclude from
                                1
                       1
                           1
                                                     1
                                                 1
                                            1
                a b    a  b  that a b    a  b .


             Exercise
             Show that these statements about the integer x are equivalent:
                                                         2
                i ) 3   x   2  is even ii ) x   5  is odd  iii ) x   is even
             Solution

                If x is even, then  x   2k  for some integer k.
                  3x  2 3 2k    2 6k   2    2 3k   which is even.
                                                      1
                  x         4 1      2 k    2  1, so  x   is odd
                      5 2k   
                                                       5
                                        
                                                   2
                            2
                    2
                                  2
                  x        4k    2 2k 2  , so  x  is odd
                        2k
                If x is odd, then  x   2k   1 for some integer k.
                  3x  2 3  2k    1  2 6k   3 2 6k    4 1    2 3k    2  1 which is odd not even.
                  x  5 2k   1 5 2k    6    2 k    3 , so  x   is even not odd.
                                                            5
                                                           
                                                                     2
                                     2
                    2
                  x   2k    1  2   4k  4k  1 2 2k    2   2k  , so  x  is odd
                                                              1







                                                             32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Show that these statements about the real number x are equivalent:
                                                                x
                i ) x  is irrational  ii ) 3   x  2  is irrational  iii )    is irrational
                                                                2
             Solution
                The simplest way is to approach in indirect proof.
                i )  ii )

                Suppose that 3x   is rational, that 3x   2   p   for some integers p and q with  q  . Then
                                                                                                0
                                  2
                                                            q
                      p      p   2q          p   2q
                3x      2             x          where 3q  . This shows that x is rational.
                                                                 0
                      q         q               3q
                                                   p
                                                                                        0
                Suppose that  x  is rational, that  x    for some integers p and q with q  .  Then
                                                   q
                          p       3p  2q
                3x         2           where  q  . This shows that 3x   is rational.
                     2 3
                                                                            2
                                                     0
                          q          q
                i )  iii )

                Suppose that   x   is rational, that   x    p   for some integers p and q with  q  . Then   x   2p   where
                                                                                        0
                              2                 2   q                                                 q
                 q  0. This shows that x is rational.


                Suppose that  x  is rational, that  x   p   for some integers p and q with q  .  Then   x    p   where
                                                                                        0
                                                   q                                             2   2q
                     0
                 2q  . This shows that   x   is rational.
                                        2


             Exercise

                                                        ,
             Prove that at least one of the real numbers  a  a  ,   , a  is greater than or equal to the average of
                                                       1   2        n
             these numbers. What kind of proof did you use?

             Solution
                Using proof of contradiction, then suppose all the number a  a  ,   , a are less than their
                                                                           ,
                                                                          1   2        n
                average.   a   a      a   nA
                           1    2         n
                                   a    a       a
                By definition:  A   1   2         n
                                           n
                The two displayed formulas clearly contradict each other, however: they imply that  nA nA  . Thus
                our assumption must have been incorrect, and we conclude that at least one of the numbers  a  is
                                                                                                          1
                greater than or equal to their average.







                                                             33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Solution           Section 1.6  Proof Methods and Strategy




             Exercise

                                n
                             
             Prove that  n  2  1 2  when n is a positive integer with 1 n   4
                                                                    
             Solution
                             2
                n  1     1      1    2 2 
                                1 2  

                             2
                                 1 2  
                n   2     2      2    5 4 

                             2
                n  3      3  1 2  3   10 8     
                             2
                                            
                                 1 2 
                n   4     4      4    17 16 



             Exercise
             Prove that there are no positive perfect cubes less than 1000 that are the sum of the cubes of two
             positive integers.

             Solution
                The cubes are: 1, 8, 27, 64, 125, 216, 343, 512, and 729.
                    1 + 8 = 9, 1 + 27 = 28, 1 + 64, 1 + 125, 
                    8 + 8, 8 + 27, 8 + 64, 8 + 125, 

                    27 + 27, 27 + 64, 27 + 125, 
                    64 + 64, 64 + 125, 64 + 216, 
                    125 + 125, 125 + 216, 
                    216 + 216, 216 + 343, 
                    343 + 343, 343 + 512, 343 + 729
                    512 + 512, 512 + 729
                    729 + 729
                None of them works.

                We can conclude the no cube less than 1000 is the sum of two cubes.


             Exercise

             Prove that if x and y are real numbers, then  max x y     ,    x  y
                                                                 min x y   . (Hint: Use a proof by cases,
                                                            ,
             with the two cases corresponding to  x   and x < y, respectively.)
                                                    y
             Solution
                                                                                  
                                                               
                                 y
                Suppose that  x  , then by definition  max  ,x  y   and  min  ,x  y  . Therefore in this case
                                                                   x
                                                                                     y
                                     
                                            y
                                        x
                max   ,x y  min   ,x y   .
                                                             34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[
                                                                                       
                                      y
                                                                                   ,
                                                                 ,
                                                                        y
                                                                                           x
                In the second case  x  , then by definition  max x  y   and  min x  y  . Therefore in this
                case,  max x y        ,    y x    x  y
                                min x y     .
                           ,
                Hence in all cases, the equality holds.


             Exercise
             Prove the triangle inequality, which states that if x and y are real numbers, then  x   y   x   y  (where
             x  represents the absolute value of x, which equals x if  x   and equals x if  x 
                                                                                            0
                                                                      0
             Solution

                If x and y are both nonnegative, then  x   y     x   y .
                                                             x
                                                                y
                If x and y are both negative, then  x   y   x      x    y   x   y .
                                                            y  
                If  x   0 and  y  , then there are two subcases to consider for x and y:
                                 0

                                                      
                  Case 1: Suppose that  x    y , then  x y   0. Therefore  x    x   y , as desired.
                                                                            y
                          x   y    y  is a positive number greater than x. Therefore  x   y    x   y
                                                                                             x
                                  x
                                                      
                  Case 2: Suppose that  x    y , then  x y   0. Therefore  x   y   x   y   x  
                                                                                             y .
                         is a positive number less than or equal to y. Therefore  x   y     x   y , as desired.
                                                                                        y


             Exercise

                                               
                               
             Prove that either  2 10 500    15 or 2 10 500    16 is not a perfect square
             Solution

                A perfect square is a square of an integer
                                                                                                     
                                                                         
                Rephrased: Show that a non-perfect square exists in the set  2 10  500   15, 2 10     500  16
                Proof: The only two perfect squares that differ by 1 are 0 and 1
                Thus, any other numbers that differ by 1 cannot both be perfect squares
                Thus, a non-perfect square must exist in any set that contains two numbers that differ by 1
                Note that we didn’t specify which one it was!


             Exercise

             Prove that there exists a pair of consecutive integers such that one of these integers is a perfect square
             and the other is a perfect cube.

             Solution
                                 2
                8 2  3     9   3





                                                             35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Suppose that a and b are odd integers with  a  . Show there is a unique integer c such that
                                                          b
               
             a c    b c
                      
             Solution

                                
                                       
                The equation  a c    b c  is equivalent to the disjunction of two equations:
                a c b c or  a c   
                    
                                 
                                        b c

                          
                                                                                              b
                                                      b
                Case: a c b c  is equivalent to  a  , which contradicts the assumption  a  , so the original

                                          
                                                                   
                equation is equivalent to  a c    . By adding b c  to both sides and dividing by 2, we see
                                                 b c
                                                      
                that this equation is equivalent to c   a b  . Thus there is a unique solution. Furthermore, this c is
                                                      2
                an integer, because the sum of the odd integers a and b is even.
























































                                                             36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Solution          Section 1.7  Sets




             Exercise

             List the members of these sets
                                                      
                  
                                                  2
              a)  x x is a real number such that x  1
              b)  x x is a positive integer less than  12 

              c)  x x is the square of an integer and  x  100 
                                             2    
              d)  x x is an integer such that x   2

             Solution

                          
                     
                a)   1, 1
                                              
                b)  1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12
                                               
                c)  0,1,4,9,16,25,36,49,64,81
                                              
                d)         2 is not an integer


             Exercise

             Determine whether each these pairs of sets are equal.

              a)  1,3,3,3,5,5,5,5,5 ,       
                                    5,3,1
                              
              b)     1, 1

                   1 ,
                        
              c)    ,   
             Solution
                a)  Yes; order and repetition do not matter.
                b)  No; the first set has one element, and the second has two elements.
                c)  No; the first set has no elements, and the second has one element (namely the empty set).


             Exercise

             For each of the following sets, determine whether 2 is an element of that set.

              a)  x    x is an integer greater than    1
              b)  x    x is the square of an integer 


              c)  2, 2   

              d)     
                   2 ,
                         2

                                                             37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[ 
              e)    2, 2
                   2 ,
                     
              f)    2

             Solution
                a)  Since 2 is an integer greater than 1, 2 is an element of this set.
                b)  Since 2 is not a perfect square, 2 is not an element of this set.
                c)  This set has two elements, and clearly one of those elements is 2.
                d)  This set has two elements, and clearly neither of those elements is 2. Both of the elements of
                    this set are seats; 2 is a number, not a set.
                e)  This set has two elements, and clearly neither of those elements is 2. Both of the elements of
                    this set are seats; 2 is a number, not a set.
                f)  This set has just one element, namely the set    . So 2 is not an element of this set. Note
                                                                2
                           
                     2 
                       2


             Exercise

             Determine whether each of these statements is true or false
                a)  0
                b)        0

                c)    0   

                d)        0
                     0 
                e)      0
                     0 
                f)      0
                       
                g)     
                h)  x   x

                i)      x
                     x
                     x 
                j)      x
                     x 
                          x
                k)     
                l)        x
                m)        x

             Solution

                a)  False, since the empty set has no elements.
                b)  False, the set on the right has only one element, namely 0, not the empty set.
                c)  False, the empty set has no proper subsets.
                d)  True, every element of the set on the left, is vacuously, an element of the set on the right; and
                    the set on the right contains an element, namely 0, that is not the set on the left.
                e)  False, the set on the right has only one element, namely 0, not the set containing the number 0.
                f)  False, for one set to be a proper subset of another, the two sets cannot be equal.
                                                             38]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[g)  True, every set is a subset of itself.
                h)  True, x is the only element.
                i)  True, every set is a subset of itself.

                j)  False, the only element of   x  is a letter, not a set.
                k)  True,   x  is the only element

                l)  True, the empty set is a subset of every set.
                m) False, the only element of   x  is a letter, not a set.



             Exercise
             Use a Venn Diagram to illustrate the relationships  A  B  and  B   C .


             Solution





                                       C      B     A







             Exercise

             Use a Venn Diagram to illustrate the relationships  A  B  and  A   C .


             Solution





                               B        A       C




                Since no information about the relationship between B and C, then B and C can be overlap.
                The set A must be a subset of each of them.











                                                             39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Exercise
             Suppose that A, B, and C are sets such that  A   B  and  B   C . Show that  A  C


             Solution

                Let  x A, then since  A   B , we can conclude that  x . Furthermore,  since  B  C , the fact that
                                                                      B
                 x  implies that  x C . Therefore,  A   C
                                    
                    B


             Exercise

             What is the cardinality of each of these sets?
              a)    a

                   a
              b)   
                       
              c)   , a   a
              d)   , a   a   a   a
                                 
                          ,
                         ,
             Solution
                a)  1

                b)  1

                c)  2
                d)  3



             Exercise

             How many elements does each of these sets have where a and b are distinct elements?

                  P
                      , ,
                             ,
              a)   a  b   a  b  
                              
              b)  P    , , a   a ,   a
                        
              c)  P    
                  P
             Solution
                                                                         3
                                                                            8
                a)  Since the set has 3 elements, the power of the set has  2   elements
                                                                         4
                b)  Since the set has 4 elements, the power of the set has  2  16 elements
                                                                         0
                c)  Since the set has 0 elements, the power of the set has  2  1 elements. The power of this set
                                  1
                    therefore has  2   elements.
                                      2








                                                             40]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Exercise

                                            
                                               
             What is the Cartesian product  A B C , where A is the set of all airlines and B and C are both the set
             of all cities in the United States? Give an example of how this Cartesian product can be used.
             Solution
                                               
                                        a  b
                This is the set of triples  , , c , where a is an airline and b and c are cities. A useful subset of
                                         
                this set of triples  , , c  for which a flies between b and c. For example, Continental, Houston,
                                  a  b
                Chicago) is in this subset.


             Exercise

                                            
             What is the Cartesian product  A B, where A is the set of all courses offered by the mathematics
             department and B is the set of mathematics professors at this university? Give an example of how this
             Cartesian product can be used.

             Solution
                                                                
                By definition it is the set of all ordered pairs  , c  p  such that c is a course and p is a professor. The
                elements of this set are the possible teaching assignments for the mathematics department.


             Exercise

             Let A be a set. Show that  A   A  

             Solution
                                                             
                By definition,     A consists of al pairs  , x  a  such that  x and  a . Since there are no
                                                                                       A
                elements  x. There are no such pairs, so   A   . Similar reasoning  A   .

































                                                             41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Solution          Section 1.8  Set Operations




             Exercise

             Let A be the set of students who live within one mile of school and let B be the set of students who
             walk to classes. Describe the students in each of these sets
              a)  A B
              b)  A B
                    
              c)  A B
                    
              d)  B A
             Solution
                a)  The set of students who live one mile of school and walk to classes.
                b)  The set of students who live one mile of school or walk to classes.
                c)  The set of students who live one mile of school but not walk to class.
                d)  The set of students who live more than one mile from school but nevertheless walk to class.



             Exercise

             Let A = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5}  and B = {0, 3, 6}
              a)  A B
              b)  A B
                    
              c)  A B
                    
              d)  B A
             Solution
                a)  {0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6}

                b)  {3}

                c)  (1, 2, 4, 5}
                d)  {0, 6}



             Exercise

             Let A = {a, b, c, d, e}  and B = {a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h}
              a)  A B
              b)  A B
                    
              c)  A B
              d)  B A
             Solution

                a)  {a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h} = B
                b)  {a, b, c, d, e} = A
                                                             42]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[c)  , since there are no elements in A that are not in B.
                d)  {f, g, h}


             Exercise

             Prove the domination laws by showing that
              a)  A U    U
              b)  A U     A
              c)  A       A

              d)  A   
             Solution

                                                             
                a)  A U    x x          x x T        U
                                                                    
                                   A x U 
                                                      A
                                                                x T
                                   A x U 
                b)  A U    x x          x x T      x x   A 
                                                             
                                                      A
                                                                       A
                c)  A     x x                 A F   x x   A 
                                             x x
                                                             
                                                                        A
                                   A x
                                                             
                d)  A     x x                 A      x F    
                                             x x  F
                                   A x


             Exercise
             Prove the complement laws by showing that
                        
              a)  A   A U
              b)  A   A  
             Solution
                                            x x  
                                                                 U
                a)  A   A   x x      A         A x     A    x T  
                                   A x
                                            x x  
                                   A x
                                                               x F
                b)  A   A   x x      A         A x     A         


             Exercise

             Show that
              a)  A     A
              b)     A  

             Solution

                                             x x T x x
                a)  A    x x  A x            A             A    A
                b)    A  x x      A  x  F    x  A  x  F   
                                       x





                                                             43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Prove the absorption law by showing that if A and B are sets, then
                             
              a)  A    A B    A

                             
              b)  A    A B    A
             Solution

                                           
                a)  Suppose  x  A   A B , then  x  A and  x  A B  by the definition of intersection. We have
                    x  A and in the latter case  x  A  or x  B  by the definition of union. Since both of these are
                    true,  x A B by the definition of intersection, and we have shown that the right-hand side is

                    a subset of the left-hand side.

                                                                     
                b)  Suppose  x  A   A B        x A or x   A B  by definition of union.

                    x  A or     x A and  x    B 

                                                                                                     
                    By the definition of the intersection, in any event,  x A.  Therefore,  x  A   A B  as well.
                    That proves that the right-hand side is a subset of the left-hand side.


             Exercise

             Show that if A, B, and C are sets, then  A B C   A B C

             Solution

                Suppose  x  A B C , then  x    A B C , which means that x fails to be in at least one of these
                three sets. In other words,  x  A   x  or  B or    x C . This is equivalent to saying that
                 x  A   x  or  B or    x C . Therefore  x A  B  C .

                Conversely, if  x A  B   C , then  x  A   xor   B or  x C  . This means  x  A   xor   B or  x C  ,
                so x cannot be in the intersection of A, B, and C. Since  x A B C , we conclude that
                 x A B C , as desired.

                                                               Or

                     A  B   C       A B C         A B C          A        B       C         A B C

                     1    1    1        1             0           0       0       0             0
                     1    1    0        0             1           0       0       1             1
                     1    0    1        0             1           0       1       0             1
                     1    0    0        0             1           0       1       1             1
                     0    1    1        0             1           1       0       0             1
                     0    1    0        0             1           1       0       1             1
                     0    0    1        0             1           1       1       0             1

                     0    0    0        0             1           1       1       1             1




                                                             44]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Let A and B be sets. Show that
                         
              a)   A B     A
                             
              b)  A    A B
                     
              c)   A B     A
                             
                         
              d)  A   B A  
                         
              e)  A   B A     A B

             Solution
                a)  If x is in  A B, then, by definition of intersection, it is in A.

                b)  If x is in A, then perforce, by definition of union, it is in  A B.
                               
                c)  If x is in  A B, then perforce, by definition of difference, it is in A.
                                                                                           
                                       
                                                                                        
                d)  Is  x A then  xB A. Therefore there can be no elements in  A   B A , so
                              
                           
                    A   B A   .
                e)  The left-hand side consists of elements of either A or  B or both. This is precisely the definition
                    of the right-hand side.


             Exercise

             Draw the Venn diagrams for each of these combinations of the sets A, B, and C.
                             
                         
              a)  A   B C
                                   
              b)   A B    A C
                                   
              c)   A B    A C

              d)  A   B   C
              e)   A B    A C   B C  


             Solution

                                                                                    A                B






                                                                                                  C














                                                             45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Show that  A B    A B         
                                        A B
             Solution

                This is just a restatement of the definition. An element is in  A B   A B    if it in the union that
                in either A or B, but not in the intersection (i.e., not in both A and B)


             Exercise

             Show that  A B   A B   B A  

             Solution

                There are two ways that an item can be in either A or B but not both. It can be in A but not B
                (which is equivalent to saying that it is in A  B), or it can be in B but not A (which is equivalent to
                saying that it is in B  A).
                                                                                
                                                                   
                                                                             
                                          B
                Thus an element is in  A  if and only if it is in  A B  B A .



















































                                                             46]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Solution          Section 1.9  Functions




             Exercise

             Why is f not a function from    to    if
                     
              a)  f x    1  ?
                          x
                     
              b)  f x     x ?

                     
                              2
              c)  f x      x  1 ?
             Solution

                                    0
                                                   f
                a)  Because for  x   the value of    x  is not defined by the given rule.
                                    0
                                                   f
                b)  Because for  x   the value of    x  is not defined in
                c)  Because for    1   2 or   f    1    2
                                 f



             Exercise

             Determine whether f is a function from    to   if
                     
              a)  f x      x?
              b)  f x      x   2  1 ?

                     
              c)  f x      1   ?
                           2
                          x   4
             Solution
                a)  This is not a function because    1  1 or  f    1   ,
                                                                        1
                                                  f
                b)  This is a function for all integers x.
                c)  This is not a function since for  x     2 the value of    x  is not defined by the given rule.
                                                                      f


             Exercise


             Find the domain and range of these functions. Note that in each case, to find the domain, determine the
             set of elements assigned values by the function.
              a)  The function that assigns to each bit string the number of ones in the string minus the number of
                  zeros in the string.
              b)  The function that assigns to each bit string twice the number of zeros in that string.
              c)  The function that assigns the number of bits over when a bit string is split into bytes (which are
                  blocks of 8 bits).

             Solution




                                                             47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[a)  The domain is the set of all bit strings. Depending on how we read the word “difference” the
                    output values can be either integers or natural numbers. For example. If the input is 1010000,
                    then one might read the rule as stating that the function value is 3, since there are three more 0s

                    than 1s; but most people would probably consider the function value to be 3, obtained by
                                                   
                    subtracting in the order stated:  2 5   . Then the range is Z.
                                                          3
                b)  The domain is the set of all bit strings. Since there can be any natural number of 0s in a bit
                    string, the value of the function can be 0, 2, 4, . Therefore the range is the set of even natural
                    numbers.
                c)  The domain is the set of all bit strings. Since the number of leftover bits can be any whole
                    number from 0 to 7 (if it were more, then we could form another byte), the range is (0, 1, 2, 3,
                    4, 5, 6, 7).


             Exercise

             Determine whether each of these functions from {a, b, c, d} to itself is one-to-one and onto.
                      b   f b 
              a)  f a     ,       , a   f    c   , c   f d 
                                                     d
                                          
              b)  f a     ,     b   f c     , d   f d 
                      b   f b 
                                                     c
                                     ,
                     
                                                     
              c)  f a     , d   f    b   , b   f    c   , c   f d  d
             Solution
                a)  This is onetoone.
                b)  This is not onetoone, since b is the image of both a and b.
                c)  This is not onetoone, since d is the image of both a and d.


             Exercise

             Determine whether the function  : f         is onto if

              a)  f   ,m  n     m n
                                    2
              b)  f m  n     m   2  n
                     ,
                          
              c)  f m  n    m
                     ,
                          
              d)  f   ,m  n   n
              e)  f   ,m  n     m n
              f)  f   ,m  n     2m n

                                   2
              g)  f m  n     m   2  n
                     ,
                          
              h)  f   ,m  n  m n  1
              i)  f   ,m  n     m   n

              j)  f   ,m  n     m   2  4

             Solution

                                                             48]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[
                a)  Given any integer n, we have  0, n  , so the function is onto.
                                                           n
                                                 f
                b)  The range contains no negative integers, so the function is not onto.
                c)  Given any integer m, we have   , 4f m      m , so the function is onto.
                d)  The range contains no negative integers, so the function is not onto.
                e)  Given any integer m, we have   , 0      m , so the function is onto.
                                                  f m
                f)  For any integer n, we have  0,f       n   n , so the function is onto.
                                            
                      2
                           2
                g)  m   n   m n m n  , since 2 is not in the range, so the function is not onto.
                                 
                                     
                                               2
                h)  For any integer n, we have  0, n    1   n , so the function is onto.
                                               f
                i)  This is onto. To achieve negative values we set  m  , and to achieve nonnegative value we set
                                                                      0
                    n   0 .
                      2
                j)  m      m  2 m   2   since 2 is not in the range, so the function is not onto.
                         4
                                             2


             Exercise
             Determine whether each of these functions is a bijection from   
              a)  f x     2x   1

              b)  f x     x   2  1

                           3
                     
              c)  f x    x
                            2
                     
              d)  f x    x   1
                           2
                          x   2
              e)  f x     x   5  1


             Solution
                       
                a)  f x    2x  1     f   1   x   x  1 . Therefore the function is a bijection.
                                                   2
                b)  It is not one-to-one since    1   f   2
                                                       1   and it is also not onto since the range is the interval
                                             f
                         
                    1,  .
                c)       x   x 3    f   1   x   3  x . Therefore the function is a bijection.
                      f

                d)  It is not one-to-one since    1f    f    1    2  and it is also not onto since the range is the interval
                                                            3
                     1   
                     2   ,  .
                             5
                       
                e)  f x    x  1      f   1   x   5  x  1. Therefore the function is a bijection.









                                                             49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Exercise

             Suppose that g is a function from A to B and f is a function from B to C.
              a)  Show that if both f and g are onetoone functions, then  f g  is also onetoone.
              b)  Show that if both f and g are onto functions, then  f g  is also onto.

             Solution

                a)  Assume that both f and g are onetoone. We need to show that  f g  is also onetoone. If x
                                                                   
                    and y are two distinct elements of A, then   f g x   f g y
                                                                              . First, since g is onetoone,
                    by definition    x   g   y . Second, since now    x  and    y  are distinct elements of B, and
                                                                            g
                                 g
                                                                  g
                                                                 
                                                                             as desired.
                    since f is onetoone, we conclude that   f g x     f g y
                b)  Assume that both f and g are onto. We need to show that  f g  is onto. If z is any element of C,
                                                                     . First, since f is onto, we can conclude
                    then there is some element  x A such that   f g x  z
                                                                                                  
                                             
                                                                  z
                    that there is an element  y B  such that    y  . Second, since g is onto and  y B , we can
                                                           f
                    conclude that there is an element  x A such that    x  . therefore  z   f    y    f g x
                                                                           y
                                                                                                          as
                                                                    g
                    desired.


















































                                                             50]]></page></pages></Search>