<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="50"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Lecture Four − Parametric Equations and Polar Coordinates




             Section 4.1 – Parameterizations of Plane Curves



             Definition

             If x and y are given as functions

                                                                       ( )
                                                      x =  f  ( ),t  y =  gt
             Over an interval I as t−values, then the set of points ( ,x y ) ( f=  ( ),t  g t
                                                                                ( ))  defined by these equations is a
             parametric curve. The equations are parametric equations for the curve





















             The variable t is a parameter for the curve, and its domain I is the parameter interval.

























             Definition

             The direction in which a parametric curve is generated as the parameter increases is called the forward or
             positive orientation of the curve.

                                                              359]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Example

          Sketch the curve defined by the parametric equations

                              t
                                          t
                 x = t 2 ,  y = + 1, −∞ < < ∞
          Then obtain an algebraic equation in x and y.
          Solution

                            2
                t       x = t     y = +  1
                                      t
                −3        9          −2
                −2        4          −1
                −1        1          0
                0         0          1
                1         1          2
                2         4          3
                3         9          4

                 t
                         t
                    1
              y = +⇒ =      y − 1
              x =  t =  2  ( y −  ) 1  2  =  y −  2  2y +  1  represents a parabola


          Example


          Graph the parametric curve   x =  cos ,t  y =  sin , 0t  ≤≤  2π
                                                              t
          Solution


               x +  2  y =  2  cos t +  2  sin t =  2  1

              This parametric curve lies along the unit circle  x +  2  y =  2  1.
              As t increases from 0 to 2π, the point ( ,x y ) (cos , sint  =  ) t

              starts at (1, 0) and traces the entire circle once
              counterclockwise.


          Example

          Graph the parametric curve   x =  a cos , t  y =  a sin , 0 t≤≤  2π
                                                          t
          Solution

                                                                   2
               x +  2  y =  2  a 2 cos t +  2  a 2 sin t =  2  a 2 ( cos t +  2  sin t = 2  )  a
                                                                       2
              This parametric curve lies along the unit circle  x +  2  y =  2  a .

                                                                                                         a
              As t increases from 0 to 2π, the point ( ,x y ) ( cos , sina=  t  a  ) t  starts at (a, 0) with a radius  r =  and
              traces the entire circle once counterclockwise.

                                                           360]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Example

                                                              t
             Graph the parametric curve   x =  , t  y =  t 2 , −∞ < < ∞
             Solution

                      2
                 y =  x



             Example

             Find a parameterization for the line through the point (a, b) having slope m.

             Solution
                A Cartesian equation of the line is  y b−=  mx   ) a
                                                           ( −
                If t =  xa−  ⇒    x t a=  +

                    y b−=  mt ⇒      y = mt b+
                That is,  x t a= +  y =  mt +  , b  −∞ < t < ∞


             Example

             Sketch the curve defined by the parametric equations   x =  t +  1 ,  y =  t −  1 , t >  0
                                                                        t          t
             Then obtain an algebraic equation in x and y.
             Solution

                                            1
                                1
                           =
                                         t
                   t     x t +       y = −
                                            t
                                t
                   .2       5.2        −4.8
                   .5       2.5        −1.5
                   1        2           0
                   2        2.5        1.5
                   5        5.2        4.8
                                     1
                                         t
                     x +  y     = t + +−    1      =  2t
                                      t     t
                                     1
                                         t
                     x −  y     = t + −+    1      =  2
                                                     t
                                      t     t      
                                                    2
                      )( −
                ( x +  yx    ) y               =  2t ( ) =  4
                                                     t
                 x −  2  y =  2  4







                                                              361]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Cycloids

          The problem with a pendulum clock whose bob swings in a circular arc is that the frequency of the swing
          depends on the amplitude of the swing.

















          Example

          A wheel of a radius a rolls along a horizontal straight line. Find parametric equations for the path traced
          by a point P on the wheel’s circumference. The path is called a cycloid.
          Solution
















             We take the line to be on the x-axis, mark a point P on the wheel, start the wheel with P at the origin,
             and roll the wheel. As parameter, we use the angle t through which the wheel turns, measured in
                                                       )
             radians. The wheel’s center C lies at ( ,at  a  and the coordinates of P are
                                              x =  at a+  cos , θ  y =  a a+  sinθ


             To express θ in terms of t, we observe that t θ =  3π , so that θ =  3π  t −
                                                        +
                                                               2
                                                                               2
                                    ( 3π   )                    ( 3π    )
             That makes  cosθ    cos  2  −  t =  −  sin , sinθ =  t  =  sin  2  −  t =  −  cost
              x =  at a−  sin ,t  y =  a a−  cost

             That implies to:   x =  ( at −  sint ),  y =  a (1 cost−  )













                                                           362]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Exercises            Section 4.1 – Parameterizations of Plane Curves



             (1 − 28)   Give parametric equations and parameter intervals for the motion of a particle in the xy-plane.
             Identify the particle’s path by finding a Cartesian equation for it. Graph the Cartesian equation.

                                                                                                4
                                                                         t
                                                                                         4 t
             1.    x = 3,t  y =  9 ,t 2  −∞ < t < ∞            15.  x = −   1,  y =  t 3 ; − ≤ ≤
             2.    x =  −  , t  y =  , t  t ≥  0               16.  x e=  2t ,  y e=  t  + 1; 0 t≤≤  25
                                          t
             3.    x = 3 3,t−  y =  2 , 0t  ≤≤ 1               17.  x =  3cos ,t  y = 3sin ;t  π  t  2π ≤≤
                                      t
             4.    x =  cos2 , t  y =  sin2 , 0 t π≤≤          18.  x = − 7cos2 ,t  y = − 7sin2 ; 0t  ≤≤
                                                                                                      t π
             5.    x = cos (π  t ),  y =  sin (π−  t ), 0 t π −  ≤≤     19.  x = −     y = +               ≤≤   1
                                                                                                            t
                                                                                          2 3cos4 ; 0t π
                                                                         1 3sin4 ,t π
                                                                                                                2
             6.    x =  4sin ,t  y =  5cos , 0t  ≤≤  2π
                                              t
                                                               20.  x =  2 , t  y =  3t − 4; − 10 t≤ ≤ 10
             7.    x = 1 sin ,t+  y =  cost − 2, 0 t≤≤  2π
                                                                                            4
                                                               21.  x t=  2  + 2,  y =  4 ;t  −≤  t ≤  4
                                6
             8.    x = t 2 ,  y =  t − 2,t 4  −∞ <  t < ∞
                                                                          t
                                                               22.  x = − +  6,   y =  3t − 3; − 5 t≤ ≤
                                                                                                      5
             9.    x =  t  ,  y =  t −  2 , − < < 1                       3
                                          1 t
                      t −  1     t +  1                        23.  x t=    − 1,  y =  5t + 1; − 3 t≤ ≤  3
             10.  x =   t +  1,  y =  , t  t ≥  0              24.  x =  cos ,t  y =  sin t , 0 t≤≤ π
                                                                                       2
             11.  x =  2sinh ,t  y = 2cosh ,t  −∞ < t < ∞
                                                                                                   t
                                                               25.  x =  1 sin t−  2  ,  y =  cos ,t  π  ≤≤  2π
             12.  x =  4cos 2,tπ  y =  4sin 2, 0tπ  ≤  t ≤ 1
                                                                                                  t
                                                               26.  x =  cos ,t  y = 1 sin ; 0t+  ≤≤  2π
             13.  x =   t +  4,  y =  3 t ; 0 t≤≤ 16
                                                                                                        t
                                                               27.  x =  2sint − 3,  y =  5 cos 2 ; 0t+  ≤≤  2π
                            2
                                    t
             14.  x = (t +  ) 1 ,  y = + 2; − 10 t≤≤ 10        28.  x =  4cost − 1,  y =  4sint +  2; 0 t≤≤  2π

             (29 − 32)   For the given parametric equations:
                a)  Plot the following curve, indicating the positive orientation.
                b)  Eliminate the parameter to obtain an equation in x and y.
                c)  Identify or briefly describe the curve.
                             dy
                d)  Evaluate     at the specified point.
                             dx

                                               t
             29.  x t=  2  +  4,  y =  6 t−  ; −∞ ≤ ≤ ∞  ( ,55    )
                                             t
             30.  x e=  t ,  y =  3e − 2t ; −∞ ≤ ≤ ∞  ( ,3    )
                                                     1
             31.  x = 10sin 2 ,t  y = 16cos 2 ; 0t  ≤≤    ( 5 3, 8   ) .
                                                   t π
             32.  x =  ln ,t  y =  8lnt 2 ; 1 t e≤≤  2  (1, 16   )




                                                              363]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[(33 − 47)   Find parametric equations:

                                                   2
                                                                           )
          33.  For the left half of the parabola  y =  x + 1, originating at (0, 1
                                                       )
          34.  A line that passes through the points (1, 1   and (3, 5   ) , oriented in the direction of increasing x.

          35.  Lower half of the circle centered at ( 2, 2 −  ) with radius 6, oriented in the counterclockwise


               direction.
                                               2
          36.  Upper half of the parabola  x =  y , originating at (0, 0   )

          37.  The circle centered at the origin with radius 4, generated counterclockwise.
                                                                                                        )

          38.  The circle centered at the origin with radius 12, generated clockwise with initial point (0, 12
          39.  The circle centered at (2, 3   )  with radius 1, generated counterclockwise.


          40.  The circle centered at (2, 0   )  with radius 3, generated clockwise.

          41.  The circle centered at ( 2,  −  −  ) 3  with radius 8, generated clockwise.


          42.  The circle  x +  2  y =  2  9 , generated clockwise.


          43.  The upper half of the ellipse   x 2  +  y 2  =  1, generated counterclockwise.
                                            9    4


          44.  The right side of the ellipse   x 2  +  y 2  =  1, generated counterclockwise.
                                           9     4

          45.  The line  y =  4x + 11

          46.  The line segment from  ( 1, 0P  −  )  to  (1, 1Q  )  and the line segment from Q to P.

                                                 3
                                         f
          47.  The segment of the curve  ( ) x =  x +  2x  from (0, 0   )  to (2, 12   )


          48.  What is the relationship among a, b, c, and d such that the equations

                  x ( ) t =  a cost + b sint
                 
                                             describe a circle?
                   y ( ) t =  c cost + d  sint
               What is the radius of the circle?

          49.  Find parametric equations (not unique) of an ellipse centered at the origin with major axis of length
               6 on the  x-axis  and minor axis of length 3 on the  y-axis , generated counterclockwise. Graph the
               ellipse and find a description in terms of x and y.

          50.  Find parametric equations (not unique) of an ellipse centered at the origin with major axis of length
               12 on the  x-axis  and minor axis of length 2 on the  y-axis , generated clockwise. Graph the ellipse
               and find a description in terms of x and y.
                                                           364]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[51.  Find parametric equations (not unique) of an ellipse centered at ( 2, −  −  ) 3  with major and minor

                  axes of lengths 30 and 20, parallel to the  x-axis  and  y-axis , respectively. Graph the ellipse and find
                  a description in terms of x and y.

             52.  Find a parametric equation and a parameter interval for the motion of a particle starting at the point

                  (2, 0) and tracing the top half of the circle   x +  2  y =  2  4  four times.

             53.  Find a parametrization for the line segment joining points (0, 2) and (4, 0) using the angle θ in the
                  accompanying figure as the parameter.


















             54.  Find a parametrization for the circle  x +  2  y =  2  1 starting at (1, 0) and moving counterclockwise to
                  the terminal point (0, 1), using the angle θ in the accompanying figure as the parameter.



















             55.  A common task is to parameterize curves given either by either Cartesian equations or by graphs.
                  Find a parametric representation of the following curves.
                                                      9
                  a)  The segment of the parabola  y = −  x 2 ,  for  − 1 ≤  x ≤  3
                  b)  The complete curve  x =  ( y −  ) 5  2  +  y

                  c)  The piecewise linear path that connects  ( 2, 0P  −  )  to  (0, 3Q  )  to  (4, 0R  )  (in that order), where
                                                                 2
                      the parameter varies over the interval 0 t≤ ≤






                                                              365]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[56.  A projectile launched from the ground with an initial speed of 20 m/s and a launch angle θ follows a
               trajectory approximated by

                                         x =  (20cosθ  ) ,t  y =  −  4.9t +  2  (20sinθ  )t

               Where x and y are the horizontal and vertical positions of the projectile relative to the launch point
               (0, 0   ) .

                                                                      <
                 a)  Graph the trajectory for various of θ in the range 0 θ <  π .
                                                                            2
                 b)  Based on your observations, what value of θ gives the greatest range (the horizontal distance
                    between the launch and landing points)?

          57.  Many fascinating curves are generated by points on rolling wheels. The path of a light on the rim of
               a rolling when is a cycloid, which has the parametric equations

                         x ( ) t =  ( a t − sin  ) t
                        
                                             for   t ≥  0
                          y ( ) t =  a (1 cost−  )



















                          0
               Where  a > . Graph the cycloid with  a = 1. On what interval does the parameter generate one arch
               of the cycloid?

                                                                                                       )
          (58 − 60)   Find parametric equations that describe the circular path of the objects. Assume ( ,x y
                    denotes the position of the object relative to the origin at the center of the circle.

          58.  A go-cart moves counterclockwise with constant speed around a circular track of radius 400 m,
               completing in 1.5 min.

          59.  The tip of the 15-in second hand of a clock completes one revolution in 60 sec.


          60.  A Ferris wheel has a radius of 20 m and completes a revolution in the clockwise direction at
               constant speed in 3 min. Assume that x and y measure the horizontal and vertical positions of a seat
               on the Ferris wheel relative to a coordinate system whose origin is at the low point of the wheel.
               Assume the seat begins moving at the origin.





                                                           366]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[61.  A plane traveling horizontally at 80 m/s over flat ground at an elevation of 3000 m releases an
                  emergency packet. The trajectory of the packet is given by





















                                            x =  80 ,t  y =  −  4.9t +  2  3000,  for  t ≥  0

                  Where the origin is the point on the ground directly beneath the plane at the moment of the release.
                  Graph the trajectory of the packet and find the coordinates of the point where the packet lands.

             62.  A plane traveling horizontally at 100 m/s over flat ground at an elevation of 4,000 m must drop an
                  emergency packet on a target on the ground. The trajectory of the packet is given by


                           x ( ) 100 ,t =  t  y ( ) t =  −  4.9t +  2  4,000,  for  t ≥  0

                  Where the origin is the point on the ground directly beneath the plane at the moment of the release.
                  How many horizontal meters before the target should the packet be released in order to hit the
                  target?

             63.  The path of a point on circle A with radius   a   that rolls on the inside of circle B with a radius a is an
                                                            4
                  asteroid or hypocycloid. Its parametric equations are























                                                                   3
                                                      3
                                                                            t
                                              x =  a cos ,t  y =  a sin , 0t  ≤≤  2π
                  Graph the asteroid with  a = 1 and find its equation in terms of x and y.

                                                              367]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Section 4.2 – Calculus with Parametric Curves




          Tangents and Areas


                                                   ( )  is differentiable at t if f and g are differentiable at t.
          A parametrized curve  x =  f  ( ) t  and  y =  gt


          Parametric Formula for dy dx
                                           /

          If all three derivatives exist and   dx  ≠  0,
                                         dt
                                                       dy  =  dy  / dt
                                                       dx   dx  / dt


          The derivatives   dy dx , and   dy   are related by the Chain Rule   dy  =  dy  ⋅ dx
                             ,
                          dt  dt      dx                               dt   dx dt


                                                2
                                         2
          Parametric Formula for  d y dx
                                            /
          If the equations  x =  f  ( ) t  ,  y =  gt
                                          ( )  define y as a twice−differentiable function of x, then at any point
          where   dx  ≠  0  and  y′ =  dy  ,
                 dt              dx
                                                       2
                                                      d y  =  dy′ / dt
                                                      dx 2   dx / dt


          Example

                                                                                           )
          Find the tangent to the curve  x = sec ,t  y =  tan ,t  − π  <<  π  , at the point  (  2, 1  , where t =  π
                                                                  t
                                                              2      2                                 4
          Solution

             The slope of the curve at t is:
                 dy    dy  / dt
                     =
                 dx    dx  / dt
                            2
                     =  sec t
                       sec tant  t

                     =  sect
                       tant



                   dy
              m =
                   dx  t= π
                         4

                                                           368]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[sec π
                  =     4
                    tan  π
                        4
                  =   2


                The tangent line is

                    y =   2 x −  (  2 +  )  1    y =  mx −  (  x 1 ) +  y
                                                                  1

                      =  2x − 21+
                       =  2  x − 1


             Example

                    2
                  dy                               2          3
             Find       as a function of t if   x =  tt−  ,  y =  tt−
                  dx 2

             Solution

                     dy   dy  / dt
                 y′ =   =
                     dx   dx  / dt
                   = 13t−  2
                      12t
                       −

                 dy′   d    −  3t +  2  1                    u =  13t−  2  v =  1 2t−
                 dt  =  dt      −  2t +  1                  u′   −  6t  v′ =  =  −  2

                      − 61 2t ( −  t −−  (  −  2 )
                                ) ( ) 2 1 3t
                    =
                               (12t  ) 2
                                 −
                               2
                                  2 6t
                    =  − 6t + 12t +−    2
                              −
                           (12t   ) 2
                                                                                   )
                                                                               −
                    =  6t −  2  6t +  2                  d      ax +  2  bx +  c      =  (ae bd x +  2  ( 2 af −  cd ) x +  bf −  ce
                        (12t  ) 2                       dx   dx +   2  ex +  f     ( dx +  2  ex +  f ) 2
                          −

                  2
                 d y  =  dy′ / dt
                  x d  2  dx  / dt
                          2
                      =  6t − 6t +  2  ÷ (12t−  )
                         (12t−  ) 2

                      =  6t −  2  6t +  2
                         (12t−  ) 3


                                                              369]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Example

                                                            3
                                                                        3
          Find the area enclosed by the asteroid:    x = cos ,t  y = sin , 0t  ≤≤  2π
                                                                                t
          Solution

             By symmetry, the enclosed area is 4 times the area beneath the curve in the first quadrant where
              0 t≤≤  π .
                     2



              A =  4 ∫ 0 1   y dx



                   ∫ π /2 sin t  d ( cos t                    (   3  )        2  sin t dt
                                        )
                            3
                                      3
                 4
               =    0                                       d  cos t = − 3cos t
                   ∫ π /2   3   3cos t  sin  dt t
                                    2
                 4
               =    0    sin t ⋅

                    ∫ π /2   4      2
               = 12  0    sin t ⋅ cos t dt




                                     2
                            −
                                         +
               = 12 ∫ 0 π /2 ( 1 cos 2t ) ( 1 cos 2t )  dt
                                           2
                               2
                                          2
                                                         )
                            −
                                                 +
               =  3 ∫ π /2 ( 1 2cos 2t +  cos 2t ) (1 cos 2t  dt
                  2  0
                                                                          )
                                                                      3
               =  3 ∫ π /2 ( 1 2cos 2t−  +  cos 2t +  2  cos 2t −  2cos 2t +  2  cos 2t  dt
                  2  0


                                                      )
                                                  3
               =  3 ∫ π /2 ( 1 cos 2t−  −  cos 2t +  2  cos 2t  dt
                  2  0


                                                                       3
                                                                                            2
                                                                           d
               =  3  t −  1  sin 2t  0 ∫  π /2  −  3  π  /2 cos 2tt +  2  d  3 ∫  π  /2 cos 2tt    cos α=  1 cos2+  2  α
                   
                                       2
                  2
                                                           2
                        2
                                         0                    0
                   (
                                                                              d
               =  3 π −  0 −  )  3 ∫  π  /2 1 cos 2t+  2  dt +  3 ∫  π  /2 ( 1 sin 2 cos 2t−  2  )  tt
                                                    2
                     2
                  2
                             2
                                0                      0
                                                           370]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[2
                  =  3π −  3 ( t +  1  sin 2t  π /2  +  3 ∫ π /2 ( 1 sin 2t ) d (sin 2t )
                                                          −
                     4
                          4
                                               4
                                2
                                         0         0
                           (
                                     3
                                                    3
                  =  3π  4  −  3 π  4 2  −  0 +  ) ( sin 2t −  1 sin 2   t  π /2
                                     4
                                                3
                                                          0
                  =  3π  4  −  3π  8  +  3 (00−  )
                               4

                  =  3π  u    nit 2
                     8
































































                                                              371]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Length of a Parametrically Defined Curve


          Definition

                                                                     ( ) ,  a t≤≤ , where  f ′  and  g′  are
          If a curve C is defined parametrically by  x =  f  ( ) t  and  y =  gt  b
          continuous and not simultaneously zero on [a, b], and C is traversed exactly once as t increases from
             a
          t =  to t = , then the length of C is the definite integral
                      a
                                                 ∫  b         2      ( )) 2
                                                                    ′
                                             L =   a   ( f t     ( g t     dt
                                                         ′
                                                          ( )) +























          Example

                                                                                                      t
          Find the length of the circle of radius r defined parametrically by    x =  r cos ,t  y =  r sin , 0t  ≤≤  2π

          Solution
                    2π        2        2
              L =         ∫      dx     +     dy     dt

                   0 2π   dt      dt 
                 ∫      ( r−  sin  ) t  2  +  ( cosr  ) t  2  dt
               =
                   0

                 ∫  2π    2   2     2  cos tt
                                         2
               =        r  sin t +  r       d
                   0 2π

                 ∫        2 (  2    cos t )  dt
                                       2
               =        r   sin t +
                   0

               = ∫  2π r dt

                   0
                                                           372]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[2π
                  =  r t
                        0

                     π
                  =  2 r  unit


             Example

                                                        3
                                                                    3
             Find the length of the asteroid:    x =  cos t ,  y =  sin t , 0 t  2π
                                                                           ≤≤
             Solution
                Because of the curve’s symmetry with respect to the coordinate axes, its length is 4 times the length of
                the first quadrant.

                      2                    2
                  dx        2          
                      =    3cos t ( sin t−  ) 
                  dt                   
                              4
                                    2
                        =  9cos t  sin t
                      2
                  dy        2          2
                      =    3sin t (cost ) 
                  dt                 
                                    2
                              4
                        =  9sin t cos t
                       2        2
                    dx     dy         4     2       4     2
                       +      =  9cos t  sin t +  9sin t cos t
                    dt     dt 
                                                           2
                                                    2
                                         t
                                  =  3 cos sint  cos t + sin t                cos t +  2  sin t =  2  1
                                         t
                                                                                               t
                                                                                 t
                                  =  3cos sin   t                             cos sint ≥ 0,  0 ≤ ≤  π
                                                                                                  2
                       2π       2        2
                 L =        ∫      dx     +      dy      dt
                      0      dt      dt 


                  =  4 ∫ π /2 3cos sint  t dt           sin 2t =  2cos sint  t
                       0  π /2


                  =  12 ∫    sin2t dt
                     2
                         0

                  = − 6  cos 2  t  π /2
                      2
                               0
                  = −  ( 3 11−−  )
                   = −−
                      3
                       ( ) 2
                   =  6 u   nit



                                                              373]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Area of Surface of Revolution for Parametrized Curves

                                               ( ) ,  a t≤≤
          If a smooth curve  x =  f  ( ) t  and  y =  gt  b , is traversed exactly once as t increases from a to b,
          then the areas of the surfaces generated by revolving the curve about the coordinate axes are as follows.


           1.  Revolution about the x−axis (y ≥ 0):



                                S =  2π ∫ b  y         dx   dt     2  +       dy   dt     2   dt


                                        a
           2.  Revolution about the y−axis (x ≥ 0):



                                S =  2π ∫  b  x         dx   dt     2  +        dy   dt     2   dt


                                        a

          Example


          The standard parametrization of the circle of radius 1 centered at the point (0, 1) in the xy−plane is

                                            x =  cos ,t  y = 1 sin , 0t+  ≤≤  2π
                                                                        t
          Use the parametrization to find the area of the surface swept out by revolving the circle about the x−axis.

          Solution
                                 2
                              dx          2
              x =  cost ⇒        =  ( sint−  )
                              dt 
                                    2
                                 dy         2
                   +
              y =  1 sint ⇒         =  (cost )
                                 dt 
                    2        2
                 dx     dy       2       2
                    +      =  sin t +  cos t =  1
                 dt     dt 

                    b           2        2
              S =    2 yπ   ∫      dx     +     dy      dt
                   a         dt      dt 


               = ∫  2π 2π (1 sint  dt+  )
                   0
                             2π
               =  2π [t −  cost ]
                             0
                          1
               =  2π  (2π  −− (01−  ))
                          2
               =  4π 2   unit
                                                           374]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Exercises            Section 4.2 – Calculus with Parametric Curves



             (1 − 4)   Find all the points at which the curve has the given slope.

              1.   x =  4cos ,t  y =  4sin ;t  slope =  1        3.    x =  t +  1 ,  y =  t −  1 ; slope =  1
                                                   2                         t          t

              2.   x =  2cos ,t  y = 8sin ;t  slope = − 1        4.    x =  2 +  , t  y =  2 4;t−  slope =  −  8


             (5 − 12)   Find an equation of the line tangent to the curve at the point corresponding to the given value
                       of t.

              5.   x = sin ,t  y =  cos ,t  t =  π               9.    x = 6 ,t  y t=  2  + 4, t = 1
                                             4
              6.   x =  t −  2  1,  y =  t +  3  , t  t =  2     10.  x t=  −  2,  y =  1 +  3, t = 1
                                                                                     t
              7.   x =  e t ,  y =  ln (t +  ) 1 , t =  0        11.  x t=  2  −+  2,  y t=  3  − 3, t  t = − 1
                                                                              t
              8.   x =  cost +  t sin , t  y =  sin tt cos , t  t =  π    12.  x =  t −  2  +  3 ,t  y =  2t 3/2 , t =  1
                                              −
                                                            4                                       4


             (13 − 33)  Find the tangent to the curve at the point defined by the given value of t. Also find the value of
                         2
                        dy   at this point
                        dx 2

             13.   x =  sin 2, t π  y =  cos 2, tt π  = − 1     24.  x = cos , θ  y = 3sin , θ  θ = 0
                                                   6
                                                                                         +
                                                                           +
             14.  x =  cos,t  y =   3 c s,o t  t =  2π          25.  x =  2 sec ,θ  y =  1 2tan , θθ  =  π
                                                                                                        6
                                                 3
                                                                                              2
             15.   x =  , t  y =  , t  t =  1                   26.  x =    , t  y =  t − 1, t =
                                       4
                                                                27.  x = cos θ  3  ,  y = sin θ  3  , θ =  π
             16.   x   sec t − =  2  1,  y =  tan t t = − π                                        4
                                                  4             28.  x θ  =  sin ,θ −  y =  1 cos , θθ −  π =

             17.  x =    1  ,  y =  t    t =  2
                       t + 1      t − 1                         29.  x =  5t +  2,  y =  1 4t−  t =  3

                                    −
             18.   x t=  +  e t ,  y =  1 e t  t =  0                         , 6    2      5
                                                                30.  x t −  =    y t=    t =
             19.  x =  4, t  y =  3t −  2, t =  3                        1
                                                                31.  x =  t  ,  y =  2t + 3 t = − 1
             20.   x =   , t  y = 3t − 1, t = 1
                                                                32.  x =  1 ,  y t=  2  t = − 2
             21.  x t +  =  1,  y t=  2  +  3 ,t  t = − 1                t

             22.  x t=  2  +  5t +  4,  y =  4,t  t =  0        33.  x =  e t ,  y = e  t −  t = 1

              23.  x =  4cos ,θ  y =  4sin ,θ  θ =  π
                                                 4


                                                              375]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[(33 − 37)  Find the equations of the tangent lines at the point where the curve crosses itself

           34.  x =  2sin2 ,t  y =  3sint                   36.  x =  t 2  , t −  y =  t −  3  3t −  1

           35.  x =  2 π  −  cos ,t  y =  2t π  −  sint               3            2
                                                            37.  x =  t −  6 ,t  y =  t

                                                              ( )  at the given value of t. Define x and y as
          (38 − 40)  Find the slope of the curve  x =  f  ( ),t  y =  gt
                    differentiable functions.

          38.   x +  3  2t =  2  9, 2y −  3  3t =  2  4, t =  2
                            2
                                         1 2t y =
          39.  x +  2x 3/2  =  t +  , t  yt ++      4, t = 0
          40.  t =  ln (x t−  ),  y =  te t , t =  0


                            2
                          dy
          (41 − 37)  Find
                          dx 2


           41.  x t      −  2  y ( ) t =  t t−  3           43.  x t     2  +  1 y ( ) t =  2t −  1
                  ( ) t t=
                                                                   ( ) t=
                  ( )
                                              2
           42.  x t =  2sect   y ( ) t =  4 tant +          44.  x t =  ( )  2t −  2  1 y ( ) t =  2t +  3  t


                                                                                      −
          45.  Find an equation of the line tangent to cycloid  ( ) t =  x  t −  sin ,t  y ( ) t =  2 cost  at the points
               corresponding to t =  π   and t =  2π .
                                    6           3

          46.  Consider Lissajous curve, estimate the coordinates of the points on the curve at which there is

                                                   t
                         x = sin2 ,t  y =  2sin ; 0t  ≤≤  2π
                                                                  y

                                                                 2

                                                                 1
                                                                             x
                                                              1       1
                                                                 1
                                                                 2

               a)  A horizontal tangent line
               b)  A vertical tangent line.











                                                           376]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[47.  Consider Lissajous curve, estimate the coordinates of the points on the curve at which there is

                                                      t
                           x =  sin4 ,t  y = sin3 ; 0t  ≤≤  2π
                                                                    y

                                                                   1



                                                                                 x
                                                             1             1


                                                                   1
                  a)  A horizontal tangent line
                  b)  A vertical tangent line.


             (48 − 58)  Find the area of the region

                                               θ
             48.  x =  2sin θ  2  ,  y =  2sin θ  2  tan , 0 θ ≤  <  π
                                                            2

















             49.  x =  2cot ,θ  y =  2sin θ 2  , 0 θ ≤  π <


















             50.  Find the area under one arch of the cycloid  x =  ( at −  sint ),  y =  a (1 cost−  )


             51.  Find the area enclosed by the y−axis and the curve     x =  tt−  2 ,  y =  1 e+  t −

                                                                                    t
             52.  Find the area enclosed by the ellipse    x =  a cos ,t  y = b sin , 0t  ≤≤ 2π





                                                              377]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[3
                          x = b cost                                           a cos t
                                       ≤≤
          53.  Ellipse              0 t    2π               54.  Astroid    x =         0 t    2π
                                                                                            ≤≤
                          y =  a sint                                              3
                                                                             y =  a sin t
                                                                            

















                           x =  2 cosa  t − a cos2t                         x =  2 cosa  t +  a cos2t
          55.  Cardioid                         0 t    2π    56.  Deltoid      2 sina   a sin 2t  0 t≤≤  2π
                                                   ≤≤
                            y =  2 sina  t −  a sin 2t                       y =     t −

















                                                                                    a
                            x =  a sin 2t                   58.  Teardrop     x =  2 cost − a sin 2t  0 t≤≤  2π
          57.  Hourglass                0 t≤≤  2π                              y =  b sint
                             y =  b sint                                     




















          (59 − 68)  Find the lengths of the curves

                                           t π
                              t
          59.  x = cos ,t  y = + sin , 0t  ≤≤
          60.  x = t 3 ,  y =  3 t 2 ,0 t≤≤  3
                            2
          61.  x = 8cost + 8 sin ,t  t  y =  8sint − 8 cos , 0t  t  ≤≤  π
                                                           t
                                                               2
                                                           378]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[t
             62.  x =  ln (sect +  tant ) sin ,t−  y =  cos , 0t  ≤≤  π
                                                               3
             63.  Hypocycloid perimeter curve:  x =  a cos ,θ  y =  a sinθ


             64.  Circle circumference:  x =  a cos θ  3  ,  y =  a sin θ  3

             65.  Cycloid arch:  x =  ( a θ  sinθ −  ),  y =  a (1 cosθ −  )

             66.  Involute of a circle:  x =  cosθ θ+  sin ,θ  y =  sinθθ−  cosθ


                                           2
             67.  x t=  2 ,  y t=  3 ,0 t≤≤
                                                 t
             68.  x =  5sin , t  y =  5cos , t  − π  ≤≤  π
                                             3       2


             (69 − 80)  Find the areas of the surfaces generated by revolving the curves

                              =
                                        ≤
             69.  x =  1 t 3 ,  y t + 1, 1 t ≤  2,  y-axis
                      3
                                                       −
                                           ≤≤
             70.  x =  2 t 3/2 ,  y =  2 t , 0 t  3; x axis
                      3
                      t
             71.  x = +    2,  y =  t 2  +  2 , t  −  2 ≤≤  2;  y axis−
                                                     t
                                   2
                                       t
             72.  x =  2 ,t  y =  3; 0t  ≤≤ 3 x-axis

             73.  x =  2 ,t  y =  3; 0t  ≤≤ 3 y-axis
                                       t

                                         t
             74.  x t=  ,  y =  4 2; 0t−  ≤≤  2 x-axis

             75.  x t  ,  y = −        ≤≤   2     - y axis
                                         t
                    =
                             4 2; 0t
             76.  x   5cos , θ=  y =  5sin , 0 θ  ≤  ≤  π ,  - y axis
                                       θ
                                                   2
             77.  x =  a cos θ 3  ,  y =  a sin θ  3  , 0 θ ≤  π ≤  , x-axis
             78.  x =  a cos , θ  y =  b sin , 0 θ ≤  2π ≤
                                       θ
                        a)  x-axis       b)  y-axis

             79.  x =  2 ,t  y =  3, 0t  ≤≤  3
                                       t
                     a)  x-axis             b)  y-axis

             80.  x t=  ,  y =  4 2, 0t−  ≤≤  2
                                         t
                     a)  x-axis             b)  y-axis











                                                              379]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[3
          81.  Use the parametric equations  x =  t 2  3 and  y =  3t −  1 t  to
                                                                     3
                                                         3
               a)  Graph the curve on the interval  3 t−≤ ≤ .
                                  2
                        dy      dy
               b)  Find     and
                        dx       dx 2

               c)  Find the equation of the tangent line at the point  (  3,  8 )
                                                                       3
               d)  Find the length of the curve
               e)  Find the surface area generated by revolving the curve about the  x-axis


          82.  Use the parametric equations   x    ( a θ =  sinθ −  ) and  y =  a (1 cosθ −  ) a >  0
                                    2
                          dy       dy
                 a)  Find      and
                          dx       dx 2

                 b)  Find the equation of the tangent line at the point where θ =  π
                                                                              6
                 c)  Find all points (if any) of horizontal tangency.
                 d)  Determine where the curve is concave upward or concave downward.
                 e)  Find the length of one arc of the curve

          83.  The involute of a circle is described by the endpoint P of a string that is held taut as it is unwound
               from a spool that does not turn.
















                 Show that a parametric representation of the involute is

                                     x =  r (cosθ θ+  sinθ ) and  y =  r (sinθθ−  cosθ )


          84.  The figure shows a piece of string tied to a circle with a radius of one unit. The string is just long
               enough to reach the opposite side if the circle.










                 Find the area that is covered when the string is unwounded counterclockwise.

                                                           380]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[85.  An Air traffic controller spots two planes at the same altitude flying toward each other.














                  Their flight paths are 20° and 315°. One plane is 150 miles from point P with a speed of 375 miles
                  per hour. The other is 190 miles from point P with a speed of 450 miles per hour.

                                                                                                             0
                  a)  Find parameteric equations for the path of each plane where t is the time in hours, with t =
                      corresponding to the time at which the air traffic controller spots the planes.
                  b)  Use part (a) to write the distance between the planes as a function of t.
                  c)  Graph the function in part (b).
                  d)  When the distance between the planes be minimum?
                  e)  If the planes must keep a separation of at least 3 miles, is the requirement met?




















































                                                              381]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Section 4.3 – Polar Coordinates and Graphs




          Definition of Polar Coordinates
          To define polar coordinates, let an origin O (called the pole) and an initial ray from O. Then each point P
                                                                      )
          can be located by assigning to it a polar coordinate pair ( ,r θ  in which r gives the directed from O to P
          and θ gives the directed angle from the initial ray to yay OP.














          Polar Coordinates



















































                                                           382]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Example

                                                       (   π )
             Find all the polar coordinates of the point  P  2,  6

             Solution

                For  r =  2 ⇒   θ  =  π  ,  π  ±  2,π  π  ±  4,π  
                                    6   6        6


                For  r =  2 ⇒    θ −  =  −  5π  , −  5π  ±  2,π  5π  ±  4,π −  
                                        6      6           6


                The corresponding coordinate pairs of P are
                    (   π       )
                     2,  6  +  2 nπ  , n =  0, ±  1, ±  2, 


                And

                    ( −  2, −  5 6 π +  2 nπ ) , n =  0, ±  1, ±  2, 





             Polar Equations and Graphs

                  Equation       Graph

                      a
                  r =            Circle of radius  a  centered at O

                  θ   θ =        Line through O making an angle θ  with the initial ray
                        0                                         0































                                                              383]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Example


                                      ≤
          Graph the polar coordinate 1 r ≤  2 and    0 θ≤  ≤  π
                                                            2
          Solution














          Example


                                    −≤
          Graph the polar coordinate  3 r ≤  2 and θ =    π
                                                           4
          Solution




















          Example

                                                                          )
          Graph the polar coordinate   2π  ≤  θ ≤  5π  (no restriction on  r
                                     3         6
          Solution




















                                                           384]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Relating Polar and Cartesian Coordinates

             When we use both polar and Cartesian coordinates in a plane, we place the two origins together and take

                                                                          0
             the initial polar ray as the positive x-axis. The ray  θ =  π , r >  becomes the positive y-axis. The two
                                                                  2
             coordinate systems are then related by the following equations

             Equations Relating Polar and Cartesian Coordinates

                   x =  r cos ,θ   y = r sinθ
                
                  2    2    2           y
                 r =  x +  y  ,  tanθ =  x
                








                                  Polar equation                      Cartesian equation

                                             2
                                    r cosθ =                                 x =  2
                                 r 2 cos sinθ  θ  =  4                       xy =  4

                              r 2 cos θ  2  r 2 sin θ −  2  =  1          x −  2  y =  2  1

                                                                             2
                                                                       2
                                  r = 1 2 cosr+  θ                    y − 3x −  4x −=
                                                                                     10
                                   r = 1 cosθ−               x +  4  y +  4  2x y + 22  2x +  3  2xy −  2  y =  2  0



             Example


             Find a polar equation for the circle  x +  2  ( y −  ) 3  2  =  9

             Solution

                 x +  2  ( y −  ) 3  2  =  9

                  2
                       2
                 x +  y − 6y + 99=
                                                            2
                 x +  2  y −  2  6y =  0         x +  2  y =  2  r
                r −  2  6 sinr  θ =  0
                  ( rr −  6sinθ ) 0=

                r =  0   &  r =  6sinθ


                                                              385]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Example

          Replace the polar equation by equivalent Cartesian equation and identify the graph:  cosr  θ = − 4

          Solution
              r cosθ = − 4 ⇒    x = − 4

                                                  4
             The graph: Vertical line through  x = −


          Example

                                                                                            2
          Replace the polar equation by equivalent Cartesian equation and identify the graph:  r = 4 cosr  θ
          Solution

               2
              r =  4 cosr  θ
              x +  2  y =  2  4x

              x −  2  4x +  y =  2  0

              x −  2  4x  4 ++  y =  2  4

              ( x −  ) 2  2  +  y =  2  4   The graph: Circle with center (2, 0) and radius 2.















































                                                           386]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Symmetry Test for Polar Graphs


                                                            )
             1.  Symmetry about the x-axis: If the point ( ,r θ  lies on the graph, then the point ( , r θ −  )  or ( r −  ,πθ−  )
                lies on the graph.




















                                                            )
                                                                                                             ,
             2.  Symmetry about the y-axis: If the point ( ,r θ  lies on the graph, then the point ( ,r πθ−  )  or ( r θ−−  )
                lies on the graph.

















                                                            )
             3.  Symmetry about the origin: If the point ( ,r θ  lies on the graph, then the point ( r−  ,θ )  or ( ,r θ  π +  )
                lies on the graph.

























                                                              387]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Example

                             1 cosθ
          Graph the curve  r = −
          Solution
             The curve is symmetric about the x-axis:

             1 cos θ  −  ( ) 1 cosθ−  =  −  =  r


                    θ    r = 1 cosθ−

                    0         0
                   π          1
                    3         2
                   π          1
                    2
                   2π         3
                    3         2
                   π          2
















































                                                           388]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Example

                              2
             Graph the curve  r =  4cosθ
             Solution

                The curve is symmetric about the x-axis:
                     2
                    r =  4cosθ
                     2
                    r =  4cos ( ) θ−
                    ( ,r θ−  )

                The curve is symmetric about the origin:
                     2
                    r =  4cosθ

                    ( ) r −  2  =  4cosθ
                    ( r−  ,θ )

                Therefore, the curve is also symmetric about the y-axis.

                r =  2  4cosθ  ⇒  r =  ±  2 cosθ


                          θ     r = ± 2 cosθ

                          0          ± 2

                         ± π       ≈± 1.9
                           6


                         ± π       ≈± 1.7
                           4
                         ± π       ≈± 1.4
                           3


                         ± π         0
                           2



             A Technique for Graphing

                                                                                 )
             One way to graph a polar equation  r =  f  ( ) θ  is to make a table of ( ,r θ  values, plot the corresponding
             points, and connect them in order of increasing.

             Another method of graphing more reliable is

              1.  First graph  r =  f  ( ) θ  in the Cartesian  rθ −  plane,

              2.  Then use the Cartesian graph as a table and guide to sketch the polar coordinate graph.


                                                              389]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Example

                                        2
          Graph the lemniscate curve  r =   sin 2θ
          Solution



































                            θ         0        π         π          π         π    π       7π
                                               6          4         3         2             6


                       r = ±  sin 2θ   0  ±   3  ≈± .93   ± 1   ±  3  ≈± .93  0   0   ±    3  ≈± .93
                                              2                   2                       2

































                                                           390]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Exercises            Section 4.3 – Polar Coordinates



             1.   Find the Cartesian coordinates of the following points (given in polar coordinates)
                                                            (
                                                   π
                                              ) 0,
                     ) a   (  2,  π  4 )  ) b    ) c   ( )  ) d   −  2,  π  4 )
                                     (1, 0
                                                    2

             2.   Find the polar coordinates, 0 θ ≤  2π <  and  r ≥  0,  of the following points given in Cartesian
                  coordinates

                     ) a  (1, 1 )  b )  ( 3, 0−  )  c )  (  3, −  1 )  d )  ( 3, 4−  )


                                                  θ
             3.   Find the polar coordinates,  π − ≤ < π  and   r ≥  0 ,  of the following points given in Cartesian
                  coordinates
                                                               (5, −
                     ) a   −  ( 2,  −  ) 2  ) b  (0, 3   ) c )  −  (  3, 1   )  ) d     12 )

             (4 − 8)   Graph

             4.   1 r ≤                                7.    − π  4  ≤ θ ≤  3π  4  ,0 ≤ ≤ 1
                         2
                    ≤
                                                                                r
                    ≤
             5.   0 θ ≤   π , r ≥  0                                π
                                                              ≤
                          6                            8.    0 θ ≤  2 ,1≤   r ≤  2
             6.   θ =  π , r ≤
                               0
                       2

             (9 − 20)   Replace the polar equation with equivalent Cartesian equation and identify the graph
             9.   r cosθ =                   14.  r =       5                 18.  r =  2cosθ   2sinθ +
                           2
                            1
             10.  r sinθ = −                          sinθ   2cosθ −          19.  r sin ( 2π −  θ =  )  5
                                             15.  r =  4tan secθ  θ                       3
             11.  r = − 3secθ
                                             16.  r sinθ   lnr + lncosθ =     20.  r =        4
             12.  r cosθ   r sinθ +  =  1             2       2                         2cosθ   sinθ −

                    2
             13.  r =  4 sinr  θ             17.  cos θ    sin θ =

             (21 − 27)  Replace the Cartesian equation with equivalent polar equation
             21.  x =                        24.  xy = 1                      26.  x +  2  ( y −  ) 2  2  =  4
                      y

             22.  x −  2  y =  2  1          25.  x +  2  xy +  y =  2  1     27.  ( x +  ) 2  2  +  ( y −  ) 5  2  =  16

             23.   x 2  +  y 2  =  1
                   9     4

             28.  a) Show that every vertical line in the xy−plane has a polar equation of the form r =  a secθ
                  b) Find the analogous polar equation for horizontal lines in the xy−plane.


                                                              391]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[(29 − 34)  Identify the symmetries of the curves. Then sketch the curves.

         29.  r =  2 2cosθ−                31.  r =  2 sinθ+               33.  r = −  sinθ
                                                                                  2
                                                  2
          30.  r = 1 sinθ+                 32.  r =  sinθ                  34.  r = −   cosθ
                                                                                  2

          (35 − 37)  Graph the lemniscate. What symmetries do these curves have?

                                                 2
                 2
                                                                                  2
          35.  r =  4cos2θ                 36.  r =  4sin 2θ               37.  r = −  cos2θ

          (38 − 42)  Graph the limaçons is Old French for “snail”. Equations for limaçons have the form

                     r =  ab cosθ   or r =  ab   sinθ
                                              ±
                          ±
          38.  r =  1  +  cosθ             40.  r = 1 cosθ−                42.  r =  2 cosθ+
                   2                       41.  r =  3  − sinθ
          39.  r =  1  +  sinθ                      2
                   2

          (43 − 46)  Graph the equation

          43.  r = −               44.  r =  sin 2 θ         45.  r = 1 sinθ−         46.  r =   4sinθ
                                                                                             2
                   1 2sin3θ
                                                  2

          47.  Graph the nephroid of Freeth equation  r = +      θ
                                                         1 2sin
                                                                 2

          48.  Water flows in a shallow semicircular channel with inner and outer radii of 1 m and 2 m. At a point
                      )
               P ( ,r θ  in the channel, the flow is in the tangential direction (counterclockwise along circles), and
               it depends only on r, the distance from the center of the semicircles.














                 a)  Express the region formed by the channel as a set in polar coordinates.
                 b)  Express the inflow and outflow regions of the channel as sets in polar coordinates.
                                                                                                       2
                 c)  Suppose the tangential velocity of the water in m/s is given by  ( ) 10v r =  r , for 1 ≤≤ . Is the
                                                                                                    r
                                       (    π ) (        3π )
                    velocity greater at  1.5,    4   or  1.2,    4  ? Explain.

                 d)  Suppose the tangential velocity of the water is given by  ( ) r =  20  , for . Is the velocity greater
                                                                           v
                                                                                  r
                     ( 1.8,   π ) (    2π  ) ? Explain.
                                or  1.3,
                                        3
                           6

                                                           392]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[e)  The total amount of water that flows through the channel (across a cross section of the channel


                       θ   θ =  ) is proportional to  ∫ 2 v ( ) r dr . Is the total flow through the channel greater for the
                             0                     1
                       flow in part (c) or (d)?

             49.  A simplified model assumes that the orbits of Earth and Mars are circular with radii of 2 and 3,
                  respectively, and that Earth completes one orbit in one year while Mars takes two years. When t =  0
                  . Earth is at (2, 0    )  and Mars is at (3, 0   ); both orbit the Sum (at (0, 0   ) ) in the counterclockwise

                  direction.
                  The position of Mars relative to Earth is given by the parametric equations

                                      x =  (3 4cos t π −  )cos t π  +  2,  y =  (3 4cos t π −  )sin t π

                    a)  Graph the parametric equations, for 0 t≤≤
                                                                 2
                    b)  Letting  r =  3 4cos tπ−  , explain why the path of Mars relative to Earth is a limaçon.























































                                                              393]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Section 4.4 – Calculus in Polar Coordinates



          Slope


          The slope of a polar curve  r =  f  ( ) θ  in the xy-plane is still given by   dy  , which is not  r′ =  df
                                                                            dx                   dθ

                                     x   r cosθ =  f  ( )cos ,θ =  θ  y  r sinθ =  f  ( )sinθ =  θ

              dy  =  dy  / dθ
              dx   dx  / dθ
                    d  ( f  ( ) sinθ  •  ) θ
                 =  dθ
                    d  ( f  ( ) cosθ  ) θ
                   dθ        •
                    df  sinθ •  f θ +  ( ) cosθ •
                 =  dθ
                    df         f θ +
                   dθ   cosθ •   ( ) sinθ •


                   dy           f θ  ′ ( )sinθ  f θ+  ( )cosθ
                                =
                   dx  ( , r θ )  f θ  ′ ( )cosθ  f θ−  ( )sinθ





          Example

          Find the points on the interval  π −≤ θ  π ≤   at which the cardioid  r =  f θ  ( ) 1 cosθ = −   has a vertical or

          horizontal tangent line.
          Solution

              dy  =  f θ  ′ ( )sinθ  f θ+  ( ) cosθ

              dx    f θ  ′ ( ) cosθ  f θ−  ( )sinθ
                   sin sinθ  θ  +  (1 cosθ−  ) cosθ
                 =
                   sin cosθ  θ  −  (1 cosθ −  )sinθ


                 =     sin θ  2  cosθ +  cos θ −  2
                   sin cosθ  θ  sinθ −  cos sinθ +  θ

                 = 1 cos θ −  2  cosθ +  cos θ −  2
                       2sin cosθ  θ  sinθ −

                 =   2cos θ −  2  cosθ +  +  1
                     sinθ  (2cosθ  −  ) 1

                     (2cosθ −  1 )(cosθ +  −  ) 1
                 =
                       sinθ  (2cosθ  −  ) 1



                                                           394]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[The points with a horizontal tangent line:
                 dy  =  0
                 dx

                (2cosθ    1 )(cosθ +  −  ) 1 =  0

                        cosθ   −  1  →   θ =  =  ±  2π
                    →            2             3
                       
                         cosθ = 1     →   θ =  0   numerator i s  0
                       

                The points with a Vertical tangent line:
                sinθ  (2cosθ  −  ) 1 =  0


                        sinθ   0  →   θ =  =  0 , π±  denominator is  0
                    →          1             π
                       
                        cosθ   2    →   θ =  =  ±  3
                       

                 dy    lim    2cos θ −  2  cosθ +  +  1   0
                                   θ
                 dx  =    +    2cos sinθ   sinθ −    =  0
                      θ → 0                      
                                                       
                    =   lim      4cos sinθ 2  θ  2 sinθ −  
                      θ → 0 +    2sin θ −  2cos θ +  cosθ −  
                    =  0
                      1
                    = 0     Therefore, the curve has a slope of 0 at origin.






































                                                              395]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Area in the plane


          The region OTS is bounded by the rays θ   α =  and θ    β =   and the curve  r =  f  ( ) θ .
























          We approximate the region with n non-overlapping fan-shaped circular sectors based on a partition P of
                                                        ( )
          angle TOS. The typical sector has radius  r =  f θ   and central angle of radian measure  θ . Its area is
                                                                                                 ∆
                                                  k       k                                         k
          ∆ θ
             k   times the area of a circle of radius  r , or
           2π                                     k

                                             A =  1 r ∆  2  θ  1 (  f θ =  ( )) 2 ∆  θ
                                              k   2 k    k   2      k       k



          Area of the Fan-Shaped Region between the Origin and the curve  r =        f θ  ( ), α  θ ≤  β ≤



                                                  A =  1 ∫ β ( f  ( )) dθ  2  θ
                                                      2  α

          This is the integral of the area differential

                                               dA =  1 r dθ  2  1 ( f  ( )) dθ =  2  θ
                                                    2         2






















                                                           396]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Example


             Find the area of the region in the plane enclosed by the cardioid  r =  ( 2 1 cosθ+  )

             Solution


                             2
                 A =  1 ∫ 2π rdθ

                     2  0

                  =  1 ∫  2π  ( 4 1 cosθ+  ) dθ  2
                    2   0



                  =  ∫ 0 2π 2 1 2cosθ+  (  +  cos θ  2  ) dθ




                  =  ∫ 0 2π ( 2 4cosθ  +  2 1 cos2θ+  2  ) dθ +




                  =  ∫ 0 2π (3 4cosθ+  +  cos2θ  )dθ



                  =  3θ  4sinθ +  1  sin 2  θ +  2π
                                 2        0


                                                                            0
                  =        3 2π  ( ) 4sin 2π +  ( ) +  1 sin 2π  ( ) ( 3 ( ) 4sin0 +  ( ) 0 +  1 sin ( ))     
                                                   −
                                         2
                                                                      2
                  =  6π




































                                                              397]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Area of the Region  0 ≤  r  ( ) θ  ≤  r ≤  r  ( ),θ  α  θ ≤  β ≤
                                   1           2



                                       A = ∫  α  β  1  rdθ  2 2  ∫  α  β  1  rdθ −  1 2
                                                             2
                                               2


                                                   2
                                        =  1 ∫  β ( r − r 2 ) dθ
                                           2  α   2    1























          Example

          Find the area of the region that lies inside the circle  r = 1 and outside the cardioid  r = 1 cosθ−

          Solution


                             2
              A =  1 ∫ π /2  ( r − r 2 )  dθ
                  2  − π /2  2   1



               =  2  1 ∫ π /2 ( 1 −  2  (1 cosθ−  ) 2 ) dθ
                   2  0


                 ∫  π /2   ( (             2  ))
                             −
               =   0    1−  1 2cosθ   +  cos θ  dθ

                 ∫  π /2 (       1   1       )
               =   0    2cosθ  −−    2 cos2θ  dθ
                                 2



               =  2sinθ   1 θ −  −  1 sin 2  θ  π /2
                          2    4        0

               =  2sin π  −  1 π  −  1 sin 2 π  −  0
                      2   2 2   4     2
                 2
               = −   π   unit 2
                     4
                                                           398]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Length of a Polar Curve

                                                                                            )
             If  r =  f  ( ) θ  has a continuous first derivative for  α ≤ θ ≤β   and if the point  ( , Pr θ  traces the curve
             r =  f  ( ) θ  exactly once as θ  runs from α to β, then the length of the curve is


                                                       ∫ β     2   ( )  2
                                                                    dr
                                                   L =        r +   dθ    dθ


                                                        α
             Example

             Find the length of the cardioid  r = 1 cosθ−

             Solution


                r =  1 cosθ  −  ⇒  dr  =  sinθ
                                   dθ
                       dr
                r +  2  ( ) 2  (1 cosθ=  −  ) +  2  sin θ  2
                      dθ
                            =  1 2cosθ −  cos θ +  2  sin θ +  2                     cos θ  2  sin θ +  2  =  1
                            =  2 2cosθ−


                    ∫  β   2   ( )  2  dθ                                                          2 θ
                                dr
                 L =  α   r +   dθ                                                   1 cosθ−  =  2sin  2



                    ∫  2π  2 2cos  d
                  =   0      −     θθ



                    ∫  2π  4sin 2 θ
                  =   0          2   dθ




                    ∫  2π     θ
                  =   0   2sin  dθ
                              2



                          θ
                  = − 4cos    2π
                           2  0
                       (
                  =  −  4 cos  2π −  c s0o  )
                            2
                         11
                       ( 4
                  = − −−     )
                  = 8 u   nit




                                                              399]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Area of a Surface of Revolution

          Theorem

          Let  f  be a function whose derivative is continuous on an interval α  θ ≤  β ≤   .

          The area of the surface formed by revolving the graph of  r =  f  ( ) θ  about the indicated line


                               ∫  β  ( ) sinθ  (      2     ′ ( )) 2       About the polar axis
                        S = 2π  α  f θ           f θ  ( )) + ( f θ  dθ



                               ∫  β  ( ) cosθ   (      2     ′ ( )) 2       About the line  =  π
                                                                                           θ
                        S = 2π     f θ            f θ  ( )) + ( f θ  dθ                        2

                                α

          Example


          Find the area of the surface formed by revolving the circle  ( ) cosf θ  θ =   about the line θ =  π
                                                                                                  2






















          Solution

                        2
                2
                     r′
               r +  ( ) =    cos θ  2  sin θ +  2
                          = 1


                            2
                                d
              S =  2π ∫ 0 π cos θθ

                   ∫ π
               = π   0  (1 cos2θ+  ) dθ


                   (    1      )  π
               = πθ +   2  sin 2θ     0


                         2
               = π 2    unit

                                                           400]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Exercises            Section 4.4 – Calculus in Polar Coordinates



             (1 – 4)  Find the slopes of the curves at the given points. Sketch the curves along with their tangents at
                      these points.
             1.   Cardioid   r = −+          θ  = ±  π
                                  1 cos ; θ
                                                   2
                                  1 sin ; θ
             2.   Cardioid   r = −+          θ   0, π =
             3.   Four leaved rose r =     sin2 ; θ  θ  =  ±  π  ,  ±  3π
                        −
                                                         4     4
             4.   Four leaved rose r =     cos2 ; θ  θ  =  0,  ±  π , π
                        −
                                                             2

             5.   Find the area of the region bounded by the spiral  r θ =  for  0 θ ≤  π ≤

















             6.   Find the area of the region bounded by the circle  r =  2sinθ  for  π  ≤  θ  ≤  π
                                                                                   4       2


















             7.   Find the area of the region inside one leaf of the three-leaved rose  r =  cos3θ

















                                                              401]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[(8 − 66)   Find the area of the region


          8.   Inside oval limaçon  r =  4 2sinθ+

          9.   Inside Cardioid  r =  a (1 cosθ+  ), a >  0

                                      2
          10.  Inside Six-leaved rose  r =  2sin3θ

          11.  Inside curve  r =  cosθ

          12.  Inside right lobe of  r =  cos 2θ
          13.  Inside Cardioid  r =  4 4sinθ+

          14.  Inside Limaçon  r =  2 cosθ+

                               6
          15.  Inside circle  r =  above the line  r =  3cscθ
          16.  Inside inner loop  r =  cosθ −  1
                                           2

          17.  Inside One leave of  r =  cos3θ
          18.  Shared by the circles  r =  2cosθ  and  r =  2sinθ

                                                                       )
                                                                −
          19.  Shared by the circle  r =  and the cardioid  r =  ( 2 1 cosθ
                                       2
          20.  Enclosed by the four-leaf rose  r =  f  ( ) θ  2cos2θ =

          21.  Lies inside the circle  r = 1 and outside the cardioid  r = 1 cosθ+

          22.  Outside the circle  r =  1   and inside the circle  r =  cosθ
                                     2

          23.  Outside the circle  r =  1   and inside the curve  r =  cosθ
                                      2

          24.  Inside the circle  r =  1   in  IQ  and inside the right lobe of  r =  cos 2θ
                                     2

                                                                 2
          25.  Inside the rose  r =  4sin2θ  and inside the circle  r =
                                     2
          26.  Inside the lemniscate  r =  2sin2θ  and outside the circle  r = 1
          27.  Inside all the leaves of the rose  r = 3sin 2θ

          28.  Inside one leaf of the rose  r =  cos5θ
          29.  A complete three-leaf rose  r =  2cos3θ

          30.  Inside the rose  r =  4cos 2θ  and outside the circle  r =
                                                                   2
                                           2
          31.  Bounded by the lemniscate  r =  6sin 2θ
          32.  Bounded by the limaçon r =  2 4sinθ−

          33.  Bounded by the limaçon  r =  4 2cosθ−

          34.  Inside one leaf:   r =  2sin6φ
                                                           402]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[35.  Between inner and outer:   r =  3 6cos−  φ

             36.  Inner loop of    r = 1 2cosθ+

             37.  Inner loop of    r =  2 4cosθ−
             38.  Inner loop of    r = 1 2sinθ+

             39.  Inner loop of    r =  4 6sinθ−

             40.  Between the loops   r = 1 2cosθ+
                                                         )
                                                 +
             41.  Between the loops       r =  ( 2 1 2sinθ
             42.  Between the loops   r = 3 6sinθ−

             43.  Between the loops   r =  1  +  cosθ
                                         2

             44.  Inside  r =  2cosθ  and outside   r = 1
             45.  Inside  r =  3sinθ  and outside   r = 1 sinθ+

             46.  Common interior of   r =  4sin2θ  and  r =
                                                          2
             47.  Common interior of   r =  4sinθ  and  r =
                                                         2
             48.  Common interior of  r =  2cosθ  and  r =  2sinθ

             49.  Common interior of      r =  ( 2 1 cosθ  +  ) and  r =  ( 2 1 cosθ  −  )

                                             3 2sinθ
             50.  Common interior of      r = −          and   r = −+
                                                                    3 2sinθ
             51.  Common interior of      r =  53sinθ  −  and  r =  53cosθ  −

                                       )
                                +
             52.  Inside  r =  a (1 cosθ  and outside  r =  a cosθ
                                                    a
             53.  Inside  r =  2 cosa  θ  and outside  r =
                                                    )
                                             +
             54.  Common interior of  r =  a (1 cosθ  and  r =  a sinθ
                                                                           0
             55.  Common interior of  r =  a cosθ  and  r =  a sinθ , where  a >  .
             56.  Enclosed by all the leaves of the rose  r = 3sin 4θ
             57.  Enclosed by the limaçon  r =  2 cosθ−

             58.  Inside limaçon  r =  2 cosθ+   and outside the circle   r =
                                                                         2
                                     2
             59.  Inside lemniscate  r =  4cos 2θ  and outside the circle   r =  1
                                                                           2
             60.  Inside both cardioids  r = 1 cosθ−   and  r = 1 cosθ+

             61.  Inside the cardioid  r = 1 cosθ+   and outside the cardioid  r = 1 cosθ−
             62.  Inside both cardioids   r =  2 2sin−  θ  and  r =  2 2sin+  θ

             63.  common interior of      r =  2 2sin−  θ  and  r =  2 2sin+  θ

             64.  Inside both cardioids   r = 1 sin+  θ  and  r = 1 cos+  θ

                                                              403]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[65.  Common interior   r =  1 and  r  =  2 cos2θ


          66.  Outside r = 1 and inside  r  =  2 cos2θ


          (67 − 89)  Find the length of

          67.  r θ  =  2 ,0 θ  ≤  ≤  5                    78.  r =  ( 8 1 cosθ+  ) 0 θ ≤  2π ≤


          68.  r =  e θ ,0 θ ≤   π ≤                      79.  r =  2θ  0 θ  ≤  ≤  π
                                                                                2
                     2                                                           π
                         ( )
          69.  r =  a sin 2 θ  , 0 θ ≤  π ≤  , a >  0     80.  r =  secθ  0 θ  ≤  ≤  3
                          2
                                                                   1
          70.  r =     6   ,0 θ≤    ≤  π                  81.  r =  θ  π   θ ≤  2π ≤
                   1 cosθ+            2                             θ
                                                                 =
          71.  r =  cos 3 θ  ( ) , 0 θ≤  ≤  π  4          82.  r e      0 θ ≤  π ≤
                         3
                                                          83.  r =  5cosθ   π   θ ≤  π ≤
                                                                            2
          72.  r =  1 sin 2 , 0 θ ≤     π ≤  2
                            θ
                      +
                                                          84.  r =  ( 3 1 cosθ−  ) 0 θ ≤  π ≤
          73.  r =  80 θ ≤    2π ≤
                                                          85.  r =  2sin6φ  one petal
          74.  r =  a  0 θ ≤  2π ≤
                                                          86.  Inner loop  r = 3 6cosφ−
          75.  r =  4sinθ  0 θ ≤   π ≤


          76.  r =  2 cosa  θ  −  π  ≤  θ  ≤  π           87.  r =  e 2θ  0 θ≤  ≤  2
                               2       2                  88.  r =  cosθ

          77.  r =  1 sinθ +  0 θ ≤  2π ≤
                                                                              )
                                                                       −
                                                          89.  r =  a (1 cosθ

          (90 − 95)  Find the surface area bounded by

          90.  r =  6cosθ  0 θ  ≤  ≤  π  revolving about Polar axis
                                   2

          91.  r =  a cosθ  0 θ  ≤  ≤  π  revolving about θ  =  π
                                   2                       2
          92.  r e=  aθ  0 θ  ≤  π  revolving about θ ≤  =  π
                                 2                       2

          93.  r =  a (1 cosθ+  ) 0 θ ≤  π ≤  revolving about polar axis
          94.  r =  1 4cosθ+  0 θ  ≤  ≤  π  revolving about Polar axis
                                      2

          95.  r =  2sinθ  0 θ  ≤  ≤  π  revolving about θ  =  π
                                   2                       2


                                                                                            2
          96.  Find the surface area of the torus generated by revolving the circle given by  r =  about the line
               r = 5secθ


                                                           404]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[a
             97.  Find the surface area of the torus generated by revolving the circle given by r =  about the line
                  r =  b secθ , where 0 a b< <

             98.  Let a and b be positive constants. Find the area of the region in the first quadrant bounded by the
                  graph of the polar equation

                                                r =       ab       ,0 θ ≤    π
                                                                       ≤
                                                    a sinθ  b cosθ +         2

             99.  Assume m is a positive integer
                   a)  Even number of leaves: what is the relationship between the total area enclosed by the 4m-leaf
                                        )
                      rose  r =  cos (2mθ  and m?
                   b)  Odd number of leaves: what is the relationship between the total area enclosed by the (2m +  ) 1 -

                      leaf rose  r =  cos  ( ( 2m + 1 ) ) θ  and m?


             100.  Let  R  be the region bounded by the nth turn and the (n +  ) 1 st  turn of the spiral  r =  e − θ  in the
                        n
                                                    0
                  first and second quadrants, for θ ≥

                    a)  Find the area  A  of  R .
                                      n      n
                    b)  Evaluate  lim A
                                 n→∞    n
                                        A
                    c)  Evaluate  lim    n+ 1
                                 n→∞     A n




             101.  The curve represented by the equation  r =  ae bθ , where a and b are constants, is called a logarithmic
                  spiral. The figure shows the graph of  r e=  θ /6 .  2π−  θ ≤  2π ≤  . Find the area of the shaded region.



























                                                              405]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[102.  The larger circle in the figure is the graph of  r = 1.



















               Find the polar equation of the smaller circle such that the shaded regrions are equal.

          103.  Find equations of the circles in the figure.

















                 Determine whether the combined area of the circles is greater than or less than the area of the
                 region inside the square but outside the circles.


          104.  A circular corral of unit radius is enclosed by a fence. A goat inside the corral is tied to the fence
               with a rope of length 0 ≤  a ≤  2 .






















                 What is the area of the region (inside the corral) that the goat can graze? Check your answer with
                                                2
                                      0
                 the special cases  a =  and  a =


                                                           406]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[105.  A circular corral of unit radius is enclosed by a fence. A goat outside the corral is tied to the fence
                  with a rope of length 0 a π≤ ≤  . What is the area of the grassy region (outside the corral) that the
                  goat can reach?





















             106.  A circular concrete slab of unit radius is surrounded by grass. A goat is tied to the edge of the slab
                  with a rope of length 0 ≤  a ≤  2 .

















                    What is the area of the grassy region that the goat can graze? Note that the rope can extend over
                                                                                  0
                    the concrete slab. Check your answer with the special cases  a =  and  a =
                                                                                            2

             107.  When recording live performance, sound engineers often use a microphone with a cardioid pickup
                  pattern because it suppresses noise from the audience. Suppose the microphone is placed 4 m from
                  the front of the stage and the boundary of the optimal pickup region is given by the cardioid
                  r =  8 8sinθ+  , where r if measured in meters and the microphone is at the pole.

















                    The musicians want to know the area they will have on stage within the optimal pickup range of
                    the microphone, Answer their question.

                                                              407]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[108.  The curve given by the parametric equations            (    2 )


                                           x ( ) t =  1 t −  2  and  y ( ) t =  t  1 t −
                                                   +
                                                 1 t  2                1 t 2
                                                                         +
                 a)  Find the rectangular equation of the strophoid.
                 b)  Find a polar equation of the strophoid.
                 c)  Sketch a graph of the strophoid.
                 d)  Find the equations of the two tangent lines at the origin.
                 e)  Find the points on the graph at which the tangent lines are horizontal.

          109.  Let a polar curve be described by  r =  f  ( ) θ  and let l  be the line tangent to the curve at the point

                                 )
                      )
               P ( ,x y =  P ( ,r  θ
















                                        dy
               a)  Explain why  tanα =
                                        dx
                                       y
               b)  Explain why  tan =θ
                                       x
                                                                                         f  ( ) θ
               c)  Let ϕ  be the angle between l  and the line O and P. Prove that  tanϕ =
                                                                                        f ′ ( ) θ

                                                                                               f  ( ) θ
               d)  Prove that the value of θ for which l  is parallel to the x-axis satisfy  tanθ = −
                                                                                              f ′ ( ) θ

                                                                                             f ′ ( ) θ
               e)  Prove that the value of θ for which l  is parallel to the y-axis satisfy  tanθ =
                                                                                             f  ( ) θ




















                                                           408]]></page></pages></Search>