<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="86"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Lecture One




             Section 1.1 – Propositional Logic



             Introduction

             The rules of logic give precise meaning to mathematical statements. These rules are used to distinguish
             between valid and invalid mathematical arguments.
             The logic rules are used in the design of computer circuits, the construction of computer programs, and
             the verification of the correctness of programs.


             Propositions

             A proposition is a declarative sentence (that is, a sentence that declares a fact) that is either true or false,
             but not both.

             All the following declarative sentences are propositions
                  Washington, D.C. is the capital of the United States of America.   True

                  1 + 1 = 2                                                         True

                  2 + 2 = 3                                                         False


             Example

             Consider the following sentences
                1.  What time is it?
                2.  Read this carefully
                3.  x +=
                       12
                4.  x +=
                        y
                           z
             Solution

                Sentences 1 and 2 are not propositions because they are not declarative sentences.
                Sentences 3 and 4 are not propositions because they are not true (T) or false (F).


             Definition

             Let p be a proposition. The negation of p, denoted by  p¬  (also denoted by  p ), is the statement

                “It is not the case that p.”
             The proposition  p¬  is read “not p”. The truth value of the negation of p,  p¬ , is the opposite of the truth
             value of p.


                                                               1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Example

          Find the negation of the proposition:  “Michael’s PC runs Linux” and express this in simple English.

          Solution

             The negation:  Michael’s PC does not run Linux


          Example

          Find the negation of the proposition:  “Vandana’s smartphone has at least 32GB of memory” and express
          this in simple English.
          Solution

             The negation:  Vandana’s smartphone has less than 32GB of memory
                             Vandana’s smartphone does not have at least 32GB of memory


          Table:  Truth table of the Negation of a Proposition

                                                       p        ¬ p

                                                       T         F
                                                      F          T


          Definition


          Let p and q be propositions. The conjunction of p and q, denoted by  pq∧ , is the proposition “p and q.“
          The conjunction  pq∧  p and q is true for both are true and it’s false otherwise.


          Example

          Find the conjunction of the propositions p and q where p is the proposition “your PC has more than 16GB
          free hard disk space” and q is the proposition “your PC processor runs faster than 1 GHz.”

          Solution
             The conjunction is  pq∧  and can be expressed as:

                   Your PC has more than 16GB free hard disk space and its processor runs faster than 1 GHz.

             For this conjunction to be true, both conditions given must be true.
             It is false when one or both of these conditions are false.








                                                            2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Definition

             Let p and q be propositions. The disjunction of p and q, denoted by  pq∨ , is the proposition “p or q.“
             The disjunction  pq∨  is false when both p and q are false and it’s true otherwise.



                          Truth Table for the Conjunction          Truth Table for the Disjunction of
                               of Two Propositions.                       Two Propositions.
                                                                                            ∨
                                                 ∧
                            p        q         pq                    p         q          pq
                            T        T           T                   T        T             T
                            T        F           F                   T        F             T
                            F        T           F                   F        T             T

                            F        F           F                   F        F            F



             Example

             Find the disjunction of the propositions p and q where p is the proposition “your PC has more than 16GB
             free hard disk space” and q is the proposition “your PC processor runs faster than 1 GHz.”
             Solution

                                    ∨
                The disjunction is  p q  and can be expressed as:
                  Your PC has more than 16GB free hard disk space, or the processor in your PC runs faster than 1
                    GHz.


             Definition

             Let p and q be propositions. The exclusive or of p and q, denoted by  p ⊕ , is the proposition that is true
                                                                                   q
             when exactly one of p and q is true and is false otherwise.


                          Truth Table for the Exclusive Or          Truth Table for the Conditional
                               of Two Propositions.                       Statement  →p  q .

                            p        q         p ⊕q                  p        q          p  → q

                            T        T           F                   T        T            T

                            T        F           T                   T        F            F

                            F        T           T                   F        T            T

                            F        F           F                   F        F            T









                                                               3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Definition

                                                                     q
          Let p and q be propositions. The conditional statement  p → , is the proposition “if p, then q.” The
                                    q
          conditional statement  p →  is false when p is true and q is false, and true otherwise. In the conditional
                         q
          statement  p → , p called the hypothesis (or antecedent or premise) and q is called the conclusion (or
          consequence).

                        If p, then q                          p implies q

                        If p, q                               p only if q

                        p is sufficient for q                 a sufficient condition for q is p

                        q if p                                q whenever p
                        q when p                              q necessary for p

                        a necessary condition for p is q      q follows from p

                        q unless  p
                                 ¬


          Example

          Let p be the statement “Maria learns discrete mathematics” and q the statement “Maria will find a good
                                          q
          job”. Express the statement  p →  as a statement in English.
          Solution

                  q
              p →  represents the statement:
                   If Maria learns discrete mathematics, then she will find a good job.
             There are many other way to express this conditional statement.
                   Maria will find a good job when she learns discrete mathematics.
                   For Maria to get a good job, it is sufficient for her to learn discrete mathematics.
                   Maria will find a good job unless she does not learn discrete mathematics.


          Example


          What is the value of the variable x after the statement
                 if   22+=  4 then      : x =+ 1
                                           x
          If  x =  before the statement is encountered? (The symbol := stands for assignment. The statement
                0
            : x = + 1 means the assignment of the value of  x + 1 to x.)
              x
          Solution
                                                                   x
             Because 2 + 2 = 4 is true, the assignment statement  :x = + 1 is executed.
             Hence, x has the value  01 1+=  after this statement is encountered.



                                                            4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Converse, Contrapositive, and Inverse.

                                  q
             The converse of  p →  is the proposition q →  p
                                                                   p
             The contrapositive of  p →  is the proposition  q¬ → ¬
                                       q
             The inverse of  p →  is the proposition  p¬ → ¬ q
                                q


             Example

             What are the contrapositive, the converse, and the inverse of the conditional statement:
                    “The home team wins whenever it is raining ? ”

             Solution

                Because “q whenever p” is one of these ways to express the conditional statement  p → , the original
                                                                                                     q
                statement can be written as

                      If it is raining, then the home team wins.

                The contrapositive of this conditional statement is:
                      If the home team does not win, then it is not raining.

                The converse:     If the home team wins, then it is raining.


                The inverse:      If it is not raining, then the home team does not win.

                Only the contrapositive is equivalent to the original statement.


             Definition

             Let p and q be propositions.
                                              q
             The biconditional statement  p ↔  is the proposition “p if and only if  q.”
             The biconditional statement  p ↔  is true when p and q have the same truth values, and is false
                                             q
             otherwise.

             Biconditional statements are also called bi-implications.
                p is necessary and sufficient for q
                If p then q, and conversely
                p iff q

                      q
                 p ↔  has exactly the truth value as ( p →  q ) (q∧  →  ) p












                                                               5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Example

          Let p be the statement “You can take the flight,” and let q be the statement “You buy a ticket.” Then
          p ↔  q is the statement:  “You can take the flight if and only if you buy a ticket.”

          Solution

             This statement is true if p and q are either both true or false, that is, if you buy a ticket and can take the
             flight or if you do not buy a ticket and you cannot take the flight.
             It is false when p and q have opposite truth values, that is, when you do not buy a ticket, but you can
             take the flight, and when you buy a ticket but you cannot take the flight.



          Truth Tables of Compound Propositions

          Example


          Construct the truth table of the compound proposition ( p ∨¬  ) q → ( pq∧  )

          Solution

                                                                                 )
                                                     ∧
                 p     q     ¬q      p ∨¬q         pq         ( ∨¬q    ) → pq
                                                                           ( ∧
                                                                p
                T      T      F         T            T                 T
                T      F      T         T           F                  F

                F      T      F         F           F                  T

                F      F      T         T           F                  F



          Precedence of Logical Operators

                  Precedence of Logical Operators

                     Operator         Precedence
                        ¬                 1

                        ∧                 2

                        ∨                 3

                        →                 4

                        ↔                 5


              pqr∧∨  means ( pq∧     ) r∨




                                                            6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Logic and Bit Opertions


             Definition

             A bit string is a sequence of zero or more bits. The length of this string is the number of bits in the string.



                                                       True Value    Bit
                                                            T         1

                                                           F          0




                Bit Operators OR, AND, and XOR

               x    y    x ∨ y    x  ∧ y     x ⊕ y
               0    0      0        0          0

               0    1      1        0          1
               1    0      1        0          1

               1    1      1        1          0











































                                                               7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Exercises  Section 1.1 – Propositional Logic



          1.   Which of these sentences are propositions? What are truth values of those that are propositions?

                 a)  Boston is the capital of Massachusetts.
                 b)  Miami is the capital of Florida
                 c)  23 5+=
                 d)  5 7 10+=
                        2 11
                 e)  x +=
                 f)  Answer this question
                 g)  Do not pass go
                 h)  What time is it?
                 i)  The moon is made of green cheese
                      n
                 j)  2 ≥  100

          2.   What is the negation if each of these propositions?

                 a)  Mei has an MP3 player
                 b)  There is no pollution in Texas
                 c)  21 3+=
                 d)  There are 13 items in a baker’s dozen,
                 e)  121 is a perfect square

          3.   Suppose the Smartphone A has 256 MB RAM and 32 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 8
               MP; Smartphone B has 288 MB RAM and 64 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 4 MP;
               Smartphone C has 128 MB RAM and 32 GB ROM, and the resolution of its camera is 5 MP.
               Determine the truth value of each of these propositions.
                 a)  Smartphone B has the most RAM of these three smartphones
                 b)  Smartphone C has more ROM or higher resolution camera than Smartphone B.
                 c)  Smartphone B has more RAM, more ROM, and a higher resolution camera than Smartphone
                    A.
                 d)  If Smartphone B has more RAM and more ROM than Smartphone C, then it also has a higher
                    resolution camera.
                 e)  Smartphone A has more RAM than Smartphone B if and only if Smartphone B has more RAM
                    than Smartphone A.

          4.   Let p and q be the proposition
                        p: I bought a lottery ticket this week

                        q: I won the million dollar jackpot
                                                                     q
                   ) a  ¬  p            ) b  pq∨             ) c  p →              ) d  pq∧
                                                     q
                                                                                        p
                                                                         q
                  ) e  p ↔              ) f  ¬  p → ¬         ) g  ¬  p ∧¬         ) h  ¬∨ ( pq∧  )
                           q

                                                            8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[5.   Let p and q be the proposition
                           p: Swimming at the New Jersey shore is allowed

                           q: Sharks have been spotted new the shore
                                                                                                q
                                                                     pq
                     ) a  ¬ q              ) b  pq∧             ) c  ¬∨               ) d  p → ¬
                          q
                                                        q
                                                                            q
                     ) e  ¬→   p           ) f  ¬  p → ¬         ) g  p ↔¬            ) h  ¬ p ∧ ( p ∨¬  ) q

             6.   Let p, q  and r be the proposition
                           p: You have the flu
                           q: You miss the final examination
                           r: You pass the course

                  Express each of these proposition as an English sentence

                                                                                           ∨∨
                                                q
                                                                          r
                             q
                     ) a  p →              ) b  ¬↔  r           ) c  q → ¬            ) d  pqr
                     ) e  ( p → ¬ r ) (q∨  → ¬  ) r       ) f  ( pq∧  ) ( qr∨¬ ∧  )

             7.   Determine whether each of these conditional statements is true or false.

                    a)  If 11 2+= , then 2 + 2 = 5
                    b)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then 2 + 2 = 4

                    c)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then 2 + 2 = 5
                    d)  If monkeys can fly, then 1 + 1 = 3

                    e)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then unicorns exist

                    f)  If 1 + 1 = 3, then dogs can fly
                    g)  If 1 + 1 = 2, the dogs can fly

                    h)  If 2 + 2 = 4, then 1 + 2 = 3

             8.   Write each of these propositions in the form “p if and only if q” in English
                    a)  If it is hot outside you buy an ice cream cone, and if you buy an ice cream cone it is hot
                       outside.
                    b)  For you to win the contest it is necessary and sufficient that you have only winning ticket.
                    c)  You get promoted only if you have connections, and you have connections only if you get
                       promoted.
                    d)  If you watch television your mind will decay, and conversely.
                    e)  The trains run late on exactly those days when I take it.
                    f)  For you to get an A in this course, it is necessary and sufficient that you learn how to solve
                       discrete mathematics problems.
                    g)  If you read the newspaper every day, you will be informed, and conversely.
                    h)  It rains if it is a weekend day, and it is a weekend day if it rains.
                    i)  You can see the wizard only if the wizard is not in, and the wizard is not in only if you can see
                       him


                                                               9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[(9 – 28)   Construct a truth table for each of these compound propositions.

           9.    p ∧¬                                      20.  ( pq∧  ) →  ( pq∨  )
                      p
           10.  p ∨¬                                       21.  (q → ¬   ) p ↔  ( p ↔  ) q
                      p
                       p
           11.  p → ¬
                                                           22.  ( p →  q ) ( p∨¬ →  ) q
                       p
           12.  p ↔¬
                                                           23.  ( p →  q ) ( p∧¬ →  ) q
           13.  p → ¬
                       q
                                                           24.  ( pq∨  ) r∨
                       q
                  p
           14.  ¬↔
                             q
           15.  ( p ∨¬  ) q →                              25.  ( pq∨  ) r∧
           16.  ( pq∨  ) →  ( pq∧  )                       26.  ( pq∧  ) r∨

                            ( q
           17.  ( p →   ) q ↔ ¬ → ¬    ) p                 27.  ( pq∧  ) r∧
                                                                            r
           18.  ( p →   ) q →  (q →  ) p                   28.  ( pq∨  ) ∧¬

                           )
           19.   p ⊕  ( pq
                       ∨


















































                                                            10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Section 1.2 – Propositional Equivalences




             Introduction

             An important type of step used in a mathematical argument is the replacement of a statement with another
             statement with the same truth value.


             Definition

             A compound proposition that is always true, no matter what the truth values of the proposition variables
             that occur in it, is called a tautology. A compound proposition that is always false is called contradiction.
             A compound proposition that is neither a tautology nor a contradiction is called a contingency.


             Example

                   p     ¬p      p ∨¬p        p ∧¬p

                   T      F         T           F

                   F      T         T           F

                      p
                 p ∨¬  is always true, it is tautology
                      p
                 p ∧¬  is always false, it is contradiction.



             Logical Equivalences

             Definition

                                                                                 q
             Compound propositions p and q are called logically equivalent if  p ↔  is a tautology. The notation
             p q≡  denotes that p and q are logically equivalent.


                                                      De Morgan’s Laws

                                                      ¬ ( pq∧  ) ≡ ¬ ∨¬
                                                                   p
                                                                        q
                                                                   p
                                                                        q
                                                      ¬ ( pq∨  ) ≡ ¬ ∧¬













                                                              11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Example

                                         q
          Show that  ( pq¬  ∨  )  and  p¬ ∧¬  are logically equivalent.
          Solution

                                            )
                p     q    pq        ( ∨ pq     ¬p   ¬q       ¬ ∧¬p  q
                             ∨   ¬
                T     T      T         F         F      F        F

                T     F      T         F         F      T        F

                F     T      T         F         T      F        F
                F     F      F         T         T      T        T

             The truth table shows that  ( pq¬  ∨  ) ↔ ¬ ∧¬  is a tautology and these compound propositions are
                                                          q
                                                     p
             logically equivalent.


          Example

          Show that  p →  and  pq¬∨  are logically equivalent.
                         q
          Solution

                p    q    ¬p      ¬∨pq       p → q

               T     T     F        T          T

               T     F     F        F          F
               F     T     T        T          T
               F     F     T        T          T

                                            q
             The truth table shows that  p →  and  pq¬∨  are logically equivalent.


          Example

          Show that  p ∨  (qr∧  )  and ( pq∨  ) ( pr∧  ∨  ) are logically equivalent. This is the distributive law of
          disjunction over conjunction.

          Solution

                                                        )
                                       ∧
                 p      q      r      qr        ∨ p  ( ∧ qr    pq       pr       ( ∨  pq ) ( ∨  ∧ p  ) r
                                                                ∨
                                                                          ∨
                T       T      T       T           T            T        T               T
                T       T      F       F           T            T        T               T
                T       F      T       F           T            T        T               T
                T       F      F       F           T            T        T               T
                F       T      T       T           T            T        T               T
                F       T      F       F           F            T        F               F
                F       F      T       F           F            F        T               F
                F       F      F       F           F            F        F               F

                                                            12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[The truth table Show that  p ∨  (qr∧  )  and ( pq∨  ) ( pr∧  ∨  ) are logically equivalent.
             In these equivalences, T denotes the compound proposition that is always true and F denotes the
             compound proposition that is always false.

                                                    Logical Equivalences

                                           Equivalence                       Name

                                             p ∧   =T  p
                                                                    Identity laws
                                             p ∨   = F  p

                                             p ∨   ≡T  T
                                                                    Domination laws
                                             p ∧   ≡ F  F

                                             p ∨  p ≡  p
                                                                    Idempotent laws
                                             p ∧  p ≡  p

                                            ¬¬    )   p             Double negation law
                                              ( p ≡
                                            pq∨ ≡∨     p
                                                   q
                                                                    Commutative laws
                                            pq∧ ≡∧     p
                                                   q
                                      ( pq∨  ) r∨  ≡  p ∨  (qr∨  )
                                                                    Associative laws
                                      ( pq∧  ) r∧  ≡  p ∧  (qr∧  )

                                    p ∨  (qr∧  ) ( pq≡  ∨  ) ( pr∧  ∨  )
                                                                    Distributive  laws
                                    p ∧  (qr∨  ) ( pq≡  ∧  ) ( pr∨  ∧  )

                                        ¬ ( pq∧  ) ≡ ¬ ∨¬
                                                     p
                                                          q
                                                                    De Morgan’s laws
                                                     p
                                                          q
                                        ¬ ( pq∨  ) ≡ ¬ ∧¬
                                           p ∨  ( pq∧  ) ≡  p
                                                                    Absorption laws
                                           p ∧  ( pq∨  ) ≡  p

                                                  p
                                            p ∨¬ ≡ T
                                                                    Negation laws
                                                  p
                                            p ∧¬ ≡ F








                                                              13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Logical Equivalences Involving                    Logical Equivalences Involving
                  Conditional Statements                            Biconditional Statements

                         q
                     p → ≡¬    pq∨                                    p ↔≡     ( p → q ∧        ) r
                                                                                      ) (q →
                                                                           q
                               q
                         q
                     p → ≡ ¬ ∨¬                                       p ↔ ≡¬ ↔ ¬
                                                                           q
                                                                                 p
                                                                                       q
                                    p
                              p
                                  q
                     pq∨ ≡¬ →                                         p ↔  q ≡ ( pq∧  ) ( p∨ ¬ ∧¬  ) q
                                                                                         q
                     pq∧ ≡ ¬  ( p → ¬  ) q                            ¬ ( p ↔  ) q ≡  p ↔¬
                    ¬ ( p →   ) q ≡  p ∧¬
                                      q
                    ( p →  q ) ( p∧  →  ) r ≡  p →  (q r∧  )
                    ( p →  r ) (q∧  →  r ) ( p q≡  ∨  ) →  r
                    ( p →  q ) ( p∨  →  ) r ≡  p →  (q r∨  )
                    ( p →  r ) (q∨  →  r ) ( p q≡  ∧  ) →  r


            ¬ (  p ∨  p ∨  2  ∨  p n ) (  p ∧¬ p ∧  2  ∧¬ p n )
                                  ≡ ¬
                                       1
                1
                                  ≡ ¬
            ¬ (  p ∧  p ∧  2  ∧  p n ) (  p ∨¬ p ∨  2  ∨¬ p n )
                                       1
                1


          Using De Morgan’s Laws

          The two logical equivalences known as De Morgan’s laws are particularly important. The equivalence
                            q
                       p
                                                              q
                                                         p
          ¬ ( pq∨  ) ≡ ¬ ∧¬  and similarly  ( pq¬  ∧  ) ≡ ¬ ∨¬


          Example

          Use De Morgan’s laws to express the negations of “Miguel has a cellphone and he has a laptop computer”
          and “Heather will go to the concert or Steve will go to the concert.”
          Solution

             Let:  p be “Miguel has a cellphone”
                   q be “Miguel has a laptop computer”
             can be expressed as  pq∧

                                                                    q
             By De Morgan’s laws  ( pq¬  ∧  )  is equivalent to  p¬ ∨¬ .We can express the negation of our
             original statement as “Miguel does not have a cellphone or he does not have a laptop computer”

             Let:  r be “Heather will go to the concert”
                   s be “Steve will go to the concert”
             can be expressed as  r ∨
                                     s
                                               r
             By De Morgan’s laws  (r¬   ∨  ) s ≡ ¬ ∧¬ . We can express the negation of our original statement as
                                                     s
             “Heather will not go to the concert and Steve will not go to the concert.”

                                                            14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Example

                                            q
             Show that  ( p¬  →  ) q  and  p ∧¬  are logically equivalent.

             Solution

                ¬ ( p →   ) q ≡¬ ( pq¬ ∨  )
                          ≡ ¬ ( p¬  ) ∧¬
                                       q
                          ≡  p ∧¬
                                  q

                                     p     q      p  → q    ¬  ( p  →  ) q     ¬q    p ∧¬q
                                     T     T        T           F         F          F
                                     T     F        F           T         T          T

                                     F     T        T           F         F          F
                                     F     F        T           F         T          F


             Example

                                                   q
             Show that  ( p¬  ∨¬     ))  and  p¬ ∧¬  are logically equivalent by developing a series of logical
                              ( pq∧
             equivalences.

             Solution

                                     p
                ¬ ( p ∨ ( pq¬∧  )) ≡ ¬∧ ¬ ( pq¬∧  )            By De Morgan’s law
                                 ≡ ¬ p ∧ ( p ∨¬  ) q           Double negation law

                                 ≡  ( p¬∧  p ) ( p∨ ¬∧ ¬  ) q    Distribution law

                                                                 p
                                 ≡ F  ∨ ¬       ) q            ¬∧    p ≡ F
                                       ( p ∧¬
                                 ≡ ( p¬ ∧¬  ) q ∨ F            Commutative law for disjunction
                                         q
                                 ≡ ¬ p ∧¬                      Identity law


             Example

             Show that ( pq∧  ) →  ( pq∨  )  is a tautology.


             Solution
                ( pq∧  ) →  ( pq∨  ) ≡  ¬  ( pq∧  ) ( pq∨  ∨  )


                                  ≡  ( p¬ ∨¬ q ) ( pq∨  ∨  )    By De Morgan’s law
                                    ( p
                                            ) ( qq
                                  ≡ ¬∨     p ∨ ¬∨      )       By Associative and commutative laws
                                  ≡   ∨ T T
                                  ≡ T

                                                              15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Exercises  Section 1.2 – Propositional Equivalences



          1.   Use the truth table to verify these equivalences

                 a)  p ∧   ≡T  p
                 b)  p ∨   ≡ F  p

                 c)  p ∧   ≡ F  F
                 d)  p ∨   ≡T  T
                 e)  p ∨  p ≡  p

                 f)  p ∧  p ≡  p

          2.   Show that  ( p¬¬  )  and p are logically equivalent

          3.   Use the truth table to verify the commutative laws
                 a)  pq ≡∨      p
                       ∨
                            q
                            q
                       ∧
                 b)  pq ≡∧      p

          4.   Use the truth table to verify the associative laws
                 a)  ( pq∨  ) r∨  ≡  p ∨  (qr∨  )

                 b)  ( pq∧  ) r∧  ≡  p ∧  (qr∧  )

          5.   Show that each of these conditional statements is a tautology by using truth result tables.
                 a)  ( pq∧  ) →  p

                 b)  p →  ( pq∨  )

                       p
                 c)  ¬→    ( p →   ) q
                 d)  ( pq∧  ) →  ( p →  ) q

                 e)  ¬  ( p →  ) q →  p

                                       q
                        p
                                  
                 f)      ¬∧ ( pq∨  ) →
                                  
                 g)  ( p →     q ) (q∧  →  ) r     →  ( p →  ) r
                 h)      p ∧  ( p →  ) q     →  q


                               q
          6.   Show that  p ↔  and ( pq∧    ) ( p∨ ¬ ∧¬  ) q  are logically equivalent
                                                q
          7.   Show that  ( p¬  ↔  ) q  and  p ↔¬  are logically equivalent
          8.   Show that  p →  and  q¬ → ¬  are logically equivalent
                                             p
                               q
                                              q
                                q
          9.   Show that  p¬↔  and  p ↔¬  are logically equivalent
          10.  Show that ( p →  q ) ( p∨  →  ) r  and  p →  (qr∨  )  are logically equivalent



                                                            16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[11.  Show that ( p →  r ) (q∨  →  ) r  and ( pq∧  ) →  r  are logically equivalent

             12.  Show that ( p →  q ) (q∧  →  ) r →  ( p →  ) r  is a tautology

             13.  Show that ( pq∨  ) ( pr∨¬ ∨  ) → (qr∨  ) is a tautology

             14.  Show that | (NAND) is functionally complete










































































                                                              17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Section 1.3 – Predicates and Quantifiers





          Introduction
          To express the meaning of a wide range of statements in mathematics and computer science in ways that
          permit us to reason and explore relationships between object, are called predicate logic.


          Predicates


          Statements involving variables, such as
                 "x >  3," "x =  y +  3," and  "computer x is under attack by an intruder."
          are often found in mathematical assertions, in computer programs, and in system specifications



          Example

              P
                                            3
          Let  ( ) x  denote the statement  x > . What are the truth values of  ( ) 4P   and  ( ) 2P  ?
          Solution
             We obtain the statement  ( ) 4  by setting  x =  in the statement  x > . Hence,  ( ) 4P  , which is the
                                      P
                                                          4
                                                                               3
             statement  4 >  is true.
                           3
                                                        3
             However,  ( ) 2P  , which is the statement  2 >  is false.


          Example

                    )
                                                  3
                                               y
          Let  ( ,Q xy  denote the statement  x = + . What are the truth values of  propositions  (1, 2Q  )  and
          Q (3, 0 ) ?
          Solution

                                                                           )
                                                  2
                                        1
             To obtain  (1, 2Q  ) ,  set  x = and  y =  in the statement  ( ,Q xy . Hence,  (1, 2Q  )  is the statement

             1 23= + which is false.

             The statement  (3, 0Q  )  is the proposition 3 03= +    which is true.














                                                            18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Example

                       )
             Let  ( ,A cn  denote the statement “Computer c is connected to netwrok n,” where c is a variable
             representing a computer and n is a variable representing a network. Suppose that the computer MATH1 is
             connected to network CAMPUS2, but not to network CAMPUS1. What are the values of
                                         A
             A (MATH  1,CAMPUS     ) 1  and  (MATH 1,CAMPUS    ) 2 ?
             Solution

                Because MATH1 is not connected to the CAMPUS1 network, we see that  (MATH         1,CAMPUS    ) 1 is
                                                                                        A

                false.
                However, because MATH1 is connected to the CAMPUS2 network, we see that
                 A (MATH  1,CAMPUS     ) 2  is true.



                                                         x
                                             0
                 Consider the statement if  x >  then  : x = + 1
                When this statement is encountered in a program, the value of the variable x at the point in the
                execution of the program is inserted into  ( ) x , which is  x > . If  ( ) x  is true for this value of x, the
                                                                                 P
                                                        P
                                                                           0
                                                                                               P
                assignment statement  :x = + 1 is executed. So the value of x is increased by 1. If  ( ) x  is false for
                                          x
                this value of x, the assignment statement is not executed, so the value of x is not changed.


             Preconditions and Postconditions

             Predicates are also used to establish the correctness of computer programs, that is, to show that computer
             programs always produce desired output given valid input.
             The statements that describe valid input are known as preconditions and the conditions that the output
             should satisfy when the program has run are known as postconditions.


             Quantifiers

             To create a proposition from a propositional function is called quantification.  Quantification expresses
             the extent to which a predicate is true over a range of elements. The words all, some, many, none and few
             are used in quantifications.
             The area of logic that deals with predicates and quantifiers is called the predicate calculus.

             There are two quantifiers
                      Existential Quantifier    “∃” reads “there exists”

                      Universal Quantifier      “∀” reads “for all”
             Each is placed in front of a propositional function and binds it to obtain a proposition with semantic
             value.




                                                              19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Definition

          The universal quantification of  ( ) x  is the statement
                                         P
                 “ ( ) x  for all values of x in the domain.”
                  P
                                                                      P
          The notation  x P x∀  ( )  denotes the universal quantification of  ( ) x . Here ∀ is called the universal
                                                     ( )
                                                                           ( )
          quantifier. We read  x P x∀  ( )  as “for all  x P x ”  or “for every  x P x ”. An element for which  ( ) x  is
                                                                                                       P
          false is called a counterexample of   x P x∀  ( ) .

             Statement      When True?                              When False?

                                                                                            P
             ∀ x P ( ) x    P ( ) x  is true for every x.           There is an x for which  ( ) x  is false.

                                                    P
             ∀ x P ( ) x    There is an x for which  ( ) x  is true.   P ( ) x  is false for every x.


          Example

          Let  ( ) x  be the statement "x +>  "                                              x P ( ) x , where the
                                        1 x .  What is the truth value of the quantification ∀
              P
          domain consists of all real numbers?
          Solution

                      P
             Because  ( ) x  is true for all real numbers x, the quantification  x P x∀  ( )  is true.


          Example

                                                                                              ( )
              Qx
          Let  ( )  be the statement "x < 2".  What is the truth value of the quantification  x Q x , where the
                                                                                        ∀
          domain consists of all real numbers?
          Solution

                ( )  is not true for every real number x, because,  ( ) 3Q
              Qx                                                     is false.
                                                                                     ( )
                                                                                ∀
             That is,  x =  is a counterexample for the statement  x Q x∀  ( ) . Thus  x Q x is false.
                         3



          Example

                                                                            2
                                                    P
          What is the truth value of  x P x∀  ( ) , where  ( ) x is the statement "x < 10" and the domain consists of

          the positive integers not exceeding 4?
          Solution

                                                                      2
             The domain consists of the integers 1, 2, 3, and 4. Since "4 < 10" is false, it follows that  x P x∀  ( ) is

             false.

                                                            20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Example
                                                 )
                                      ∀
             What is the truth value of  x x ≥  (  2  x , if the domain consists of real number? What is the truth value of
             this statement of the domain consists of all integers?

             Solution
                    ( ) 2   1                    (  2   )
                     1
                                             ∀
                    2   ≥  2  , it follows that  x x ≥  x  is false.
                               2
                                            2
                                                x
                       Note:  x ≥  x iff   x −=      ( x x −  ) 1 ≥ 0 ⇒     x ≤  0  x ≥  1
                                                             (  2   )
                  If the domain consists of the integers,   x x∀  ≥  x  is true, because there are no integers x with
                        x
                    0 <<   1


             Definition


                                             P
             The existential quantification of  ( ) x  is the proposition
                    “There exists an element x in the domain such that  ( ) x ”
                                                                     P
             We use the notation  x P x∃  ( )  for the existential quantification of  ( ) x . Here ∃ is called the existential
                                                                            P
             quantifier.


             Example

                 P
             Let  ( ) x  denote the statement "x >  3".  What is the truth value of the quantification x P x∃  ( ) , where the

             domain consists of all real numbers?
             Solution
                                                                         4
                Because "x >  3" is sometimes true, for instance, when x = − the existence quantification of  ( ) x ,
                                                                                                           P


                which is  x P x∃  ( ) , is true.


             Example

                 Qx
             Let  ( )  denote the statement "x = + 1".  What is the truth value of the quantification x Q x∃  ( ) , where
                                                x

             the domain consists of all real numbers?
             Solution

                Qx                                                                  Qx                   ( ) , is
                  ( )  is false for every real number x, the existential quantification of  ( ) , which is  x Q x∃
                false.







                                                              21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Example

                                                                            2
                                                    P
          What is the truth value of  x P x∃  ( ) , where  ( ) x is the statement "x > 10" and the universe discourse of

          the positive integers not exceeding 4?
          Solution

                                                                      2
             The domain consists of the integers 1, 2, 3, and 4. Since "4 > 10" is true, it follows that  x P x∃  ( ) is

             true.


          Quantifiers with Restricted Domains

                                                                                     )
                                                                )
                                               )
                                          2
                                                           3
                                                                                2
          What do the statement  x∀<  0 ( x >  0 ,  y∀≠  0 ( y ≠  0 , and  z∀>  0 ( z =  2  mean, where the domain
          in each case consists of the real numbers?
                                       (  2   )                                                2
                                                                                                   0
               The statement  x∀<  0   x >  0  states that for every real numbers x with  x < ,  x < . That is, it
                                                                                           0
                 states “the square of a negative real number is positive.” This statement is the same as
                     (
                                    )
                               2
                         0
                 ∀ x x <→     x >  0 .
                                       (  3   )                                                3
                                                                                                   0
               The statement  y∀≠   0  y ≠  0  states that for every real numbers y with  y ≠ ,  y ≠ . That is, it
                                                                                           0
                 states “the cube of every nonzero real number is nonzero.” This statement is the equivalent to
                     (
                                     )
                                3
                 ∀ y y ≠  0 →  y ≠  0 .
                                       (  2   )                                                        2
                                                                                                          2
               The statement  z∀>  0   z =  2  states that for every real numbers z with  z > such that  z = .
                                                                                          0
                 That is, it states “There is a positive square root of 2.” This statement is the equivalent to
                                     )
                 ∃   z  z > (  0   z∧  2  =  2 .




          Binding Variables

          When a quantifier is used on the variable x, we say that this occurrence of the variable is bound. An
          occurrence of a variable that is not bound by a quantifier or set equal to a particular value is said to be
          free.













                                                            22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Logical Equivalences Involving Quantifiers

             Definition

             Statements involving predicates and quantifiers are logically equivalent if and only if they have the same
             truth value no matter which predicates are substituted into these statements and which domain of
             discourse is used for the variables in these propositional functions. We use the notation  S ≡ T  involving
             predicates and quantifiers are logically equivalent.




             Negating Quantified Expressions

             We will often want to consider the negation of a quantified expression. For instance, consider the negation
             of the statement
                “Every student in your class has taken a course in calculus”


             This statement is a universal quantification, namely,  x P x∀  ( )
             where  ( ) x  is the statement “x has taken a course in calculus” and the domain consists of the students in
                   P
             your class.
             The negation of this statement is “ It is not the case that every student in your class who has not taken a
             course in calculus”. This is simply the existential quantification of the negation of the original proposition
             function, namely,  x P x∃ ¬  ( ).

             This example illustrates the following logical equivalence:

                                                    ¬∀  x P ( ) x ≡ ∃ x  P¬  ( ) x

                                  x  Q
                    ¬∃ x Q ( ) x ≡ ∀ ¬  ( ) x


                      De Morgan’s Laws for Quantifiers

               Negation      Equivalent Statement     When Is Negation True?            When False?

                                                                                      There is an x for which
               ¬∃ x P ( ) x        ∀¬      ( ) x     For every x,  ( ) x  is false
                                     x P
                                                                  P
                                                                                      P ( ) x  is true
                                                     There is an x for which  ( ) x
                                                                             P
               ¬∀  x P ( ) x       ∃ x P¬  ( ) x                                      For every x,  ( ) x  is true
                                                                                                   P
                                                     is false












                                                              23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Example

          What are the negations of the statements “There is an honest politician” and “All Americans eat
          cheeseburgers”?

          Solution

             Let  ( )  denote “x is honest.”
                 Hx
             Then the statement “there is an honest politician” is represented by  x H x∃  ( )
                                                                                ( )
             The negation statement is ¬∃ x H  ( ) x , which is equivalent to  x H x .
                                                                         ∀¬
             This negation can be expressed as “All politicians are not honest”

             Let  ( ) denote “x eats cheeseburgers.”
                 Gx
             Then the statement “All Americans eat cheeseburgers” is represented by  x G x∀  ( )

             The negation statement is ¬∀ x G ( ) x , which is equivalent to  x G x∃ ¬  ( ) .
             This negation can be expressed as “There is an American who does not eat cheeseburgers.”


          Example
                                                                              )
          What are the negations of the statements  x x∀  (  2  >  x  and  x x∃ )  (  2  =  2

          Solution

                                 (  2    )                      (  2   )           (  2   )
             The negation of  x x∀   >  x  is the statement ¬∀ x x >  x   ≡ ∃  x ¬  x >  x
                                         (  2   )
             Which can be written as  x x∃   ≤  x

                                 (  2   )                      (  2   )           (  2    )
             The negation of  x x∃   =  2  is the statement ¬∃ x x =  2  ≡ ∀   x ¬  x =  2

                                         (  2    )
             Which can be written as  x x∀   ≠  2




          Example

          Consider these statements, of which the first three are premises and the fourth is a valid conclusion
             “All hummingbirds are richly colored”
             “No large birds live on honey”
             “Birds that do not live on honey are dull in color”
             “Hummingbirds are small”
                                     Sx
          Let  ( ) x ,  ( ) ,  ( ) x and  ( )  be the statements “x is a hummingbird, “ “x is large,” “x lives on
                     Qx
                            R
              P
          honey,” and “ x is richly colored,” respectively. Assuming that the domain consists of all birds, express
          the statements in the argument using quantifiers and  ( ) x ,  ( ) ,  ( ) x and  ( ) .
                                                                           R
                                                                    Qx
                                                                                    Sx
                                                             P
          Solution
                                                            24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[We can express the statements in the argument as
                                  ( ))
                    ∀  ( xP ( ) x →  S x
                                   ( ))
                    ¬∃  ( xQ ( ) x ∧  R x
                                     ( ))
                    ∀  ( x ¬ R ( ) x → ¬ S x
                                    ( ))
                    ∀  ( xP ( ) x → ¬ Q x


                “small” is the same as “not large”
                “dull in color” is the same as “not richly colored”
































































                                                              25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Exercises  Section 1.3 – Predicates and Quantifiers




          1.   Let  ( ) x  denote the statement "x ≤  4". What are these truth values?
                   P
                 a)  ( ) 0P     b)  ( ) 4P     c)  ( ) 6P


          2.   Let  ( ) x  be the statement "the word   contains the letter x  a ". What are these truth values?
                   P
                                                  )
                                                                      )
                                                                                         )
                             )
                 a)  (orange          b)  (lemon            c)  (true         d)  ( false
                                                                                 P
                                                               P
                    P
                                         P

          3.   State the value of x after the statement if  ( ) x  then  :1x =  is executed, where  ( ) x  is the statement
                                                       P
                                                                                           P
               "x > 1", if the value of x when the statement is reached is
                       0
                                                    2
                 a)  x =       b)  x =        c)  x =
                                      1

          4.   Let  ( ) x  be the statement "  spends more than five hours every weekday in class,x  " where the
                   P
               domain for x consists of all students. Express each of these quantifications in English.
                 a)  x P x∃  ( )      b)  x P x∀  ( )       c)  x P x∃ ¬  ( )   d)  x P x∀¬  ( )

          5.   Let  ( )  be the statement "  has visited North Dakota,x  " where the domain consists of the
                   Nx
               students in your class. Express each of these quantifications in English.
                                               ( )
                 a)  x N x∃  ( )      b)  x N x             c)  ¬∃ x N  ( ) x    d)  x N x∃ ¬  ( )
                                         ∀
                 e)  ¬∀ x N ( ) x     f)  x N x∀¬  ( )


          6.   Let  ( )  be the statement "  has a cat,x  " let  ( )  be the statement "  has a dog,x  ", and let  ( ) x
                                                                                                         F
                                                            Dx
                   Cx
               be the statement "  has a ferret.x  " Express each of these statements in terms of  ( ) ,  ( ) ,  ( ) x
                                                                                            Cx
                                                                                                   Dx
                                                                                                          F
               , quantifiers, and logical connectives. Let the domain consist of all students in your class.
                 a)  A student in your class has a cat, a dog, and a ferret.
                 b)  All students in your class have a cat, a dog, or a ferret.
                 c)  Some student in your class has a cat and a ferret, but not a dog.
                 d)  No student in your class has a cat, a dog, and a ferret.
                 e)  For each of the three animals, cats, dogs, and ferrets, there is a student in your class who has
                    this animal as a pet.

          7.   Let  ( )  be the statement "x +>
                   Qx
                                              1 2"x . If the domain consists of all integers, what are these truth
               values?
                 a)  ( ) 0Q           b)  ( ) 1             c)  ( ) 1Q        d)  x Q x∃  ( )
                                         Q −
                 e)  x Q x∀  ( )      f)  x Q x∃ ¬  ( )     g)  x Q x∀¬  ( )


          8.   Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain consists of all integers
                           1
                 a)  nn∀  ( +>  ) n    b)  n∃  (2n =  3n )    c)  nn∃  ( =  −  ) n    d)  nn∀  (3 ≤  4n )

                                                            26]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[9.   Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain consists of all real numbers
                                  )
                    a)  xx∃  (  3  =  −  1    b)  xx∃  (  4  <  x 2 )    c)  x∀  ( ( ) x−  2  =  x 2 )   d)  x∀  (2x >  ) x


             10.  Suppose that the domain of the propositional function  ( ) x  consists of the integers 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5.
                                                                       P
                  Express these statements without using quantifiers, instead using only negations, disjunctions, and
                  conjunctions.
                                                 ( )
                    a)  x P x∃  ( )      b)  x P x             c)  ¬∃ x P ( ) x    d) ¬∀ x P ( ) x
                                            ∀
                                       ( ))   ∨∃
                    e)  x ∀  ( ( x ≠  ) 3 →  P x    x  P¬  ( ) x

             11.  For each of these statements find a domain for which the statement is true and a domain for which
                  the statement is false.
                    a)  Everyone is studying discrete mathematics.
                    b)  Everyone is older than 21 years.
                    c)  Every two people have the same mother.
                    d)  No Two different people have the same grandmother.

             12.  Translate each of these statements into logical expressions using predicates, quantifiers, and logical
                  connectives.
                    a)  No one is perfect.
                    b)  Not everyone is perfect.
                    c)  All your friends are perfect.
                    d)  At least one of your friends is perfect.
                    e)  Everyone is your friend and is perfect.
                    f)  Not everybody is your friend or someone is not perfect.


             13.  Translate each of these statements into logical expressions using predicates, quantifiers, and logical
                  connectives.
                    a)  Something is not in the correct place.
                    b)  All tools are in the correct place and are in excellent condition.
                    c)  Everything is in the correct place and in excellent condition.
                    d)  Nothing is in the correct place and is in excellent condition.
                    e)  One of your tools is not in the correct place, but it is in excellent condition.


















                                                              27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Section 1.4 – Nested Quantifiers





          Introduction

          Nested quantifiers commonly occur in mathematics and computer science. Nested quantifiers can
          sometimes be difficult to understand.
          We will see how to use nested quantifiers to express mathematical statements such as “The sum of two
          positive integers is always positive.” We will show how nested quantifiers can be used to translate
          sentences such as “Everyone has exactly one best friend” into logical statements.


          Example

                                       ( (
                                             ) ( y <
          Translate the statement  x y x >  0 ∧        ) 0 →  ( xy <  0 ))
                                 ∀∀
          Where the domain for both variables consists of all real numbers.
          Solution

             This statement says that for every real number x and every real number y, if  x >  and  y < , then
                                                                                                     0
                                                                                          0
              xy < 0 . That is, this statement says that for all real numbers x and y, if x is positive and y is negative,
             then xy is negative.
             This can be stated more succinctly as
             “The product of a positive real number and a negative real number is always a negative real number.”



          The Order of Quantifiers

          Example

                     )
          Let  ( ,P x y  be the statement "x y  yx  ". What are the truth values of the quantifications
                                          += +
                       )
                                          )
                             ∀∀
          ∀∀      ( ,x  y  and  y x P ( ,x  y  where the domain for all variables consists of all real numbers?
            x y P
          Solution
             The quantification  x y P x  y∀∀  ( ,  ) denotes the proposition

                        For all real numbers x, for all real numbers y,  x +=  yx+
                                                                        y

                                             )
             The quantification  y x P∀∀  ( ,x  y denotes the proposition

                        For all real numbers y, for all real numbers x,  x +=  yx+
                                                                        y
             Which they have the same meaning.
                                                        )
                                     )
             Therefore;  x y P∀∀  ( ,x  y  and  y x P∀∀  ( ,x  y  have the same meaning, and both are true. This
             illustrates the principle that the order of nested universal quantifiers in a statement without other
             quantifiers can be changed without changing the meaning of the quantified statement.



                                                            28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Example

                                                                                                                )
                        )
             Let  ( ,P x y  be the statement "x y+= 0". What are the truth values of the quantifications  y x P∃ ∀  ( ,x  y
                             )
             and  x y P∀∃  ( ,x  y  where the domain for all variables consists of all real numbers?
             Solution

                The quantification  y x P x  y∃ ∀  ( ,  ) denotes the proposition

                                                                                            )
                           There is a real number y, such that for every real number x,  ( ,P x y
                                                                                                0
                No matter what value of y is chosen, there is only one value of x for which  x y+= . Because there is
                                                                                                    )
                no real number y such that  x y   0 for all real numbers x, the statement  y x P∃ ∀  ( ,x  y  is false.
                                            +=
                    10
                 x +=

                The quantification  x y P x  y∀∃  ( ,  ) denotes the proposition

                           For every real number x, there is a real number y such that  ( ,P x y )
                                                                  )
                      “For all x, there exists a y such that  ( ,P x y ”

                    y
                 x +=   0 ⇒     y = − x
                                                  )
                                     ∀∃
                Hence, the statement  x y P  ( ,x  y  is true.
                                                                  )
                      There exists an x such that for all y  ( ,P x y is true”





                Quantifications of Two variables

                  Statement           When True?                              When False?

                ∀∀      ( ,x  y )    P ( , x y  is true for every pair  , x y    There is a pair  ,x y  for which
                  x y P
                                          )
                                                                                   )
                             )
                  y x P
                ∀∀      ( , x  y                                            P ( ,x y  is false.
                                                                                                          )
                                   For every x there is a y for which      There is an x such that  ( ,P x y is
                             )
                  x y P
                ∀∃      ( ,x  y
                                          )
                                    P ( ,x y  is true.                     false for every y.
                                                                  )
                             )

                  x y P
                ∃∀      ( ,x  y    There is an x for which  ( ,P x y is    For every x there is a y for which
                                                                                   )
                                   true for every y.                        P ( ,x y  is false.
                ∃ x y P∃  ( , x  y )    There is a pair  ,x y  for which    P ( ,x y  is false for every pair  ,x y
                                                                                   )
                                          )
                             )
                  y x P
                ∃∃      ( ,x  y     P ( ,x y  is true.


                                                              29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Example

                       )
          Let  ( ,, z  be the statement "x y+=     " z . What are the truth values of the statements
              P x y
                                                    )
                            )
          ∀∀        ( ,,x  y  z  and  z x y P∃ ∀ ∀  ( ,,x  y  z  where the domain for all variables consists of all real
            x y z P∃
          numbers?
          Solution

                                              )
                            ∀∀ ∃
             The statement  x y z P   ( ,,x  y  z denotes the proposition

                 For all real numbers x and for all real numbers y there is a real number z such that  x +=
                                                                                                    y
                                                                                                       z
             This statement is true.
                                              )
             The statement  z x y P∃ ∀ ∀  ( ,,x  y  z denotes the proposition

                 There is a real number z such that for all real numbers x and for all real numbers y it is true that
              x +=
                     z
                 y
                                                                                              y
             This statement is false, because there is no value of z that satisfies the equation  x +=  z for all values

             of x and y.




          Translating Mathematical Statements into Statements Involving Nested Quantifiers

          Example

          Translate the statement “The sum of two positive integers is always positive” into a logical expression.

          Solution
             Let x and y be the positive integers variables which: “For all positive integers x and y,  x +  is
                                                                                                    y
             positive.”
             We can express as:

                 ∀∀     ( ( x >  0 ) ( y∧  >  ) 0 → ( x + > 0 ))
                                               y
                   xy
             We also can translate this using the positive integers as the domain.
                   x y x
                 ∀∀     ( +  y >  ) 0
                 Where the domain for both variables consists of all positive integers

















                                                            30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Example


                                                                                           Cx
             Translate the statement   ∀  ( x C ( ) x ∨∃  ( y C ( ) y ∧  F ( , xy )))  into English, Where  ( )  is “x has a
                               )
             computer,”  ( ,F x y  is “x and y  are friends,” and the domain for both x and y consists of all students in
             your school.

             Solution

                The statement says
                    For every student x in your school, x has a computer or there is a student y such that y has a
                    computer and x and y are friends.
                In other words
                    Every student in your school has a computer or has a friend who has a computer.


             Example

                                                                                                                 )
                                                                                     )
             Translate the statement   ∃ x y∀ ∀  ( z F ( ,x y ) F∧  ( ,x z ) ( y∧  ≠  z )) → ¬ F ( ,y z  into English, where  ( ,F ab
             means a and b are friends and the domain for both x, y and z consists of all students in your school.

             Solution

                The original statement says:
                    There is a student x such that for all students y and all students z other than y, if x and y are friends
                    and x and z are friends, then y and z are not friends.
                In other words
                    There is a student none of whose friends are also friends with each other.


             Example

             Express the statement “Everyone has exactly one best friend” as a logical expression involving predicates,
             quantifiers with domain consisting of all people, and logical connectives.

             Solution

                For every person x, x has exactly one best friend y. “ x∀ (person x has exactly one best friend)” with
                domain consisting of all people.
                For every person z, if person z is not person y, then z is not the best friend of x.
                           )
                Let  ( ,B xy  be the statement “y is the best friend of x”.
                Therefore; the statement can be expressed as:
                              )
                            ,
                    ∃     ( ( y B x y ∧∀  ( ( z z ≠  ) y → ¬ B ( ,x z )))
                The original statement can be expressed as:
                                 )
                    ∀ x∃    ( ( y B x y ∧∀  ( ( z z ≠  ) y → ¬ B ( ,x z )))
                              ,


                                                              31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Negating Multiple Quantifiers

          The negation rules for single quantifiers:

             •  ¬∀   xP ( ) x = ∃ x P¬  ( ) x

             •  ¬∃  xP ( ) x = ∀ x P¬  ( ) x
             •  Essentially, you change the quantifier(s), and negate what it’s quantifying


          Example

                                                    (
                                              ∀∃
          Express the negation of the statement  x y xy =  ) 1  so that no negation precedes a quantifier
          Solution

             The negation is: ¬∀ x∃  ( y xy =  ) 1
             Which is equivalent:  ≡ ∃ x¬∃  ( y xy =  ) 1

                                  ≡ ∃∀       ( xy =  ) 1
                                       x y¬
                                  ≡ ∃∀     ( y xy ≠  ) 1
                                       x


                                                         ))
                                       x
              ( x y zP¬ ∀ ∃∀  ( , ,x  y  z )) ≡ ∃¬ ( y zP∃∀  ( , ,x  y  z
                                   ≡∃ x y∀ ¬ ( zP∀  ( , ,x  y  z ))

                                                       )
                                      x y z P
                                   ≡∃ ∀ ∃ ¬     ( , ,x y  z


          Consider ¬(∀x∃y P(x,y)) = ∃x∀y ¬P(x,y)

             •  The left side is saying “for all x, there exists a y such that P is true”

             •  To disprove it (negate it), you need to show that “there exists an x such that for all y, P is false”


          Consider ¬(∃x∀y P(x,y)) = ∀x∃y ¬P(x,y)

             •  The left side is saying “there exists an x such that for all y, P is true”
             •  To disprove it (negate it), you need to show that “for all x, there exists a y such that P is false”















                                                            32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Exercises          Section 1.4 – Nested Quantifiers



             1.   Translate these statements into English, where the domain for each variable consists of all real
                  numbers

                    a)  ∀∃   ( y x <  ) y
                         x
                    b)  ∃∀   ( y xy =  ) y
                         x
                         xy
                    c)  ∀∀     ( ( ( x ≥  0 ) ( y∧  < 0 )) → ( x y− > 0 ))

                    d)  ∀∀     ( ( ( y  x ≥  0 ∧  0 )) → ( xy ≥ 0 ))
                         x
                                     ) ( y ≥
                         x y∃
                    e)  ∀∀      ( z xy =  ) z
                                    y
                         x yz∃
                    f)  ∀∀      ( x = +  ) z

                             )
             2.   Let  ( ,Q x y be the statement “x has sent an e-mail message to y,” where the domain for both x and y
                  consists of all students in your class. Express each of these quantifications in English
                                   )
                         x yQ
                    a)  ∃ ∃   ( ,x  y
                                    )
                         x yQ
                    b)  ∃∀     ( ,x  y
                                    )
                         x yQ
                    c)  ∀∃     ( , x  y
                                    )
                         y xQ
                    d)  ∃ ∀    ( ,x  y
                                    )
                         y xQ
                    e)  ∀∃     ( ,x  y
                                    )
                         x yQ
                    f)  ∀∀     ( ,x  y

             3.   Express each of these statements using predicates, quantifiers, logical connectives, and
                  mathematical operators where the domain consists of all integers.
                    a)  The product of two negative integers is positive.
                    b)  The average of two positive integers is positive.
                    c)  The difference of two negative integers is not necessarily negative.
                    d)  The absolute value of the sum of two integers does not exceed the sum of the absolute values
                       of these integers.

             4.   Rewrite these statements so that the negations only appear within the predicates
                                     )
                    a)  ¬∃ y xP∀  ( ,x y
                                     )
                    b)  ¬∀ x yP∃  ( ,x y
                                               ))
                    c)  ¬∃  ( y Q ( ) y ∧ ∀ x R¬  ( ,xy

             5.   Express the negations of each of these statements so that all negation symbols immediately precede
                  predicates.
                                        )
                         x y zT∀
                    a)  ∀∃       ( , ,x y z
                                   )
                                                  )
                                        x yQ
                    b)  ∀∃    ( ,x y ∨ ∀∃    ( ,x y
                         x yP
                                                              33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[)
          6.   Let  ( ,T x y  mean that student x likes cuisine y, where the domain for x consists of all students at
               your school and the domain for y consists of all cuisines. Express each of these statements by a
               simple English sentence.
                              )
                 a)  ¬ T  ( ,A J
                                    )
                                                         )
                 b)  ∃ xT  ( ,x  Korean ∧∀ xTx ( ,x  Mexican
                                    ,
                 c)  ∃  ( y T  (Monique  y ) T Jay  y∨  (  ,  ))
                                               ,
                 d)  ∀ x z∀ ∃  ( ( y x ≠  ) z → ¬  ( (Tx y ) Tz y∧  ( ,  )))
                                          ( , y
                 e)  ∃ x z∃ ∀  ( y Tx  )  Tz  ))
                               ( , y ↔
                                          ( , y
                 f)  ∀ x z∀ ∃  ( y Tx  )  Tz   ))
                                ( , y ↔

                          )
          7.   Let  ( ,L x y  be the statement “ x loves y”, where the domain for both x and y consists of all people
               in the world. Use quantifiers to express each of these statements.
                 a)  Everybody loves Jerry.
                 b)  Everybody loves somebody.
                 c)  There is somebody whom everybody loves.
                 d)  Nobody loves everybody.
                 e)  There is somebody whom Lois does not love.
                 f)  There is somebody whom no one loves.
                 g)  There is exactly one person whom everybody loves.
                 h)  There are exactly two people whom L loves.
                 i)  Everyone loves himself or herself.
                 j)  There is someone who loves no one besides himself or herself.

                                                                                                           )
          8.   Let  ( )  be the predicate “x is a student,”  ( ) x  the predicate “x is a faculty member,”  ( ,A xy  the
                                                         F
                   Sx
               predicate “x has asked y a question,” where the domain consists of all people associated with your
               school. Use quantifiers to express each of these statements.
                 a)  Lois asked Professor Fred a question.
                 b)  Every student has asked Professor Fred a question.
                 c)  Every faculty member has either asked Professor Fred a question or been asked a question by
                    Professor Miller.
                 d)  Some student has not asked any faculty member a question.
                 e)  There is a faculty member who has never been asked a question by a student.
                 f)  Some student has asked every faculty member a question.
                 g)  There is a faculty member who has asked every other faculty member a question.
                 h)  Some student has never been asked a question by a faculty member.

          9.   Express each of these system specifications using predicates, quantifiers, and logical connectives, if
               necessary.
                 a)  Every user has access to exactly one mailbox.
                 b)  There is a process that continues to run during all error conditions only if the kernel is working
                    correctly.
                 c)  All users on the campus network can access all websites whose url has a .edu extension.

                                                            34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[10.  Translate each of these nested quantifications into an English statement that expresses a
                  mathematical fact. The domain in each case consists of all real numbers

                         x
                    a)  ∃∀   ( yx + =  ) y
                                  y
                         xy
                    b)  ∀∀     ( ( ( x ≥  0 ) ( y∧  < 0 )) → ( x y− > 0 ))
                    c)  ∃ x∃   ( ( ( y  x ≤  0 ) ( y∧  ≤  0 )) ( x y∧  − > 0 ))

                         x
                    d)  ∀∀     ( ( ( y  x ≠  0 ) ( y∧  ≠  0 )) ↔ ( xy ≠  0 ))

             11.  Determine the truth value of each of these statements if the domain for all variables consists of all
                  integers
                                      )
                    a)  ∀ n m n∃  (  2  <  m

                               (     2 )
                    b)  ∃∀
                         n m n m<

                    c)  ∀ n m n m∃  ( +  =  ) 0
                         n m nm =
                    d)  ∃∀     (     m )
                              (  2    2    )
                         n m n +
                    e)  ∃∃          m =   5
                                           )
                                      2
                    f)  ∃∃    (  2  m =   6
                         n m n +
                         n m
                    g)  ∃∃    (n m =   4  ∧  n m =  ) 1
                                             −
                                 +
                    h)  ∃∃    (n m+  =  4  ∧  n m−  =  ) 2
                         n m
                                 (     mn+  )
                         n m p p∃
                    i)  ∀∀           =   2



















                                                              35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Section 1.5 − Introduction to Proofs





          Some Terminology

          A theorem is a statement that can be shown to be true. Theorems can also be referred to as facts or results.
          We demonstrate that a theorem is true with a proof. A proof is a valid argument that establishes the truth
          of a theorem. The statements used in a proof can include axioms (or postulates), which are statements we
          assume to be true.

          Less important theorems sometimes are called propositions. A less important theorem that is helpful in
          the proof of other results is called a lemma (plural lemmas or lemmata).

          A corollary is a theorem that can be established directly from a theorem that has been proved.
          A conjecture is a statement that is being proposed to be true statement, usually on the basis of some
          partial evidence, a heuristic argument, or the intuition of an expert.



          Direct Proofs

                                                      q
          A direct proof is a conditional statement  p →  is constructed when the first step is the assumption that p
          is true; subsequence steps are constructed using rules of inference, with the final step showing that q must
          be true.
                                       q
          Consider an implication:  p →
             •  If p is false, then the implication is always true.
             •  Show that if p is true then q is true.



          Definition

          The integer n is even if there exists an integer k such that  n =  2k , and n is odd if there exists an integer k
          such that  n = 2k + 1. Two integers have the same parity when both are even or both are odd; they have
          opposite parity when one is even and the other is odd.



          Example

                                                                        2
          Give a direct proof of the theorem “If n is an odd integer, then  n  is odd”

          Solution

             This state:  n P n∀  ( ) →  Q ( ) n , where
                 P ( ) n  is “n is an odd integer”

                 Qn         2
                   ( )  is “ n  is an odd”



                                                            36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Using direct proof, we assume that n is odd, is a true statement. By the definition of an odd integer, it
                                                                                      2
                follows that  n =  2k + 1, where k is some integer. We need to show that  n  is odd.

                     2
                    n =  (2k +  ) 1  2           Square both sides

                        =  4k +  2  4k +  1
                           (
                        =  22k +  2  2k +  )  1    2k +  2  2k =  K

                        =  2K + 1
                                                                         2
                By the definition of an odd integer, we can conclude that  n  is also an odd integer.



             Example

             Give a direct proof that if m and n are both perfect squares, then nm is also a perfect square.
             (An integer a is a perfect square if there is an integer b such that  ab=  2 .)

             Solution

                Using direct proof of this theorem, we assume that the hypothesis of this conditional statement is true,
                namely, we assume that m and n are both perfect squares.
                By the definition of a perfect square:
                                                                                   2
                    ∃∋         2                 There is an integer s such that  m =  s
                     s   m s=
                     t   n t
                    ∃∋     =  2
                The goal is to show that nm is also a perfect square.
                                                        2
                           22
                                                     st
                    mn =  s t = ( )( ) ( )( ) ( )
                                           st st =
                                 ss tt =
                By the definition of a perfect square, it follows that nm is also a perfect square.































                                                              37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Proof by Contraposition

          In logic, proof by contrapositive is a form of proof that establishes the truth or validity of a proposition by
          demonstrating the truth or validity of the converse of its negated parts.
                                                                                       p
                                                                 q
          To prove by contraposition, consider an implication  p → , prove that  q¬ → ¬ ,
                 •  If the antecedent  q¬  is false, then the contrapositive is always true.
                 •  Show that if  q¬  is true, then  p¬  is true

          To perform an indirect proof, do a direct proof on the contrapositive.


          Example

          Prove that if n is an integer and 3n + 2 is odd, then n is odd.

          Solution
             The first step in a proof by contraposition is to assume that the conclusion of the conditional statement
             “3n + 2 is odd, then n is odd” is false. Assume that n is even, then by the definition of an even integer,
              n =  2k for some integer k.

                      2 3 2
                 3n +=    ( ) 2k +
                        = 6k +
                               2
                        =   ( 2 3k +  ) 1

             This show 3n +  is even, because it is a multiple of 2, therefore not odd. This is the negation of the
                             2
             theorem of the conditional statement implies that the hypothesis is false; the original conditional
             statement is true.
             Our proof by contraposition succeeded; we have proved the theorem “If 3n + 2 is odd, then n is odd.”



          Example

          Prove that if  n =  ab  where a and b are positive integers, then  a ≤  n  or b ≤  n .

          Solution

             By using proof by contraposition, let assume that the conclusion of the conditional statement “if
              n =  ab  where a and b are positive integers, then  a ≤  n  or b ≤  n ” is false.
              ( a ≤  n ∨  ) ( b ≤  n  is false.
                                )

             Using the meaning of disjunction together with De Morgan’s law, that implies that both  a ≤  n  and

              b ≤  n  are false
                  ⇒   a >   n  and b >  n
             Then

              ab >  n n
                 =  n

                                                            38]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[n
                ab ≠ , which contradicts the statement n = ab .
                This is the negation of the theorem of the conditional statement implies that the hypothesis is false; the
                original conditional statement is true.
                Our proof by contraposition succeeded; we have proved the theorem “If  n =  ab  where a and b are

                positive integers, then  a ≤  n  or b ≤  n .”


             Vacuous and Trivial Proofs
             If p is a conjunction of other hypotheses and we know one or more of these hypotheses is false, then p is
             false and so  p →  is vacuously true regardless of the truth value of q.
                              q
                                          q
             If we know q is true then  p →  is true regardless of the truth value of p, this called Trivial Proofs.

             Example

                                                                                  2
                                                                                      n
                                                          P
             Show that the proposition  ( ) 0P   is true, where  ( ) n  is “If  n > , then n > ”  and the domain consists
                                                                         1
             of all integers.
             Solution
                                                               2
                                                                   0
                Using a vacuous proof;  ( ) 0P   is “If  01> , then 0 > ” .
                Indeed, the hypothesis  01>  is false. This tells us that  ( ) 0P   is automatically true.


             Example

                                                                           n
                                                                               n
             Let  ( ) n  be “If a and b are positive integers with  ab≥ , then  a ≥  b ,” where the domain consists of all
                 P
             nonnegative integers. Show that  ( ) 0P   is true.

             Solution
                                                          0
                                                               0
                The proposition  ( ) 0  is “If   ab≥ , then  a ≥  b .”
                                P
                          0
                               0
                Because  a =  b =  1
                The conclusion of the conditional statement is true.

                Hence, this conditional statement, which is  ( ) 0P  , is true.


             Definition

                                                                              0
             The real number r is rational if there exist integers p and q with  q ≠  such that  r =  p  . A real number
                                                                                              q
             that is not rational is called irrational.



                                                              39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Example

          Prove that the sum of two rational numbers is rational. (Note that if we include the implicit quantifiers
          here, the theorem we want to prove is “For every real number r and every real number s, if r and s are
          rational numbers, the r + s is rational.)

          Solution

                                                                                                             p
                                                                                             0
             From the definition of a rational number, that there exist integers p and q with  q ≠  such that  r =  ,
                                                                                                            q
                                          0
             and integers t and u with u ≠  such that  s =  t  .
                                                         u
                 rs+=   p  +  t
                        q   u

                        pu qt+
                      =
                          qu
                                                          0
                          0
                                    0
             Because  q ≠  and u ≠ , it follows that  qu ≠ . Therefore; we have r + s is rational.


          Example

                                        2
          Prove that n is an integer and  n  is odd, then n is odd

          Solution

                                                                         2
                                              2
                                                                                 1
             Suppose that n is an integer and  n  is odd. Then,  k∃ ∈  ∋  n =  2k + .
                            1
              ⇒= ±     2k +  (which is not useful).
                n
             By using proof by contraposition, the statement n is not odd, that means n is even.
             That implies that  k∃ ∈  ∋  n = 2k .
                                                                                                   2
             To prove the theorem, we need to show that this hypothesis implies the conclusion that  n  is not odd,
                          2
             that means  n  is even.
                  2
                           2
                 n =  ( )
                       2k
                         2
                     = 4k
                        ( )
                     = 22k  2


                                  2
             Which implies that n  is even.
                                                      2
             We have proved that n is an integer and  n  is odd, then n is odd by a proof of contraposition.









                                                            40]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Proofs by Contradiction

             The basic ides of a proof of contradiction is to assume that the statement we want to prove is false.
             That is, the supposition that p is false followed necessarily by the conclusion q from not ¬p, where q is
             false, which implies that p is true.

                Given a statement p, assume it is false, assume ¬ p

                    •  Prove that ¬ p cannot occur
                       o  A contradiction exists
                       o  Given a statement of the form p → q
                       o  To assume it’s false, you only have to consider the case where p is true and q is false


             Example

             Show that at least four of any 22 days must fall on the same day of the week.

             Solution

                Let p be the proposition “at least four of any 22 days must fall on the same day of the week”
                Suppose that ¬ p is true  ⇒ “at most three of the 22 days fall on the same day of the week”.

                There are 7 days per week  ⇒ at most 3 of the chosen days could fall on that day.
                That contradicts the premise that we have 22 days under consideration.

                If r is the statement that 22 days are chosen, that we have shown that

                                  ) r
                    ¬ p → (r ∧¬ .
                We know that p is true. We have proved that at least four of any 22 days must fall on the same day of
                the week.


             Example

             Prove that  2  is irrational by giving a proof by contradiction.

             Solution

                Let p be the proposition “ 2  is irrational”.  Suppose that ¬ p is true  ⇒ “ 2  is rational”.

                If  2  is rational,  a and b∃  ∋  2 =  a
                                                    b
                    ( ) ( )     2
                         2
                              a
                       2
                           =
                              b
                    2 =  a 2
                        b 2
                       2
                            2
                      2b = a



                                                              41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[2
             It follows that  a  is even, that implies a must also be even. Therefore, by the definition of an even
             integer then we can let  a = 2c  for some integer c.

                            2
                      2
             Thus,  2b =  4c
                     2
                    b =  2c 2

                                                       2
             By the definition of even, this means that b  is even, that implies b must also be even as well.

             The assumption of ¬ p leads to the equation  2 =  a  ,  where a and b have no common factors, but
                                                              b
             both a and b are even, that is, 2 divides both a and b.

             However, our assumption ¬ p leads to the contradiction that 2 divides both a and b and 2 doesn’t
             divide both a and b, ¬ p must be false.
             That is, the statement p “ 2  is irrational” is true.



          Proofs of Equivalence

                                                                                                q
          To prove a theorem that is a biconditional statement, that is, a statement of the form  p ↔ , we must
          show that  p →  and  q →  p  are both true. The validity of this approach is based on the tautology
                         q

                                              ( p ↔  ) q ↔  ( p →  q ) (q∧  →  ) p



          Example

                                                                          2
          Prove the theorem “If n is an integer, then n is odd if and only if  n  is odd”
          Solution

                                           2
             Let: p is “n is odd” and q is “ n  is odd”.
                                                "
             The theorem has the form: " p iff  q . To prove this theorem, we need to show that  p →  and
                                                                                                   q
              q →  p  are both true.

             Using direct proof, we assume that n is odd, is a true statement. By the definition of an odd integer, it follows
                                                                       2
             that  n =  2k + 1, where k is some integer. We need to show that n  is odd.
                  2
                             2
                 n =  (2k +  ) 1
                    =  4k +  2  4k +  1
                       (
                    =  22k +  2  2k +  )  1   2k +  2  2k =  K

                    =  2K + 1





                                                            42]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[2
                                                                                                          q
                By the definition of an odd integer, we can conclude that n  is also an odd integer. Therefore,  p →  is
                true.

                                              2
                Suppose that n is an integer and n  is odd. Then,
                            2
                                     1
                  k∃ ∈  ∋  n =  2k +
                               1
                 ⇒= ±      2k +  (which is not useful).
                    n
                By using proof by contraposition, the statement n is not odd, that means n is even.
                That implies that  k∃ ∈  ∋  n =  2k .
                                                                                               2
                To prove the theorem, we need to show that this hypothesis implies the conclusion that n  is not odd, that
                        2
                means  n  is even.
                             2
                     2
                          2k
                    n =  ( )
                            2
                        =  4k
                           ( )
                        =  22k 2

                                      2
                    which implies that n  is even.
                                                     2
                We have proved that n is an integer and n  is odd, then n is odd by a proof of contraposition.

                Therefore,  q →  p  is true.

                             q
                Because  p →  and  q →   p  are both true, we have shown that the theorem is true.


             Example


             Show that these statements about the integer n are equivalent:
                 p  :   n is even
                  1
                 p  :   n − 1 is odd
                  2
                       2
                 p  :   n  is even
                  3

             Solution
                We will show that these 3 statements are equivalent by showing that the condition statements
                 p →   p  ,  p →  p  p →  ,   p  are true.
                  1     2    2      3   3      1

                Using a direct proof to show that  p →  p .
                                                  1      2
                Suppose that n is even, then  n =  2k  for some  k ∈ .
                    n −=       1
                       12k −
                         =  ( 2 k −  ) 1 +  1

                This means that  n − 1 is odd because it is of the form  2m + 1, where m is the integer  k − 1.

                Therefore, the statement  p →  p   is true.
                                          1     2
                                                              43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Also using a direct proof to show that  p →  p .
                                                    2     3
             Suppose that  n − 1 is even, then  n −=   1 for some  k ∈ .
                                                12k +
                 n =  2k +  2
                   2
                 n =  (2k +  ) 2  2

                     =  4k +  2  8k +  4
                        (
                     =  22k +  2  4k +  2 )

               Hence,  n − 1 is even.

             Therefore, the statement  p →  p is true.
                                       2      3

             Using a proof by contraposition to prove p →   p . That is, we have to prove that if n is not even,
                                                      3      1
                    2
             then  n  is not even.
                                                                                            2
             To prove the theorem, we need to show that this hypothesis implies the conclusion that n  is not odd, that
                     2
             means  n  is even.
                           2
                  2
                       2k
                 n =  ( )
                         2
                     = 4k
                        ( )
                     = 22k  2

                                   2
                 which implies that n  is even.
                                                  2
             We have proved that n is an integer and n  is odd, then n is odd by a proof of contraposition.
             Therefore,  p →   p  is true.
                          3     1

             This completes the proof.































                                                            44]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Counterexamples

             To show that a statement of the form  x P x∀  ( )  is false, we need only find a counterexample, that is, an

             example of x for which  ( ) x  is false.
                                    P


             Example

             Show that the statement “Every positive integer is the sum of the squares of two integers” is false.
             Solution

                To show that this statement is false, we look for a counterexample, which is a particular integer that is
                not the sum of the squares of two integers.
                To choose a counterexample, we can select 3 because it cannot be written as the sum of the squares of
                two integers.

                                               2
                                                   2
                                                                 3
                Let use 0 and 1 which implies 0 + 1 =  0 1 1+= ≠ .
                Therefore, we can’t get 3 as the sum of two terms of which is 0 or 1.
                Consequently, we have shown that “Every positive integer is the sum of the squares of two integers”
                is false.



             Mistakes in Proofs

             Each step of a mathematical proof needs to be correct and the conclusion needs to follow logically from
             the steps that precede it. Many mistakes result from the introduction of steps that do not logically follow
             from those that precede it.



             Example

                                                  2
             What is wrong with this “proof?”: If  n  is positive, then n is positive.
                                    2
                                                                                                         2
              Proof: Suppose that  n  is positive. Because the conditional statement “If n is positive, then  n  is
                      positive” is true, we can conclude that n is positive.

             Solution

                                                           2
                Let  ( ) n  be “n is positive” and  ( )  be “ n  is positive.”
                                                Qn
                    P
                                                            ( )) .
                The statement can be written:  ( n P n∀  ( ) →  Qn
                                                             2
                A counterexample is supplied by  n = − ⇒   n =  1 is positive, but n is negative.
                                                      1






                                                              45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Exercises          Section 1.5 − Introduction to Proofs




          1.   Show that the square of an even number is an even number
                                               3
                                                   5
          2.   Prove that if n is an integer and  n +  is odd, then n is even
                            2
                                 2
          3.   Show that  m =  n  if and only if  m =  n or  m = −
                                                                  n
          4.   Use a direct proof to show that the sum of two odd integers is even.
          5.   Use a direct proof to show that the sum of two even integers is even.
          6.   Use a proof by contradiction to prove that the sum of an irrational number and a rational number is
               irrational.

          7.   Prove or disprove that the product of two irrational numbers is irrational.

          8.   Prove that if x is irrational, then   1   is irrational.
                                               x

          9.   Prove that if x is rational and  x ≠ , then   1   is rational.
                                                0
                                                        x
                                                  P
          10.  Prove the proposition  ( ) 0P  , where  ( ) n  is the proposition “If n is a positive integer greater than 1,
                      2
               then  n >  . n ” What kind of proof did you use?


          11.  Let  ( ) n  be the proposition “If a and b are positive real numbers, then (ab+  ) ≥  n  a +  n  b n .” Prove
                   P
               that  ( ) 1P   is true. What kind of proof did you use?


          12.  Show that these statements about the integer x are equivalent:
                                                          2
                 i )3   x +  2  is even ii ) x +  5  is odd  iii ) x   is even

          13.  Show that these statements about the real number x are equivalent:
                 i ) x  is irrational  ii )3   x + 2  is irrational  iii )   x    is irrational
                                                                 2

          14.  Prove that at least one of the real numbers  a a  ,  , a  is greater than or equal to the average of
                                                           ,
                                                          1   2       n
               these numbers. What kind of proof did you use?











                                                            46]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Section 1.6 − Proof Methods and Strategy




             Introduction

             The strategy behind constructing proofs includes selecting a proof method and then successfully
             constructing an argument step by step, based on this method.


             Exhaustive Proof and Proof by Cases

                                                         (
             To prove a conditional statement of the form   p ∨  1  p ∨  2  ∨  p n )  →  q


             The tautology     (  p ∨  p ∨  ∨  p  ) →  q ↔      (  p →  q ∧  ) ( p →  q ∧  )  ∧  (  p →  q ) 
                                1    2        n             1          2               n      
             can be used as a rule of inference.
                                                                                                            q
             Such an argument is called a proof by cases. Sometimes to prove that a conditional statement  p →  is
             true, it is convenient to use a disjunction  p ∨  p ∨  ∨  p  instead of p as the hypothesis of the
                                                      1    2        n
             conditional statement, where p and  p ∨  p ∨   ∨  p  are equivalent.
                                                1     2        n


             Exhaustive Proof

             Also known as proof by cases, perfect induction, or the brute force method, is a method of mathematical
             proof in which the statement to be proved is split into a finite number of cases and each case is checked to
             see if the proposition in question holds.



             Theorem
             A proposition that has been proved to be true

                •  Two special kinds of theorems: Lemma and Corollary.
                •  Lemma: A theorem that is usually not too interesting in its own right but is useful in proving
                    another theorem.
                •  Corollary: A theorem that follows quickly from another theorem.



             Example

                                  n
                                                                    4
             Prove that (n +  ) 1  3  ≥  3  if n is a positive integer with  n ≤
             Solution
                Using a proof by exhaustion:
                                             1
                                                 3
                For n = 1: (n +  ) 1  3  =  2 =  3  8 ≥ 3 =
                                                              47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[For n = 2: (n +  ) 1  3  =  3 =  3  2 ≥  2  9
                                       7 3 =
                                   3
                                            3
             For n = 3: (n +  ) 1  3  =  4 =  64 ≥ 3 =  27
                                  3
                                             4
             For n = 4: (n +  ) 1  3  = 5 = 125 ≥ 3 = 81
                                                                            n
             We have used the method of exhaustion to prove that (n +  ) 1  3  ≥  3  if n is a positive integer with
              n ≤ 4


          Example

                                           2
          Prove that if n is an integer, then  n ≥
                                               n
          Solution

                                                  2
                                                                        2
                                                     0
                                                                           n
             Case 1: When n = 0, that implies to 0 ≥ . It follows that  n ≥  is true.
                                                           2
                                                                                 2
                                                               n
                                                                                     n
             Case 2: When  n ≥ 1, ⇒  n n⋅ ≥ 1 n⋅ , we obtain n ≥  It follows that  n ≥  is true.
                                         2
                                                               2
                                                                  n
                                            0
             Case 3: When  n ≤−  1, but n ≥ . It follows that  n ≥  is true.
                                     2
             Because the inequality  n ≥  holds in all three cases, we can conclude that if n is an integer, then
                                         n
               2
                   n
              n ≥ .


          Example
          Show that if x and y are integers and both xy and x + y are even, then both x and y are even.
          Solution

             Using the proof by contraposition:
             Suppose that x and y are not both even. That is, x is odd or y is odd (or both).

             Assume that x is odd, so that  x =  2k + 1 for some integer k.
             Case 1: y even ⇒  y =  2n

                        y
                                1 2n
                     x + =  2k ++
                          =  ( 2 kn+  ) 1+      is odd
             Case 2: y odd ⇒  y =  2n +  1

                     xy =  (2k +  1 )(2n +  ) 1
                        =  4kn +  2k +  2n +  1

                        =  ( 22kn k n++  ) 1+    is odd

             This completes the proof by contraposition.


                                                            48]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Existence Proofs

             A statement   x P x∃  ( )  is called an existence proof. There are several ways to proof a theorem of this type.

                  Constructive: Find a specific value of c for which P(c) exists

                  Nonconstructive: Show that such a c exists, but don’t actually find it. Assume it does not exist,
                    and show a contradiction



             Example

             Show that a square exists that is the sum of two other squares
             Solution

                                    2
                Proof:   3 +  2  4 =  2  5
               Because we have displayed a positive integer that can be written as the sum of two squares, we are
               done.



             Example

             Show that there is a positive integer that can be written as the sum of cubes of positive integers in two
             different ways.

             Solution

                                                 3
                Proof:   1729 10=  3  +  9 =  3  12 +  3  1
               We proved that there is a positive integer that can be written as the sum of cubes of positive integers in
               two different ways.


             Example

             Show that a cube exists that is the sum of three other cubes

             Solution

                                        3
                Proof:   3 +  3  4 +  3  5 =  3  6
               We proved that a cube exists that is the sum of three other cubes.













                                                              49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Uniqueness Proofs

          A theorem may state that only one such value exists. Theorem statements that involve the word ``unique''
          are known as uniqueness theorems. Typically, the proof of such a statement follows the idea that we
          assume there are two elements that satisfy the conclusion of the statement and then show that these
          elements are identical.

             Existence: We show that an element x with the desired property exists.

             Uniqueness: We show that if  y ≠ , then y does not have the desired property.
                                              x
          Equivalently, we can show that if x and y both have the desired property, then x = y.



          Example

                                                                                                          y
          Show that if x and y are real numbers and  x ≠ , then there is a unique real number r such that  xr +=
                                                                                                             0
                                                      0
          Solution
                                               y
             The solution of  xr +=  is  r = −  because
                                     0
                                 y
                                               x
               
                                y
                            y
              x −  y     +  y = − +
               
                 x  
                        = 0
                                                                y
                                                                   0
             Consequently, a real number r exists for which  xr += . This is the existence part of the proof.
                                                             0
             Suppose that s is a real number such that  xs y+= , then
              xr +=   xs +
                          y
                  y
              xr =  xs   ( x ≠  ) 0
              →  r =  s
                                                   0
             This means that if  s ≠ , then  xs y+≠ . This establishes the uniqueness part of the proof.
                                   r


          Proof Strategies

          Usually, when you are working on a proof, you should use the logical forms of the givens and goals to
          guide you in choosing what proof strategies to use. Generally, if the statement is a conditional statement,
          we should try a direct proof; if this fails, we can try an indirect proof. If neither of these approaches
          works, you might try a proof by contradiction.















                                                            50]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Example


             Given two positive numbers x and y, their arithmetic mean is    x +  y   and their geometric mean is  xy .
                                                                           2
             When we compare the arithmetic and geometric means of pairs of distinct positive real numbers, we find
                                                                                                                6
                                                                                                     4
             that the arithmetic mean is always greater than the geometric mean. For example, when  x =  and  y = ,
                       +
             we have   46  = 5 >  4 6 ⋅=  24 . Can we prove that this inequality is always true?
                       2
             Solution

                To prove   x +  y  >  xy
                            2
                  x +   y  2  (  ) 2
                        >   xy
                   2  

                 x +  2  2xy +  y 2  >  xy
                       4
                 x +  2  2xy +  y >  2  4xy

                 x −  2  2xy +  y >  2  0

                ( x −  ) y  2  >  0


                It is true inequality, since  ( x −  ) y  2  >  0 when  x ≠ , it follows that   x +  y  >  xy .
                                                                 y

                                                                                    2
                Suppose that x and y are distinct positive real numbers. Then ( x −  ) y  2  >  0 because the square of a
                nonzero real number is positive.

                    x −  2  2xy +  y >  2  0

                                2
                    x −  2  2xy +  y +  4xy >  4xy
                    x +  2  2xy +  y >  2  4xy

                    ( x +  ) y  2  >  4xy        divide both sides by 4

                    ( x +  ) y  2  >  xy
                        4                        Square roots both sides
                    x +  y  >  xy
                      2


             We conclude that if x and y are distinct positive real numbers, then their arithmetic mean   x +  y  is greater
                                                                                                     2
             than the geometric mean  xy










                                                              51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Fermat’s Last Theorem

                                        n
          The eqaution      x +  n  y =  n  z
                                                          0
                                                                                             2
          Has no solutions in integers x, y, and z with  xyz ≠  whenever n is an integer with  n > .












































































                                                            52]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Exercises          Section 1.6 − Proof Methods and Strategy



                              2
             1.   Prove that  n +≥    n                                        4
                                  12  when n is a positive integer with 1 n≤≤
             2.   Prove that there are no positive perfect cubes less than 1000 that are the sum of the cubes of two
                  positive integers.

             3.   Prove that if x and y are real numbers, then  max ( ,xy ) min+  ( ,xy =  )  x +  y . (Hint: Use a proof by
                  cases, with the two cases corresponding to  x ≥  and x < y, respectively.)
                                                                y

             4.   Prove the triangle inequality, which states that if x and y are real numbers, then  x +  y ≥  x +  y

                                                                                                         0
                                                                                   0
                  (where  x  represents the absolute value of x, which equals x if  x ≥  and equals −x if  x <

             5.   Prove that either  2 10⋅  500  +  15 or 2 10⋅  500  +  16 is not a perfect square

             6.   Prove that there exists a pair of consecutive integers such that one of these integers is a perfect
                  square and the other is a perfect cube.

                                                                b
             7.   Suppose that a and b are odd integers with  a ≠ . Show there is a unique integer c such that
                   a c =  bc
                    −
                            −











































                                                              53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Section 1.7 − Sets



          Introduction

          A set is an unordered collection of objects, called elements or members of the set. A set is said to contain
          its elements. We write  a∈  to denote that a is an element of the set A. The notation  a∉  denotes that
                                    A
                                                                                                A
          a is not an element of the set A.


          Example

          Colors of a rainbow: {red, orange, yellow, green, blue, purple}

          Example

          States of matter {solid, liquid, gas, plasma}


          Example

                                                                                         }
          The set V of all vowels in the English alphabet can be written as: V = { , , , ,a  e i  o  u


          Example

          The set O of odd positive integers less than 10 can be expressed by O = {1, 3, 5, 7, 9}

          Example

          The set of positive integers less than 100 can be denoted by {1, 2, 3, …, 99}


            Another way to describe a set is to use set builder notation.


          For instance, the set O of odd positive integers less than 10 can be written as

              O = { |x x is an odd positive integer less than  10 }


          Or, specifying the universe as the set of positive integers, as
                  {     +                       }
              O =  x∈    | x is an odd and x <  10











                                                            54]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[The set of Natural numbers:           = {0, 1, 2, 3,        }


             The set of Integers:                  =   { ,  −   2,  −  1, 0, 1, 2,         }

                                                                 }
             The set of positive integers:        +  = {1, 2, 3   , 
                                                     { p                         }
             The set of Rational numbers:          =  q   p∈  ,  q∈    ,  and q ≠  0


             The set of Real numbers:            
                                                   +
             The set of positive Real numbers:   
             The set of Complex numbers:         


             Intervals


             The notations for intervals of real numbers. When a and b are real numbers with a < b, we write
                                x
                [ ,a  b ] {x a=  ≤≤  } b

                     ) {x a ≤<
                [ ,a  b =       x   } b
                ( ,a  b =       x   } b
                     ] {x a <≤
                ( ,a  b ) {x a=  <<  } b
                                x

                  ]
             [ ,a b  is called closed interval from a to b.

                  )
             ( ,a b  is called open interval from a to b.



             Definition

             Two sets are equal iff they have the same elements. Therefore, if A and B are sets, then A and B are equal
                   (
             iff  x x∈  A ↔∈    B ). We write  A B=   if A and B are equal sets
                ∀
                             x


             Example

             The set {1, 3, 5} and {3, 5, 1} are equal, because they have the same elements.


                Order of the elements of a set are listed does not matter.
                       {1, 2, 3, 4, 5} = {5, 4, 3, 2, 1}




                                                              55]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[The Empty Set

          There is a special set that has no elements. This set is called the empty set, or null set, and is denoted by
          ∅. The empty set can also denoted by { }.

          A set with one element is called a singleton set.



          Venn Diagrams

          In Venn diagrams the universal set U, which contains all the objects under consideration, is represented
          by a rectangle.

           Represents sets graphically
                 The box represents the universal set

                 Circles represent the set(s)
             Consider set S, which is the set of all vowels in the alphabet

             The individual elements are usually not written in a Venn diagram


                                                                      U
                                                  b  c  d  f
                                                 g  h j k l m      S
                                                 n p q r s t v   a  e i
                                                   w x y z       o u





          Example

          Draw a Venn diagram that represents V, the set of vowels in the English alphabet.

          Solution

























                                                            56]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Subset

             Set A is a subset of set B (written  A ⊆  B ) if and only if every element of A is also an element of B. Set A

             is a proper subset (written  A ⊂  B ) if  A ⊆  B  and  A B≠

             We see that  A ⊆  B if and only if the quantification:

                ∀ x x    A →∈    B )  is true
                              x
                    ( ∈
             Note that to show that A is not a subset of B we need only find one element   x∈  with  x∉ . Such an x
                                                                                                     B
                                                                                          A
                                                   A
             is counterexample to the claim that  x∈  implies  x∈ .
                                                                 B

             Showing that A is a Subset of B – To show that  A ⊆  B , show that if x belongs to A then x also belongs to
             B.

             Showing that A is Not a Subset of B – To show that  A ⊆ B , find a single  x∈  such that  x∉ .
                                                                                        A
                                                                                                       B

             Example

                                               }
                {1, 2, 8 ⊆ {   1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
                       }


             Proper subsets: Venn diagram  S ⊂ R

















             Example

             The set of people who have taken discrete mathematics at the school is not a subset of all computer
             science majors at the school if there is at least one student who has taken discrete mathematics who is not
             a computer science major.















                                                              57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Theorem

          For every set S

            i.  ∅⊆  S  and

           ii.  S ⊆
                    S

          Proof  (i)
                                                                (
           Let S be a set. To show ∅⊆  S , we must show that  x x∈∅ → ∈       S )  is true.
                                                             ∀
                                                                          x
           Because the empty set contains no elements, it follows that  x∈∅  is always false. It follows that the
                                              S
                                          x
           conditional statement  x∈∅ → ∈  is always true, because its hypothesis is always false and a
                                                                                      x
           conditional statement with a false hypothesis is true. Therefore,  x x∀  ( ∈∅ → ∈ S )  is true.
           This complete the proof of (i) using a vacuous proof.


          Showing Two Sets are Equal –
          To show that two sets A and B are equals, show that  A ⊆  B  and B ⊆  A .



          Example

                                                                                                 } }
                                          ,
                                               ,
          We have the sets    A =  { , ∅  { } { } { ,a   b   a b }} and  B =  { x x is a subset of the set  { ,a b
          Solution
             These two sets are equal, that is, A = B.

             Note: { } a ∈  A but  a∉  A


          The Size of a Set


          Definition

          Let S be a set. If there are exactly n distinct elements in S where n is a nonnegative integer, we say that S
          is a finite set and that n is the cardinality of S. The cardinality of S is denoted by  S .

             •  Let A be the set of odd positive integers less than 10.   |A| = 5

             •  Let S be the set of letters in English alphabet.         |S| = 26

             •  The null set has no elements.                            |� | = 0








                                                            58]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Definition

             A set is said to be infinite if it is not finite.

             Example:  The set of positive integers is infinite.


             Power Sets

             Definition

             Given a set S, the power set of S is the set of all subsets of the set S. The power set of S is denoted by
             P ( ) S

             Note that the empty set and the set itself are members of the set of subsets.


             Example

             What is the power set of the set {0, 1, 2}?
             Solution

                                                             } { } {0,1,2
                            =
                P  { ( 0,1,2 }) { , 0 , 1 , 2 , 0,1 ,∅  { } { } { } { } {0,2 , 1,2 ,  }}


             Example

             What is the power set of the empty set? What is the power set of the set {∅}?

             Solution

                   ∅= ∅
                P ( ) { }
                         =
                           ∅
                  ( ∅ P  { }) { ,  ∅  { }}



























                                                              59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Cartesian Products


          Definition
                            (
                               ,
          The order n-tuple  a  a 2 ,  , a n )  is the ordered collection that has  a  as its first element,  a  as its
                              1
                                                                               1
                                                                                                     2
          second element, …, and  a  as its nth element.
                                   n
          Let A and B be sets. The Cartesian product of A and B, denoted by  AB× , is the set of all ordered pairs
               )
          ( , a b , where  a∈  and bB∈ . Hence
                            A
                 A B×  =  ( { ,a  b a∈ )  A   b B∧  ∈  }


          Example

          Let A represent the set of all students at a university, and let B represent the set of all courses offered at
          the university. What is the Cartesian product  AB×  and how can it be used?

          Solution

                                                                                         )
             The Cartesian product  AB×  consists of all the ordered pairs of the form ( ,a b , where a is a student
             at the university and b is a course offered at the university. One way to use the set  AB×  is to
             represent all possible enrollments of students in courses at the university.


          Example

          What is the Cartesian product A = {1, 2} and B = {a, b, c}?
          Solution

                            ,
                                   ,
                                                          ,
              A B×  =  ( { 1, a ) (1,    b ) (1,    c ) (2,,    a ) (2,,    b ) (2,    c )}


          Example

          Show that the Cartesian product  BA×  is not equal to  AB× , where A = {1, 2} and B = {a, b, c}?
          Solution


                                                          ,
                                   ,
              A B×  =  ( { 1, a ) (1,    b ) (1,    c ) (2,,    a ) (2,,    b ) (2,    c )}
                            ,
              B A×  =  ( { ,1 ,a    ) ( , 2 ,  a    ) ( ,1 b    ) ( 2, b   ) ( ,1 ,,  c    ) ( , 2  c    )}
              ⇒   AB×  ≠  B A×









                                                            60]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Definition

                                                 ,
             The Cartesian product of the sets  A  A  , , A , denoted by  A ×  A ×  ×  A , is the set of ordered n-
                                               1    2      n               1    2        n
                   (
             tuples  a  a 2 , , a n ) , where  a  belongs to  A  for i = 1, 2, …, n. In other words,
                       ,
                                                           i
                     1
                                             i
                                                                                  }
                    A ×  A ×    ×  A =  ( {  a  , a  ,   , a  )   a ∈  A   for i =  1,2,  ,n
                     1    2        n      1   2        n    i    i


             Example

             What is the Cartesian product  A BC , where A = {0, 1}, B = {1, 2}, and C = {0, 1, 2}
                                            ××
             Solution

                 A BC××   =  ( { 0, 1, 0 ,        ) (0, 1, 2 ,       ) (0, 2, 0 ,          ) (0, 2, 2 ,       )
                                                                    ) (0, 2, 1 ,
                                    ) (0, 1, 1 ,
                                    (1, 1, 0 ,     ) (1, 1, 1 ,         ) (1, 1, 2 ,         ) (1, 2, 0 ,         ) (1, 2, 1 ,         ) (1, 2, 2         )}

             Example

                                                   3
                                           2
             Suppose that A = {1, 2}, find  A  and  A
             Solution

                           ) (1, 2 , 2, 1 , 2, 2
                 A 2  =  ( { 1, 1 ,  ) (  ) (     )}
                                                 ) (1, 2, 2 , 2, 1, 1 , 2, 1, 2 , 2, 2, 1 , 2, 2, 2
                             ) (1, 1, 2 ,
                 A 3  =  ( { 1, 1, 1 ,  ) (1, 2, 1 ,        ) (       ) (       ) (        ) (        )}


             Example


             What are the ordered pairs in the less than or equal relation, which contains (a, b) if  ab≤ , on the set
                    }
             {0,1,2,3 ?
             Solution

                The ordered pairs in R are:
                    (0, 0), (0, 1), (0, 2), (0, 3), (1, 1), (1, 2), (1, 3), (2, 2), (2, 3), (3, 3)




















                                                              61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[Using Set Notation with Quantifiers

                                ( ))  denotes
          For example  x∀∈  S ( P x
             Universal quantification of  ( ) x  over all elements in the S
                                         P
                                          ( ))
                                   S
             Shorthand for  ( xx∀  ∈→   P x
          ∃∈   S ( P x
           x
                   ( ))  denotes
             Existential quantification of  ( ) x  over all elements in the S
                                          P
                                        ( ))
             Shorthand for  ( xx∃  ∈ S ∧  P x


          Example
                                        (  2   )            (  2   )
          What do the statements  x∀∈ R  x ≥  0  and  x ∃∈ Z  x = 1  mean?

          Solution
                                          )
                                                                                2
                                     2
                                                                                    0
             The statement  x∀∈ R  ( x ≥  0  states that for every real numbers x,  x ≥ .
             This statement can be expressed as “The square of every real number is nonnegative.” This is a true
             statement.

                                   (  2  )                                     2
                                                                                  1
             The statement  x∃∈ Z   x = 1  states that there exists an integer x,  x = .
             This statement can be expressed as “The is an integer whose square is 1.” This is also a true statement
             because  x = 1 o r   − 1 such an integer.




































                                                            62]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Exercises         Section 1.7 − Sets


             1.   List the members of these sets
                                                            }
                        {
                                                       2
                    a)  x x is a real number such that x = 1
                    b)  {x x is a positive integer less than  12 }

                    c)  {x x is the square of an integer and  x < 100 }
                        {                          2    }
                    d)  x x is an integer such that x =  2


             2.   Determine whether each these pairs of sets are equal.
                                         } {5,3,1
                    a)  {1,3,3,3,5,5,5,5,5 ,      }
                                   { }}
                        { 1 ,

                    b)  { }} { 1, 1
                             ∅
                    c)  ∅  ,  { }

             3.   For each of the following sets, determine whether 2 is an element of that set.
                    a)  {x∈   x is an integer greater than   } 1

                    b)  {x∈   x is the square of an integer }

                    c)  {2, 2  { }}

                        { 2,
                    d)  { } { }}}
                              { 2
                                  { }}}
                        { 2 ,
                    e)  { } {2, 2
                    f)  { { 2
                         { }}}

             4.   Determine whether each of these statements is true or false
                    a)  0∈∅
                    b)  ∅∈  { } 0

                    c)  { } 0 ⊂∅

                    d)  ∅⊂  { } 0

                    e)  { } { } 0∈
                         0
                         0
                    f)  { } { } 0⊂
                    g)  { } { }
                         ∅ ⊆∅
                    h)  x∈ { } x
                    i)  { } { } x⊆
                         x
                    j)  { } { } x
                         x ∈
                         x ∈
                    k)  { } { }}
                             { x
                                                              63]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[l)  ∅⊆  { } x
                 m)  ∅∈  { } x


          5.   Use a Venn Diagram to illustrate the relationships  A ⊂  B  and  B ⊂ C .
          6.   Use a Venn Diagram to illustrate the relationships  A ⊂  B  and  A ⊂ C .

          7.   Suppose that A, B, and C are sets such that  A ⊆  B  and  B ⊆ C . Show that  A ⊆  C

          8.   What is the cardinality of each of these sets?
                 a)  { } a
                 b)  { }}
                     { a
                         { }}
                 c)  { , a a

                         { } { ,  a a
                 d)  { ,a a  ,    { }}}

          9.   How many elements does each of these sets have where a and b are distinct elements?
                 a)  (  { ,,a b   { ,a b }})
                     P

                               { } { }}})
                            a
                 b)  P  { (  ∅ ,,  a ,  { a
                 c)  (    ( ))
                          ∅
                     PP

          10.  What is the Cartesian product  A BC×× , where A is the set of all airlines and B and C are both the
               set of all cities in the United States? Give an example of how this Cartesian product can be used.

          11.  What is the Cartesian product  AB× , where A is the set of all courses offered by the mathematics
               department and B is the set of mathematics professors at this university? Give an example of how
               this Cartesian product can be used.

          12.  Let A be a set. Show that ∅×  A =  A×∅ = ∅















                                                            64]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Section 1.8 − Set Operations




             Union of Two Sets

             Let A and B be sets, the union of the sets A and B, denoted by  AB , is the set that contains those
             elements that are either in A or in B, or in both.

                    A  B =  { | x x∈  A ∨  x∈  B }














             Example

                                                        }
             Let  A = {1,3,5, 7,9, 11          },  B = {3, 6, 9, 12 . Find the set  AB
             Solution

                 A  B = {1, 3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 11, 12              }



             Intersection of Two Sets

             Let A and B be sets, the intersection of the sets A and B, denoted by  AB , is the set containing those
             elements in both A or in B.

                    A  B =  { |x x∈  A ∧  x∈  B }













             Example

             Let  A = {3, 6, 9    },  B = {2, 4, 6, 8      } , find  AB


             Solution

                 AB =  { } 6


                                                              65]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Disjoint Sets

                                                                                                      =
                                                                                                 
          For any sets A and B, if A and B are disjoint sets, then their intersection is the empty set   AB φ













          Example

                                             }
                           }
          Let  A = {1,3,5,7,9 ,  B = {2,4,6,8,10 , find  AB
          Solution

              AB = ∅   . Therefore, A and B are disjoint.


          Complement of a Set


          Let A be any set, with U representing the universal set, then the complement of A.

                          ′
                         A or  A or  A =  c  {x x∉  |  A and x U∈  }






































                                                            66]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Difference of two Sets

             Let A and B be sets, the difference of A and B, denoted by  AB− , is the set containing those elements that
             are A but not in B. The difference of A and B is also called the complement of B with respect to A.
















             Example


             Find {1, 3, 5} − {1, 2, 3}

             Solution

                {1, 3, 5} − {1, 2, 3} = {5}


             Example

             What is the difference of the set of computer science majors at the school and the set of mathematics
             majors at the school?
             Solution

                The difference is the set of all computer science majors at your school are not also mathematics
                majors.


             Example

             Let A be the set of positive integers greater than 10 (with universal set the set of all positive integers).
             Find  A

             Solution

                                                }
                 A  = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10












                                                              67]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Set Identities

                 Identity                           Name
                  AU =   A
                  A ∅=   A                         Identity laws

                  AU =  U                          Domination laws
                  A ∅= ∅
                  A  A =  A
                  A  A =  A                        Idempotent laws

                  A
                 ( ) =  A                           Complementation laws
                  AB =   B   A
                   
                  AB =  B   A                     Commutative laws

                  A  (BC  ) ( A=    B ) C       Associative laws
                  A  (BC  ) ( A=    B   ) ( )
                                          C

                                                )
                                            
                  A  (B C =  ) ( A  B   ) ( AC    Distributive laws
                  A  (B C  ) ( A=    B ) ( AC    )

                  AB =   A   B                    De Morgan’s laws
                  AB =   A   B
                  A  ( AB =  )  A
                                                    Absorption laws
                  A  ( AB =  )  A
                  A  AU=
                      A = ∅                         Complement laws
                  A


          Example


          Prove that  AB =  A   B
          Solution


             1.  We need to show that  AB ⊆   A   B

                 Suppose that  x∈  AB ⇒      x∉  AB     (by the definition of complement)
                 Using the definition of the intersection, we see that the proposition  ( x¬  ( ∈  A ) ( x∧  ∈  B ))  is true.

                 ¬  ( x∈  A )  or ¬  ( x∈  B )   By applying De Morgan’s law of the proposition

                 x ∉  A or x ∉  B             Using the definition of the negation of proposition

                 x∈  A or x B∈                Using the complement of a set


                                                            68]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[A
                    x∈     B                    Using the definition of union
                    AB ⊆    A   B


                                                    
                2.  We need to show that  A   B ⊆  AB
                    Suppose that  x∈  A  B ⇒    x∈  A  or ∈  x  B   (by the definition of union)
                    x∉  A or x∉  B               Using the definition of the complement

                    ¬  ( x∈  ) A  ∨  ¬  ( x∈  B )    True

                    ¬  ( x∈  A ∧  B )            By applying De Morgan’s law of the proposition


                    ¬  ( x∈  AB  )              Using the definition of the intersection

                    x∈  AB                      Using the definition of complement

                    That shows that  A   B ⊆  AB


                Therefore;  AB =  A   B


             Example


             Use set builder notation and logical equivalences to establish the first De Morgan law  AB =  A   B

             Solution

                 AB =  {x x∉  AB  }               By definition of complement


                       =  { x ¬  ( x∈  ( AB  ))}


                       =  { x ¬  ( x∈  A  ∧   x∈  B )}     By definition of complement


                       =  { x ¬  ( x∈  ) A ∨  ¬  ( x∈  B )}    By the first De Morgan law for logical equivalences


                       =  {x x∉  A   x B∨  ∉  }     By definition of does not belong symbol
                                          }
                       =  { x x∈  A  ∨   x∈  B      By definition of complement

                                     }
                               A
                       = { xx∈    B                By definition of union
                       =  A   B









                                                              69]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[Example


          Use a membership table to show that  A  (B C  ) ( A=    B ) ( AC    )
          Solution



                               A Membership Table for the Distributive Property

                                                       )
                A     B     C      BC       A  (BC        AB       AC     ( A   B ) ( AC    )
                                                   
                1     1      1       1            1           1         1               1
                1     1      0       1            1           1         0               1
                1     0      1       1            1           0         1               1

                1     0      0       0            0           0         0               0
                0     1      1       1            0           0         0               0
                0     1      0       1            0           0         0               0

                0     0      1       1            0           0         0               0
                0     0      0       0            0           0         0               0



          Example


          Let A, B, and C be sets. Show that   A  (BC  ) (C=    B )   A
          Solution

                                      )
                                  
              A  (BC =  )  A   ( BC        By the first De Morgan law
                                       )
                          =  A   ( BC        By the second De Morgan law
                                   
                          = ( BC   )  A      By the commutative law for intersection
                               
                          = ( C   B )   A    By the commutative law for union



























                                                            70]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Generalized Unions and Intersections


















                          A  (BC  ) ( A=    B ) C                        A  (BC  ) ( A=    B ) C



             Example

                                                                                                    
             Let A = {0, 2, 4, 6, 8}, B = {0, 1, 2, 3, 4}, and C = {0, 3, 6, 9}. What are  A BC   and  A BC
             Solution
                     BC =
                 A        {0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9             }
                     BC =
                 A        { } 0












































                                                              71]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Definition

          The union of a collection of sets is the set that contains those elements that are members of at least one
          set in the collection.
                                                                     n
                                                                n 
                                                A   A      A =      A
                                                 1    2                  i
                                                                    i= 1


          Definition

          The intersection of a collection of sets is the set that contains those elements that are members of at all the
          sets in the collection.

                                                                     n
                                                                n 
                                                A   A      A =      A
                                                 1    2                  i
                                                                    i= 1


          For i = 1, 2, …, let  A =  { , i  i +  1, i +  2,  }. Then,
                              i
               n       n
                A =  i  { , i  i +  1, i +  2,   } {1, 2, 3,    =       }

              i= 1    i= 1


               n       n
                A =  i  { , i  i +  1, i +  2,   } { , n n=  +  1, n +  2,   } =  A
                                                                    n
              i= 1    i= 1




































                                                            72]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Exercises         Section 1.8 − Set Operations



             1.   Let A be the set of students who live within one mile of school and let B be the set of students who
                  walk to classes. Describe the students in each of these sets.
                    a)  AB
                    b)  AB
                    c)  AB
                          −
                    d)  BA
                          −

             2.   Let A = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5}  and B = {0, 3, 6}

                    a)  AB
                    b)  AB
                          −
                    c)  AB
                    d)  BA−

             3.   Let A = {a, b, c, d, e}  and B = {a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h}
                    a)  AB
                    b)  AB
                          −
                    c)  AB
                    d)  BA−

             4.   Prove the domination laws by showing that
                    a)  AU =    U
                          
                    b)  AU =   A
                    c)  A ∅=   A

                    d)  A ∅= ∅

             5.   Prove the complement laws by showing that

                    a)  A  AU=
                    b)  A  A = ∅

             6.   Show that
                    a)  A−∅ =   A
                    b)  ∅−  A = ∅

             7.   Prove the absorption law by showing that if A and B are sets, then

                    a)  A  ( AB =  )  A

                                  )
                              
                    b)  A  ( AB =    A





                                                              73]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[8.   Show that if A, B, and C are sets, then  A BC =  A   B  C
          9.   Let A and B be sets. Show that

                 a)  ( AB ⊆  )  A
                 b)  A ⊆  ( AB  )

                 c)  ( AB−  ) ⊆  A

                 d)  A  (BA−  ) =  ∅
                            −
                 e)  A  (BA =  )  AB
                                    

          10.  Draw the Venn diagrams for each of these combinations of the sets A, B, and C.
                 a)  A  (B C−  )
                                     )
                                 
                 b)  ( A  B   ) ( AC
                 c)  ( A B  ) ( AC    )

                 d)  A   B   C

                 e)  ( A B−  ) ( A C−    ) (B C−    )

          11.  Show that  A⊕  B =  ( AB  ) ( AB−    )

          12.  Show that  A⊕  B =  ( AB−  ) (B −  ) A











































                                                            74]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Section 1.9 − Functions



             Definition

             Let A and B be nonempty sets. A function  f  from A and B is an assignment of exactly one element of B

             to each of A. We write  ( ) a =  if b is the unique element of B assigned by the function  f  to the
                                    f
                                          b
             element a of A. If  f  is a function from A to B, we write  :f A →  B














             When we define a function, we specify its domain, its codomain, and the mapping of elements of the
             domain to elements in the codomain. Two functions are equals when they have the same domain, have
             the same codomain, and map each element of their common domain to the same element in their common
             codomain.


             Example

             What are the domain, codomain, and range of the function that assigns grades to students shown below?












             Solution

                The domain is the set G = {Adams, Chou, Goodfriend, Rodriguez, Stevens}

                The codomain is the set {A, B, C, D, F}
                The range of G is the set {A, B, C, F}

















                                                              75]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Example

                                                                                   2
                                                                           f
          Let  :f   →    assign the square of an integer to this integer. Then  ( ) x =  x , where the domain of  f  is
          the set of all integers, the codomain of  f  is the set of all integers, and the range of  f is the set of all

          integers that are perfect squares, namely, {0, 1, 4, 9,  . . . }


          Definition

          Let  f  and  f  be functions from A to R. Then  f +  f  and  f f  are also functions from A to R defined
               1       2                                 1    2       12
          for all  x∈  by
                    A
              (  f +  1  f 2 )( ) x =  f 1  ( ) x +  f 2  ( ) x

              (  f f  )( ) x =  f 1  ( ) x f 2  ( ) x
                12



          Example

                                                                      2
                                                                                 xx . What are the functions
          Let  f  and  f  be functions from R to R such that   ( ) x =  x  and  f = −  2
                                                            f
               1       2                                     1               2
          f +  f  and  f f ?
           1    2       12
          Solution
              (  f +  1  f 2  )( ) x =  x +  2  ( xx−  2 )  =  x


              (  f f  )( ) x =  x 2 ( x x−  2 )  =  x −  3  x
                                             4
                12


          Definition

          Let  f  be function from A to B and Let S be a subset of A. The image of S under the function  f  is the
          subset of B that consists of the images of the elements of S. We denote the image of S by  ( ) , so
                                                                                                fS
                                         ( ))}
                   ( ) {
                  fS =    t ∃     s∈ S  (  t =  fs

                                       ( )
          We also use the shorthand { fS  s S∈  } to denote this set.













                                                            76]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[One-to-One and Onto Functions

             Definition

                                                                                          ( )  implies that  ab
                                                                                 f
             A function  f  is said to be one-to-one, or an injunction, if and only if  ( ) a =  fb         =
             for all a and b in the domain of  f . A function is said to be injective if it is one-to-one.


             Note:
             A function f is one-to-one (1 – 1) if different inputs have different outputs that is,
                           if   a ≠  b ,     then      ( )f a ≠  f  ( )b


             A function f is one-to-one (1 – 1) if different outputs the same, the inputs are the same – that is,
                           if     ( )f a =  f  ( ),     b  then   a b=


             Remark
                We can express that  f  is one-to-one using the qualifier as  a b f a∀ ∀  (  ( ) =  f  ( ) b → =  ) b  or
                                                                                                a
                                  (
                                                     ( )) , where the universe of disclosure is the domain of the
                equivalently a ba ≠ →       f  ( ) a ≠  f b
                                       b
                            ∀ ∀
                function.


             Example

             Determine whether the function  f  from {a, b, c, d} to {1, 2, 3, 4, 5} with  ( ) a = ,  ( ) = ,  ( ) 1fc = ,
                                                                                     f
                                                                                            4
                                                                                                fb
                                                                                                      5
             and  ( ) 3f d =  is one-to-one.
             Solution

                The function is one-to-one because f takes on different values of the four elements of its domain.














             Example

                                                     2
             Determine whether the function  ( ) x =  x  from  the set of integers to the set of integers is one-to-one.
                                             f
             Solution

                The function is not one-to-one because  ( ) 1f −  =  f  ( ) 1 =  1 but 1≠− 1



                                                              77]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Example

          Determine whether the function  ( ) x = +  from  the set of real numbers to itself is one-to-one.
                                                    1
                                          f
                                                 x
          Solution
                                                   1
             The function is one-to-one because  x +≠ +   1 when  x ≠
                                                       y
                                                                      y


          Definition

          A function f whose domain and codomain are subsets of the set of real numbers is called increasing if
                                                                             y
          f  ( ) x ≤  f  ( ) y , and strictly increasing if  ( ) x <  f  ( ) y , whenever  x <  and x and y are in the domain of
                                                  f
          f.
                                            f
                                                                                   f
          Similarly, f is called decreasing if  ( ) x ≥  f  ( ) y , and strictly increasing if  ( ) x >  f  ( ) y , whenever
              y
          x <  and x and y are in the domain of f. (The word strictly in this definition indicates a strict inequality.)


          Definition

          A function  f  from A to B is called onto, or a surjection, iff for every element bB∈  there is an element
          a∈  with  ( ) a = . A function  f is called surjective if it is onto.
                             b
                      f
              A


          Example

                                                                                     2
                                                                   f
                                                                              fb
          Let  f  be function from {a, b, c, d} to {1, 2, 3} defined by  ( ) a = 3,  ( ) = ,  ( ) 1fc = , and  ( ) 3f d = .
          Is  f  an onto function?
          Solution
             Because all three elements of the codomain are images of elements in the domain, we see that  f  is
             onto.


























                                                            78]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[Example

                                    2
                            f
             Is the function  ( ) x =  x  from  the set of integers to the set of integers onto?
             Solution

                                                                          2
                The function is not onto because there is no integer x with  x = − 1.


             Example

             Is the function  ( ) x = +  from  the set of integers to the set of integers onto?
                            f
                                   x
                                      1
             Solution
                The function is onto because for every integer y there is an integer x such that  ( ) x = .
                                                                                                   y
                                                                                            f
                                                                        y
                                   1
                                       y
                 f  ( ) x =  y iff  x += , which holds if and only if  x = − 1








                                   One-to-One                                     Not One-to-One
                                    Not onto                                            onto










                                   One-to-One                                   Neither One-to-One
                                       onto                                           Nor onto









                                  Not a function










                                                              79]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Definition

          The function  f is one-to-one correspondence, or a bijection, if it is both one-to-one and onto. We say
          also that such a function is bijective.


          Example


          Let  f  be function from {a, b, c, d} to {1, 2, 3, 4} defined by  ( ) a = ,  ( ) = ,  ( ) 1fc = , and
                                                                                       2
                                                                      f
                                                                                fb
                                                                             4
          f  ( ) 3d = . Is  f  a bijection?
          Solution
             The function f is one-to-one and onto.
             It is one-to-one because no two values in the domain are assigned the same function value.
             It is onto because all four elements of the codomain are images of elements in the domain.
             Hence, f is a bijection.



          Inverse Functions and Compositions of Functions

          Definition

          Let  f  be a one-to-one correspondence from the set A to the set B. The inverse function of f  is the

          function that assigns to an element b belonging to B the unique element a in A such that  ( ) a = . The
                                                                                               f
                                                                                                      b
                                                                   a
                                                                            f
          inverse function of f  is denoted by  f  − 1 . Hence,  f  − 1 ( ) b =  when  ( ) a =
                                                                                  b





















          Example

          Let  f  be function from {a, b, c} to {1, 2, 3} defined by  ( ) a = ,  ( ) = , and  ( ) 1fc = . Is  f
                                                                                  3
                                                                 f
                                                                           fb
                                                                        2
          invertible, and if it is, what is its inverse?
          Solution

                                                            80]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[The function  f  is invertible since it is a one-to-one.

                                               c
                The inverse function:  f  − 1 ( ) 1 = , and  f  − 1 ( ) 2 = ,  f  − 1 ( ) 3 =
                                                                             b
                                                                a


             Example

             Let  :f   →    be such that  ( ) x = + . Is  f  invertible, and if it is, what is its inverse?
                                               x
                                                  1
                                        f
             Solution
                The function  f  is invertible since it is a one-to-one.
                 y =  x +  1 ⇒  x =  y −  1

                 f  − 1 ( ) y = − 1
                           y



             Example

                                                 2
                                         f
             Let  :f   →    be such that ( ) x =  x  Is  f  invertible?

             Solution
                The function is not one-to-one. Hence,  f  is not invertible.











































                                                              81]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Composition Functions


          Definition

          Let g be a function from the set A to the set B and let f  be a function from the set B to the set C. The
          composition of the function f and g, denoted for all  a∈  by  f g , is defined by
                                                               A
                                                                   ( ))
                                                  ( f g a =  )( )  ( f ga





























          Example

          Let g be the function from the set {a, b, c} to itself such that  ( ) = ,  ( ) = , and  ( ) = .
                                                                                             gc
                                                                     ga
                                                                            b gb
                                                                                      c
                                                                                                     a
                                                                                                        fc =
                                                                               f
          Let f be the function from the set {a, b, c} to the set {1, 2, 3} such that  ( ) a = 3,  ( ) = , and  ( ) 1
                                                                                                2
                                                                                         fb
          . What is the composition of f and g, and what is the composition of g and f?
          Solution
                                             2
              ( f g a =  )( )  ( f ga  f  ( ) b =
                               ( )) =
                               ( )) =
              ( f g b =  )( )  ( f gb  f  ( ) 1c =
                   )( )
                 
              ( f g c =     ( f gc   f  ( ) 3a =
                               ( )) =
                               ( )) =
              ( g f  )( ) a =  g ( f a  g ( ) 3  ∃ .
             Therefore;  g f   is not defined, because the range of f is not a subset of the domain of g.












                                                            82]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[Example

                                                                                               f
             Let f  and g be the functions from the set of integers to the set of integers defined by  ( ) x =  2x + 3 and
               ( ) 3x=
             gx        +  2. What is the composition of f and g, and what is the composition of g and f?
             Solution

                                  ( ))
                ( f g  )( ) x =  ( f gx
                           =  f  (3x +  ) 2

                           =   ( 2 3x +  ) 2 +  3
                           =  6x +  7

                               (
                                  ( ))
                ( g f  )( ) x =  gf x
                           =  g (2x +  ) 3

                           =  ( 3 2x +  ) 3 +  2

                           =  6x + 11





















































                                                              83]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[Exercises         Section 1.9 − Functions



          1.   Why is f not a function from    to    if
                       ( )
                 a)  f x =   1  ?
                             x
                       ( )
                 b)  f x =    x ?

                 c)  f x =  ( )  ±  x +  2  1 ?

          2.   Determine whether f is a function from   to  if
                       ( )
                 a)  f x = ± ?
                              x
                               2
                       ( )
                 b)  f x =    x + 1 ?
                       ( )
                 c)  f x =     1   ?
                              2
                             x − 4

          3.   Find the domain and range of these functions. Note that in each case, to find the domain, determine
               the set of elements assigned values by the function.
                 a)  The function that assigns to each bit string the number of ones in the string minus the number
                    of zeros in the string.
                 b)  The function that assigns to each bit string twice the number of zeros in that string.
                 c)  The function that assigns the number of bits over when a bit string is split into bytes (which
                    are blocks of 8 bits).

          4.   Determine whether each of these functions from {a, b, c, d} to itself is one-to-one and onto.
                                                     ( ) =
                 a)  f a     ,   ( ) =  , a   f  ( ) c =  , c   f d  d
                       ( ) b   f b=
                 b)  f a     ,   ( ) b  f c=  ,  ( ) =  , d   f d  c
                                                      ( ) =
                       ( ) b  f b=
                       ( )
                                                      ( ) =
                 c)  f a =    , d   f  ( ) b =  , b   f  ( ) c =  , c   f d  d

          5.   Determine whether the function  :f    →    is onto if
                                                    ×
                            )
                 a)  f  ( ,m n = m n+
                                      2
                                 2
                            )
                 b)  f  ( ,m n =  m + n
                            )
                 c)  f  ( ,m n =  m
                            )
                 d)  f  ( ,m n =  n
                            )
                 e)  f  ( ,m n = m n−

          6.   Determine whether each of these functions is a bijection from    → 
                       ( )
                 a)  f x =  2x + 1
                              2
                       ( )
                 b)  f x =  x +  1


                                                            84]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[3
                          ( )
                    c)  f x =  x
                                 2
                          ( )
                    d)  f x =   x + 1
                                 2
                                x + 2
                                5
                          ( )
                    e)  f x =  x + 1

             7.   Suppose that g is a function from A to B and f is a function from B to C.
                    a)  Show that if both f and g are one-to-one functions, then  f g  is also one-to-one.

                    b)  Show that if both f and g are onto functions, then  f g  is also onto.































































                                                              85]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[86]]></page></pages></Search>